We are going to have some lunch comments
here in just a couple minutes. So, those
who are supposed to be speaking, uh,
just get prepared.
Goodbye.
Okay, we are going to get started here.
Um Jay Stanley from the National ACLU
who is uh privacy and security. What's
the title?
And
okay, he leads uh the technology privacy
project. Um he's flown all the way here
from DC and he's going to talk to us
about the ACLU's
uh stance on digital identity and uh
hopefully not going to say he hates what
we're doing.
Thanks Chris. Sorry to interrupt so many
great conversations but this is when
I've been told to speak so you you're
stuck with me. Um again Jay Stanley with
the ACLU. I've been working for a long
time for the ACLU. I started uh n in
and I've been dealing with a a lot of
tech issues since then. Um you know,
things are constantly new, so it keeps
us on our feet. And you know, the ACLU
has always been against a national
identity system. We don't like a
national ID for a lot of reasons. For
one thing, it it it it does take away
your your individual identity and it
makes it a bureaucratic artifact and it
threatens to create a system of tracking
in which government agencies and big
businesses have a unique identifier, a
key that you are stuck with and you
cannot get rid of that will track you
across different areas. If one area, if
one company is tracking you here and one
government agency's tracking you there
and somebody else is tracking you there
and they all have their silos, that is
good for privacy. a national identity
system creates a unique identifier and
we've always so we opposed Real ID um
because it it basically turned our
driver's licenses into a de facto
distributed national identity system.
Now a lot of the bad consequences that
we feared that would come from that have
not materialized. It's sort of a low-key
national identity system that we have a
lot of and but a lot of that is because
it's physical. Um, and what we worry
about, um, with a digital identity is
that it will fully bring forth the
negative potential that Americans across
the political spectrum um, have always
worried about with a national ID system.
And I work on privacy issues. I have
always gotten support from the left and
from the right. I think among all the
issues the ACLU works on, it really is
the the least partisan. Um, and I think
with the national identity issue, in
some ways it is, um, it is the left and
the right against people who aren't
really thinking about it and are just
marching forward. And I think that, you
know, the driver's license started as a
license to drive. You need to you it's
probably in the public interest to
license people who are drivers. Um, but
it has become something much bigger than
that. It's become something much more
central to our society. And as it moves
online, it's going to become much much
bigger. Um and that is the goal of the
dig digital identity pro proponents of
course. Um so um we I you know I I was
ignoring the digital identity issue for
a while because it seemed like nothing
was going to happen and then in around
2001 I wrote a big report because it
seemed like this um MDL thing was really
happening in the states. We were
starting to see a lot of uptake. It was
like okay this is real again. Um and we
were very concerned because it was
created by uh an international group,
the ISO, which included as we know some
big tech companies like Apple and Google
and some government agencies like uh DHS
and AMVA and we don't know who else was
on it. I asked them who else was on the
committee and they refused to tell me.
Um and also you couldn't even see the
standard without paying thousands of
dollars and it was copyrighted. What
kind of a way is that to make public
policy? Maybe that is okay for light
bulb standards or something like that,
but for something that's going to be at
the heart of the relationship between
government and the governed, uh, that
was very dubious. Um, and in fact, the
ISO standard, the MDL standard reflects
the interests of who was at that table,
which is the verifiers. We're going to
do everything possible to make sure that
nobody can ever fool a verifier about
their identity, but it doesn't reflect
the interests of the holders, the people
who are holding the identity, the people
whose identity has been granted to them
by the DMVs. um under this um thing. So
I did a we did a report in 2001 um
called identity crisis um and then over
time me and my colleague who is our
technologist and others refined our
thinking and put out a uh last year a
set of um state legislative
recommendations for state legislators
with proposed language. It's kind of a
work in progress. That's a version one
1.0. We're working on a a second version
now. But the question, you know, we've
been hearing talk all day today, we need
a privacy protecting digital identity
system. We're gonna have digital
identity. It needs to be privacy
protective. Well, when the rubber hits
the road, what does that look like? What
is privacy protective? And that's what
we set out to answer and put some meat
on the bones there. And so this report
basically has 12 items that we think
state legislators should pass and
basically say our state shall not have a
digital identity system unless it has
these technological qualities and comes
with these policy envelopes and
protections because you can't do
everything through technology. Although
we think you should do as much as you
can with technology because it's much
harder to change and to back out of. So
let me just I'm going to I'm going to
mention quickly going to run through the
12 just so you have a flavor. You can
look it up if you're interested in any
of those more. Might highlight one or
two which might be interesting that
people have thought about and then I'm
going to finish with a couple thoughts
and then I'll be done in my in the next
five minutes. Um which is how much time
I have. So one of the big features is no
phone home. If I show my driver's
license to a liquor store clerk, they
look at it. End of story. Nobody's the
wiser. If it's digital, there's the
capability to create a record. And for
in in particular for the issuer, the
DMV, the government or their um their uh
the companies that are their contractors
to see that I've done that and what time
and at what liquor store um and uh and
where everywhere else that I um show my
ID um uh doctor's offices, uh etc., etc.
And it needs to be built without that
feature. There should be no phone home.
We can build it. The ISO standard
allowed for that. um uh and and and and
that is something that we've been
working on. We think that a key privacy
feature is verifier unlinkability. If I
show my digital driver's license at um
six gun shops or six liquor stores or
six doctor's offices, the companies
involved should not be able to first of
all, if I, for example, if I have to
prove I'm over 18 or I'm over 21, they
should just get a binary which um which
a binary bit which says yes, no, this
person's over 21 and it's encrypted and
proofed. Um but there shouldn't be a
unique signature or any other unique
identifier that is passed over as part
of that that can later be used to
correlate all your presentations. Um and
there are there are readily available
cryptographic techniques that can make
that possible and that needs to be a
part of uh of a privacy protecting
digital identity system. New Jersey
which may have outside of Utah the best
um uh digital driver's license law has
this. They say their law says which was
just passed a couple months ago. The
system shall ensure that a digital
driver's license or non-digital license
includes techniques and methodologies
that ensure that multiple presentations
of non-unique data by a holder cannot be
linked together by one or more
verifiers. Um
the uh selective disclosure we think
needs to be mandated that basically you
should have the right to disclose the
minimum amount of data that is necessary
for the for the transaction. You are
over 21, you are not. you are a resident
of the city without sharing your
address. Uh whatever the the use case
may be, people should uh relying parties
verifiers shouldn't get any more than
they need for that transaction. Here's
here's an interesting one and I talked
about this in one of the breakouts.
There shouldn't be a government's kill
switch for your identity. And I think
that's where the philosophical approach
of you know the government endorses your
identity and doesn't create or bestow
upon you your identity. Um but in
bureaucratic sense that's what is
happening in some senses and there is a
real potential that we're going to the
government is going to have a a a
significant power that has never had
before. Three steps. Step one create a
digital identity system. Step two allow
a bunch of dependencies to be built on
that and and some of our proposals are
trying to avoid this so that your
digital identity doesn't become the key
to actually doing your ability to do
anything in life which is a real threat.
um buil build make it make it so you
can't live without the digital identity
system and then because some governor
doesn't like your politics or whatever
pull the rug out from those people
revoke their digital ID and make them an
unperson um and unable to do many things
in society and that is a power a
government has never had before but with
this with a with a central digital
identity becomes a very real possibility
and danger
um we think that uh there should be
verifier accountability you have to
verify yourself to the whatever whoever
wants you to prove something about
yourself, you should have um a verified
identity of who that is and make sure
that you actually are identifying
yourself to who you think you're
identifying yourself with. Um that
hasn't really been implemented. We call
for an open wallet ecosystem so that
people have a choice of wallets. We
think that like forcing people to run
government code on their personal phones
is a bad idea. It should not be
government code. If it is, it should
certainly be open source. Um, but it's
better to have the free market provide
lots of different wallets provided they
meet security standards so that people
can pick whose wallet they want to put
it in whether it's Google's or Samsung's
or Apples or maybe you know Mosilla's or
a privacy protecting group that you have
more trust in um or what have you. Um,
and we call for and one of our biggest
things is restrictions on ID demands.
The real threat here is that once this
infrastructure is created, it makes it
really frictionless to present your ID.
When you go into websites, unless they
really need you to prove ID, they do not
ask you to approve your ID. They're not
going to like make you get a camera and
go in different angles and show your ID.
It's too big an ask. They'll scare away
customers and they know that. But if
they can send you a popup says click
here to send us your digital driver's
license, they will. They'll have a bunch
of incentives to do it for advertising
to make sure you know who you are as
cookies go away potentially. Um for u
security and forensics. And so the real
danger is that we wake up one day, oh,
you want to watch this YouTube video?
Well, just click here to send us your
digital driver's license. You click no,
sorry, we uh we can't. Um it could be
used for um uh surveillance pricing
where companies set their prices for you
based on who you are and everything they
know about you rather than offering the
same price to everybody else. And
there's a lot of abuses there. So, um
let me just I'm running out of time
rapidly. Let me just finish up by saying
that the really important thing here is
is that legislators decide. We have our
12 things that we think are important
parts of privacy. Maybe some people
disagree with we're going to have
disagreements over some of those and the
details and they're complex, but I think
we should all agree that it should be
part of the political process. It should
be legislators who are making these
value judgments. We obviously don't want
legislators getting the nuts and bolts
of technology, but this should be back
in the hands of the legislature. should
not be in the hands of secret
international committee. Uh China and
Russia are on part of the overseeing
committee of the smaller committee. Um
it should not be technologists in the
DMV who are just been told to implement
it who get to make the decisions in the
dark of night. It should not be
unaccountable private organizations like
AMVA. No shade on AVA but they came out
of the old world where it's about
licensing digital driver's licenses and
this is much much bigger than that. I'm
sorry licensing your ability to drive.
This is much bigger than that and it's
it can't be left to a private
organization that asserts copyrights in
its in its policy documents. It won't
let people publish them, let alone not
being subject to the privacy act, FOYA
and so forth, checks and balances on
government. And it should not be the
TSA. The TSA right now because of Real
ID has the power to shape what our
digital identity system looks like. It
should be um legislators and and the
political community. And one of the
things that's really fantastic about
SETI and I think that um you know
there's a bunch of traps and there are
questions and I don't know what it'll
look like as it evolves and what the
ACLU will think of it but I think it's
fantastic that these decisions have
moved from people who are not involved
and are not going to be affected to the
political level which is where it
belongs. Thank you.
We're now going to have Jason Chipman,
director of public policy at Liberatas.
And uh I'll say this, Jason and
Labbertos were heavily involved in
helping to champion and uh and get
really strong privacy protections in
SB260 to make sure um it was going to be
implemented were created correctly and
has to be authorized by the legislature
before the program can actually be
implemented.
Thanks Chris. Um Chris said my name is
Jason Shipman. I'm the uh director of
public policy at the Libertus Institute.
Uh we're a nonprofit think tank based
here in Utah. Um we are probably the
primary voice when it comes to privacy
uh among uh private groups in Utah. Um
one of the things that we did was we
actually helped get Chris a job. Uh we
were very heavily involved in getting
the privacy commission created. So you
owe us one. Don't forget that. Um,
so a couple other things that we've done
in the privacy space. A couple of years
ago, we became the first state in the
nation to require a geoence warrant. If
law enforcement want to use geoence,
they got to have a warrant to do it. We
did that. Uh, two years ago, we became
the first state in the nation to put
guard rails around the use of real-time
surveillance. To my knowledge, we're
still the only state that actually has
that in statute. Um, so this is
something near and dear. This is one of
our core privacy core principles as an
organization among many different
things. Uh, one of the things that I
learned a long time ago was to hire
people that are smarter than you. And
this person that works for me is smarter
than me. And so she wrote this for me
and I'm going to read what she said
before I I give my remarks. So um, as
you know, countries like the UK and the
EU at large are pushing hard to create a
mandatory surveillance regime through
digital IDs. These are intended to trace
every activity, every service, all of
these things that, you know, we've been
uh learning more and more about. Uh we
supported Senate Bill 260 as a vehicle
for rigorously examining the risks and
potential pitfalls of the digital
identity systems, including a study to
probe whether a truly voluntary and
untraceable option is actually feasible
in practice. As the state prioritizes
teen mental health online through
privacy invasive age verification, we
recognize the intent behind exploring
alternatives like SETI. But we have to
be straightforward about it. ID systems,
even innovative approaches like SETI,
amplify government involvement in
identity from static issuance to dynamic
always on oversight that could over time
challenge user autonomy as seen in many
international examples. We appreciate
the legislaturator's commitment guided
by the state's privacy advisory board to
examine these realities through the
study process. We lend our support to
continued research and discussion with a
focus on the high bar of preserving
constitutional protections and
individual freedoms amid these systems
inherent challenges. The most
fundamental reason for our engagement in
Senate Bill 260 is an appreciation for
the study's focus in probing the
tensions between digital ID frameworks
and the privacy and autonomy they seek
to preserve in service of Utah's broader
goals of safeguarding individual
liberty. However, there are some things
that we would like to see changed. Kind
of like the acco said. Uh we want to
require optin for all data beyond
absolute minimum proofs just like they
said. You know, um I can see a a
scenario where you go into an
establishment where you need to show
your ID and all they need is a picture
to prove that you are who you say you
are and your date of birth and they ask
for everything else because they want to
package that off and sell it to data
brokers because it's a way for them to
make money. So, we have to be able to
say no, you can't do that with this. You
know, we have to say that you don't need
that and you don't you cannot require
that for somebody to use your service.
Uh we want to bar government access to
SETI data via thirdparty brokers. This
happens all the time. There was a
presentation in a committee hearing on
Wednesday here in Utah where a
transportation company talked about how
they gathered Bluetooth signals to uh
track traffic patterns in Salt Lake City
over a period of time to determine where
construction was affecting travelers,
you know. And then right after that,
there was another presentation about
population data and how they were
gathering all that. And Representative
Chevier had some very good questions
that went unanswered in that committee
hearing. And uh I will say that those
people who were were speaking at that,
they weren't really happy with her tone
of her tone throughout that after the
hearing. I heard them talking outside.
So that's something you want to follow
up on uh next time you talk to them. We
also want to establish a right of action
against government ages agencies for
violations. Um the easiest way to hold
somebody accountable is make them
accountable. You know, make sure that
they don't do the bad things. Tell them
they're going to go to jail. Tell them
they're going to lose money.
This is something that I proposed when
uh whenever cities try to violate. This
is so I used to be a legislator in
Missouri once upon a time. I'm still
recovering from that.
One of the things that we did as a
legislature was we put a cap on the the
uh amount of fines and fees that cities
could impose on anyone on their
citizens. And if they exceeded that, the
state could take action. Well, one of
those cities no longer exists. We
disinccorporated them and they got
annexed into surrounding cities. Cities
have no constitutional right to do
anything. There's no government agency
that has a constitutional right to
exist. you know, the there's a fallacy
about co-equal branches of government
that that that doesn't exist. That was
made up by President Nixon a long time
ago because well, he was weird. Uh the
fact is the legislature is the supreme
branch of government because it's the
only one that can fire members of the
other two. And we have to remember that
and this is the reason why going through
the legislature for this is so important
and not allowing the agencies to just
kind of do whatever they want. You know,
we're working on a bill this year for
for privacy that doesn't allow law
enforcement to do anything with
surveillance unless the legislature has
already given the go-ahad. So there no
free trials, no demos, no free stuff
from the feds. And then they come back
and say, "Well, sorry, we it's helping
us. We're doing stuff." It's like, "No,
you can't do that." And it provides a
private right of action, removes
qualified immunity, it makes them
accountable for doing things they're not
supposed to do. Uh we also want imp to
impose ironclad bans on unwanted federal
overlays and revocation overreach. You
know state-to-state portability is is a
goal but the federal systems like real
ID expansions to co-op setting without
consent eroding state control. The study
must recommend explicit prohibitions on
such national integrations, preserving
voluntary state cooperation alongside
strict due process requirements for any
endorsement revocation to guard against
escalations of de of centralized power.
So in a nutshell, we are very much in
favor of the study. It's going to show
us what we can do. It's also going to
show us what's going on that we should
be worried about. You know, this is very
much one of those things where we're
trying to shove a camel through an eye
of a needle. And if they can't figure
out a way to do it, we need to slaughter
the camel and burn it to the ground.
That's essentially going to be our
stance. This is good until it's not. And
once it's not, we're coming full guns
ablazing at you, you know. So, we we've
shown that we have been effective in in
some of our other endeavors in the
state. And I'm hopeful that I hope this
works out, you know. I'm not going to
lie. I hope it works out. I got five
kids. My oldest is 16. I worry about
what could happen to them. You know, as
a legislator, I've heard all of the
horror stories from my constituents
about my kids doing this. Can you do
something? Can you know something
happened? Can you do something? You
know, sometimes government does need to
do something. Sometimes they don't, you
know, but uh legislators, having been
one of them, often feel like they have
to do something and sometimes the best
thing they can do is nothing. But I
really do hope this can work out the way
we want to. But if it's not, you know,
somebody has to be held accountable and
we have to be able to just say it's not
going to work. You know, we don't have,
you know, and remember that other
people, other organizations have
different incentives.
And so until they realize that our
constitutional rights are the primary
incentive and nothing else really has
matters in the situation, you know,
we're not going to be able to be
successful at this. So, I'm hoping that
Chris and his team and this process will
lay out all of the pros and cons, all
the things we can do, all the things we
shouldn't do, you know, so it lets
everybody know ahead of time kind of
what we're getting into. Thank you very
much.
You have to admit we've brought a
diverse group of opinions today and as
Governor Cox has said, we we do know how
to disagree better in Utah and um I
assure you I have not slept well for
four years balancing all of these
different requirements, but we're doing
a good job. Um I am really excited to
announce the next person who's going to
address us, Jeremy Grant. So he's
managing director in Venable uh
Venable's LLP technology and innovation
practice, but I think most interestingly
and most importantly, he coordinates the
better identity coalition and has been
working in the space for decades and is
going to be an extremely valuable member
as we move forward to learn how to work
with those he represents. Thanks,
Jeremy.
Hey, thank you Chris for the invitation
to come out and great meeting so many of
you today and also seeing a few old
friends. Uh so better identity coalition
I just want to say from the start we're
really thrilled to see this today and
that if there is one thing we have been
consistently calling for since the
coalition was first formed in 2018 and
published our initial policy blueprint
it's that as a country and in individual
states. We need to be thinking about
this constructively and strategically.
We have not had a strategy for digital
identity in the US that outlines what
good looks like and how to get there or
for that matter what the bad outcomes
could look like and how to avoid them
since the last time we had a strategy
was one that I ran. It was an Obama
administration initiative that was
launched in 2011 that was called the
national strategy for trusted identities
in cyerspace. And there were some things
that worked well in that program and
some things that didn't. But I think one
thing that everybody should take away is
that for the last 10 years as our peers
across the globe are all thinking about
identity different ways and they're
thinking about it strategically we've
been take tackling it really on sort of
a siloed approach something for age
verification something for government
login something perhaps for KYC for
banks but there hasn't been a holistic
approach and so this is what we've been
some cases I would say begging policy
makers to take on and so seeing uh what
Utah's done and you know other so many
officials today from governor's offices
and state legislatores and other states.
It's awesome to see uh in terms of who
we are. So, you know, I mentioned my my
time running the the NStick initiative.
I was also dualheaded as the guy who led
the digital identity research and
standards team uh at NIST uh in uh the
DC area and helped launch the privacy
engineering team around identity uh that
still does a lot of great projects today
on that front. The coalition is an
interesting group. Uh so we've got big
tech giants that some of whom people
have been calling into question what
they want today. So Apple's a member,
Google, Microsoft. We also have
companies that help pioneered or led
efforts in decentralized or self-s
sovereign identity. Companies like uh
Gen Digital or Block. The C uh
coalition's really driven however by
those that I would say are on the buy
side of identity. Our origin story was
was around this time eight years ago.
There was a little breach that happened
that wasn't in the news at all from a
company called Equifax where uh they
lost 141 million social security numbers
and it also raised some bigger concerns
around identity in that the default way
we would prove who we were online say to
open a bank account or apply for a
government service was to use
knowledgebased verification. Here's five
questions from your credit report or you
can answer them. It must be you. Well,
we all know that hasn't been true for a
long time given all the breaches we've
had. And so we were largely founded by
the buyers of identity who just need
better solutions to run their
businesses. So think companies in
banking, payments, fintech, healthcare,
telecom. We have some of the vendors at
the table as well, but it's a you know
pretty mly assortment and the companies
probably don't agree on much other than
we should be thinking about digital
identity strategically. Um, I called Jay
in 2021 when he published his uh paper,
which is a great read by the way, on the
risks of digital ID, uh, because he
talked a lot about the shadowy identity
industrial complex that was pushing for
things like mobile driver's licenses.
And I said, I think I'm running that.
But the good news is we mostly agree
with you on the issues that are in the
paper. uh we actually think they did an
amazing job at highlighting the risks to
digital ID along with you know potential
decisions in terms of architecture or
policy on how you could uh you know be
designing things like MDLs. Uh there's
you know Wayne was uh Chang was
mentioning before the great work that's
happening at NIST right now through
their national cyber security center of
excellence to come up with a family of
standards and or playbook of standards
and best practices to help states
including you know the folks who are
here set a high bar for security and
privacy and ensure interoperability.
Five states are participating alongside
Apple and Google and seven banks and a
lot of other big players right now. It's
a great example of how you can actually
get interest from all across the board
to collaborate on, you know, achieving
good outcomes here. So, you know, we're
out there, you know, quite a bit
sometimes excited about MDLs, not
because we think the DMVs are the most
awesome place for identity to be uh
housed, but it is at the end of the day
the one place that most adult Americans
go through and prove who they are in
person to get either a driver's license
or a non-driver state ID card. And so we
think as we look to get away from
companies who are basically trying to
hoover up a bunch of data on us and
guess who we are. Look, I live in DC. I
went to the DMV 3 years ago to get my
Real ID driver's license. It was not a
pleasant experience. I've gone through a
similar process with the post office at
the to get a uh who partners with the
State Department to issue passports. If
I'm trying to open an account online and
there's a legal or regulatory
requirement that they need to know who I
am, why can't I ask the DMV or the state
department to vouch for me? That idea
that we should start to give people the
ability to ask government to provide
this to them as a service in a way that
actually is secure and privacy
enhancing, that's really what we're
calling for. So, I mentioned before uh
we published a policy blueprint at the
end of 2022. We published one
specifically for state policy makers. I
hold a bunch of them over in my suitcase
this morning and they're in a stack
downstairs if you'd like to grab one.
But I think my my final message would be
for those of you who are engaging uh on
the policy side of this uh we'd love to
work with you. So please don't be shy
about reaching out. Uh you know our goal
look the reason our members are all
funding this effort is because they want
to have an organization that can engage
and collaborate constructively on
getting these issues uh thought through
properly and you know get good outcomes
for everybody. So appreciate the invite
again and look forward to talking to
you. Thank you.
We are next going to hear from Christian
Riza who's from the he's the Utah
chapter president of Stand with Crypto.
And for those who aren't aware, uh the
crypto enthusiasts I think are pretty
excited about the decentralized identity
approach. Um, and the Utah Blockchain
Association has gone way out of their
way to bring together stakeholders and
even many in this room that they've been
working with for years to help educate
them on SETI and and bring their support
to help make this happen. Christian,
so I do I represent Stand with Crypto. I
am the uh chapter president for the
state of Utah. Um, and it's my repres
It's my responsibility to represent the
20,000 pro- crypto voters in the state
of Utah. Um, and mobilize them on
initiatives that really align with our
values. Um, now you're probably
thinking, okay, crypto, that has nothing
to do with SETI. Cryptocurrency has
nothing to do with SETI. Why, you know,
why are you here? What does this matter?
um
you know, our our assets, our finances
and our assets have been digital for
years. We've just never had the ability
to to take ownership, to take custody
and and to have those in our control. Um
and likewise, our birth certificates,
our social security numbers, all of
these things are already digital. They
live in a in a database somewhere. we've
just never had the ability to have true
ownership and custody over those over
those pieces of our identity. Um
recently I had the opportunity to go to
our community and really ask them and
have some honest discussions and a bunch
of different um chats throughout the
state. And uh you know all these people,
the crypto and blockchain people are
extreme skeptics um when it comes to
this kind of stuff because frankly you
know all they know is we want to have
control over our assets, our finances,
all these things. We we don't want the
government involved in these things,
right? So at first gut reaction of hey
guys what do you think of this
initiative? It was no. No. What? No.
Please don't do it. What are you talking
about? Like no. This is terrible. And
what I did was had everybody actually
dig in. And uh Will Seos as well, which
is he's here. We had some conversations
in deep in-depth conversations with a
lot of these community members and had
them really dig into the underlying
protocols. They're technical people,
right? Um, and after having reviewed the
information and the framework and how
it's being proposed, it was an emphatic
yes.
And I can I've got some quotes here from
some of these people, which in this
case, it seems great. It seems too good
to be true. I'm surprised the state is
backing this.
Definitely the best approach that I've
seen. This actually makes sense. I like
it. There's no way the state of Utah
would go for it.
And my favorite one, if the state of
Utah did this, I would be proud.
Um, I'm not a policy maker. Um, I don't
come from uh, you know, I'm not I'm not
here representing a a big tech
enterprise or anything like that. Um,
you know, these people that we represent
are just people. you know, they're
regular Joe's, regular community
members, and like they deeply care about
um their privacy, their control, their
ability to hold these different things,
parts of their lives, their identity,
their assets, and these things. uh they
deeply care about these issues and um
based on the SETI framework some of the
things that ACL ACLU has said um
you know the way that SETI is structured
and framed today the community
emphatically wants to support this um
and so I guess I'm here to say that uh
you know as a community member as a uh
person that represents people in the
community uh you know if you move
forward with SETI in this way the state
of Utah and other states that are here
uh represented that um we'll we'll
support that and um and we hope that you
that you will. So, thank you.
Before our next speaker, I'm going to
make one comment. Uh a lot of people
don't know this, and I'm not going to
say which company. We have had the first
company that is now reinccorporating in
Utah because of what we're doing with
SETI. I'm not going to say what state
they're leaving from. Um, but this is a
valuable economic
uh uh it's it's it's a value ad. People
will come to your state because they
want privacy. People are crazying uh
craving this type of freedom. So, you
can think about that. What is it that
this offers that other states or other
countries can't offer? and it really
will be an export, but it's going to
attract people to your state. And I
think for all of you, the message is
resounding. This is something people
want. We just have to work through and
figure out how we're going to get there.
All right, the last comments we are
going to hear from, I think this is
probably the the coolest person we have
in attendance today. So, we have Scott
Sternetta, uh, co-inventor of the
blockchain and mentioned in the Satoshi
paper for Bitcoin.
Sorry, where do we have Scott? Oh, right
here in front.
I think Stuart, my co-inventor, is
actually the coolest person here. But,
um, I'm Scott Stoetta and I speak for
the trees. Actually, not. I just for
years wanted a situation because I'm
such a Dr. Seuss fan to be able to give
that line, but whatever.
I am grateful for the opportunity to
speak briefly.
Uh by way of introduction, Dr. Haber and
I began an effort more than 30 years ago
at Bell Communications Research, part of
the old Bell Labs family. As research
scientists, we published an influential
paper outlining a method to create
immutable digital records through widely
witnessed public events
made through widely witnessed events
made public. This is what we now call a
blockchain.
While I don't endorse any specific
cryptocurrency
or blockchain application, the data
integrity mechanisms that Stuart and I
pioneered
have proven reliable and they now
safeguard over $3 trillion in digital
assets. That's trillion with a T.
What does this have to do with identity?
Well, let me address it first
philosophically and then technically.
Philosophically, the SETI initiative
holds that a person's digital identity
is an inherent human right in the
digital age created and controlled by
the individual.
Yet, as Lach and Rouso
argued, individuals choose to enter a
social contract with a community
governed by the state. This creates a
need to link personal identity with
state requirements. Hence the concept of
state endorsed digital identity.
Technical technically this aligns very
well with the principles Stuart and I
used to construct the blockchain to
build trust in immutable records without
relying on any single third party. We
spread the trust mechanism across the
user community. This is what is now
commonly described as the principle of
decentralization.
Similarly, decentralizing digital
identity, keeping it under individual
control
well reflects the enable the inalienable
rights.
You know, they wanted to correct Thomas
Jefferson and call those unalienable
rights, but
uh Virginia prevailed on that one.
Inalienable rights articulated in
America's Declaration of Independence
and echoed in many Declarations of Human
Rights both in Europe and in varying
degrees throughout the world. I must
emphasize
that I did not participate in any of the
work leading to this summit. So I'm
offering an outsers's perspective. Born
in Maryland and a New Jersey resident
for over 30 years, my view is not Utah
ccentric. Though I do confess my wife is
from Ogden and Dr. Haber similarly
confesses that he has at least flown
over the state in route from New York to
California many times.
Okay. Point is, we've been entirely
external to the process, the
legislation, and the technical details.
With that said, I endorse this effort.
Not because I agree with every part of
the legislation or descriptions,
because no initiative is perfect at
birth, and this one is evolving. I
invite you to listen to a later speaker
today, Scott Kelly, who will talk about
the word iterative.
I'm a fan of it. But we shouldn't let
the perfect be the enemy to the good.
And so I invite you, especially those
from other states,
to join this cause,
not because it's flawless, but because
your involvement can refine it. Not
because you fully agree. Polics.
Politics is the art of the possible and
it often requires compromise but not
compromise of principle.
But because good people united at a good
cause can achieve more together.
I close with a unifying phrase from late
17th century Europe originally in Latin
but I will spare that part.
In necessary things, unity,
in undecided things, liberty,
and in all things, charity. If we're
guided by this principle, I'm confident
that we collectively can achieve
something of value to many, many people
across the world. Thank you.
Okay, that concludes our lunch. We are
going to now move downstairs back into
the atrium we first met with and we will
continue from there. So, if you could
please start moving downstairs.