Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
you. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
Thank you. Thank you.
through the legislature for this is so
important and not allowing the agencies to
just kind of do whatever they want. You
know, we're working on a bill this year
for privacy that doesn't allow law
enforcement to do anything with
surveillance unless the legislature has
already given the go-ahead. So there are
no free trials, no demos, no free stuff
from the feds, and then they come back and
say, well, sorry, it's helping us. We're
doing stuff. It's like, no, you can't do
that. And it provides a private right of
action, removes qualified immunity. It
makes them accountable for doing things
they're not supposed to do. We also want
to impose ironclad bans on unwanted
federal overlays and revocation overreach.
You know, state-to-state portability is a
goal, but the federal systems like RealID
expansions to co-op SEDI without consent
eroding state control. The study must
recommend explicit prohibitions on such
national integrations preserving voluntary
state cooperation alongside strict due
process requirements for any endorsement
revocation to guard against escalation to
guard against escalations of centralized
power. So, in a nutshell, we are very much
in favor of the study. It's going to show
us what we can do. It's also going to show
us what's going on that we should be
worried about. You know, this is very much
one of those things where we're trying to
shove a camel through an eye of a needle
and if they can't figure out a way to do
it, we need to slaughter the camel and
burn it to the ground. That's essentially
going to be our stance. This is good until
it's not. And once it's not, we're coming
full guns a blazing at you. You know, so
we've shown that we have been effective in
some of our other endeavors in the state
and I'm hopeful that I hope this works
out. You know, I'm not going to lie. I
hope it works out. I got five kids. My
oldest is 16. I worry about what could
happen to them. You know, as a legislator,
I've heard all of the horror stories from
my constituents about my kids doing this.
Can you do something? Can you know,
something happen? Can you do something?
You know, sometimes government does need
to do something. Sometimes they don't, you
know, but legislators having been one of
them often feel like they have to do
something and sometimes the best thing
they can do is nothing. But I really do
hope this can work out the way we want to.
But if it's not, you know, somebody has to
be held accountable and we have to be able
to just say it's not going to work. You
know, we don't have, you know, and
remember that other people, other
organizations have different incentives.
And so until they realize that our
constitutional rights are the primary
incentive and nothing else really matters
in the situation, you know, we're not
going to be able to be successful at this.
So I'm hoping that Chris and his team and
this process will lay out all of the pros
and cons, all the things we can do, all
the things we shouldn't do, you know, so
it lets everybody know ahead of time kind
of what we're getting into. Thank you very
much.
You have to admit we've brought a diverse
group of opinions today. And as Governor
Cox has said, we do know how to disagree
better in Utah. And I assure you, I have
not slept well for four years balancing
all of these different requirements, but
we're doing a good job. I am really
excited to announce the next person who's
going to address us, Jeremy Grant. So he's
managing director in Venable, Venable's
LLP technology and innovation practice.
But I think most interestingly and most
importantly, he coordinates the Better
Identity Coalition and has been working in
the space for decades and is going to be
an extremely valuable member as we move
forward to learn how to work with those he
represents. Thanks, Jeremy. Hey, thank
you, Chris, for the invitation to come out
and great meeting so many of you today and
also seeing a few old friends. So Better
Identity Coalition. I just want to say
from the start, we're really thrilled to
see this today. And then if there is one
thing we have been consistently calling
for since the coalition was first formed
in 2018 and published our initial policy
blueprint, it's that as a country and an
individual state, we need to be thinking
about this constructively and
strategically. We have not had a strategy
for digital identity in the US that
outlines what good looks like and how to
get there or for that matter what the bad
outcomes could look like and how to avoid
them since is the last time we had a
strategy was the last time we had a
strategy was one that I ran. It was an
Obama administration initiative that was
launched in 2011 that was called the
National Strategy for Trusted Identities
in Cyberspace. And there were some things
that worked well in that program and some
things that didn't. But I think one thing
that everybody should take away is that
for the last 10 years as our peers across
the globe are all thinking about identity
different ways and they're thinking about
it strategically, we've been tackling it
really on sort of a siloed approach,
something for age verification, something
for government login, something perhaps
for KYC, for banks, but there hasn't been
a holistic approach. And so this is what
we've been in some cases I would say
begging policymakers to take on. And so
seeing what Utah has done and other so
many officials today from governor's
offices and state legislatures and other
states, it's awesome to see. In terms of
who we are, so I mentioned my time running
the NSTIC initiative. I was also dual
-hatted as the guy who led the digital
identity research and standards team at
NIST in the DC area and helped launch the
DC area and helped launch the privacy
engineering team around identity that
still does a lot of great projects today
on that front. The coalition's an
interesting group. So we've got big tech
giants that some of whom people have been
calling into question what they want
today. So Apple's a member of Google,
Microsoft. We also have companies that
help pioneered or led efforts in
decentralized or self-sovereign identity
companies like Gen Digital or Block. The
coalition's really driven, however, by
those that I would say are on the buy side
of the identity. Our origin story was
around this time eight years ago. There
was a little breach that happened that
wasn't in the news at all from a company
called Equifax where they lost 141 million
social security numbers and it also raised
some bigger concerns around identity in
that the default way we would prove who we
were online, say to open a bank account to
apply for a government service, was to use
knowledge-based verification. Here's five
questions from your credit report or you
can answer them. It must be you. Well, we
all know that hasn't been true for a long
time given all the breaches we've had. And
so we were largely founded by the buyers
of identity who just need better solutions
to run their businesses. So think
companies in banking, payments, fintech,
healthcare, telecom. We have some of the
vendors at the table as well, but it's a
pretty motley assortment and the companies
probably don't agree on much other than we
should be thinking about digital identity
strategically. I called Jay in 2021 when
he published his paper, which is a great
read by the way on the risks of digital ID
because he talked a lot about digital
identity about the shadowy identity
industrial complex that was pushing for
things like mobile drivers licenses. And I
said, I think I'm running that. But the
good news is we mostly agree with you on
the issues that are in the paper. We
actually think they did an amazing job at
highlighting the risks to digital ID along
with potential decisions in terms of
architecture or policy on how you could be
designing things like MDLs. There's Wayne
was, Chang was mentioning before the great
work that's happening at NIST right now
through their International Cybersecurity
Center of International Cybersecurity
Center of Excellence to come up with a
family of standards and our playbook of
standards and best practices to help
states including the folks who are here
set a high bar for security and privacy
and ensure interoperability. Five states
are participating alongside Apple and
Google and seven banks and a lot of other
big players right now. It's a great
example of how you can actually get
interest from all across the board to
collaborate on achieving good outcomes
here. So we're out there quite a bit
sometimes excited about MDLs not because
we think the DMVs are the most awesome
place for identity to be housed. But it is
at the end of the day the one place that
most adult Americans go through and prove
who they are in person to get either a
driver's license or a non-driver state ID
card. And so we think as we look to get
away from companies who are basically
trying to hoover up a bunch of data on us
and guess who we are. Look, I live in DC.
I went to the DMV three years ago to get
my real ID driver's license. It was not a
pleasant experience. I've gone through a
similar process with the post office to
get a who partners with the state
department to issue passports. If I'm
trying to open an account online and
there's a legal or regulatory requirement
that they need to know who I am, why can't
I ask the DMV or the state department to
vouch for me? That idea that we should
start to give people the ability to ask
government to provide this to them as a
service in a way that actually is secure
and privacy enhancing, that's really what
we're calling for. So I mentioned before
we published a policy blueprint at the end
of 2022. We published one specifically for
state policymakers. I hauled a bunch of
them over in my suitcase this morning and
they're in a stack downstairs if you'd
like to grab one. But I think my final
message would be for those of you who are
engaging on the policy side of this, we'd
love to work with you. So please don't be
shy about reaching out. You know, our
goal, look, the reason our members are all
funding this effort is because they want
to have an organization that can engage
and collaborate constructively on getting
these issues thought through properly and
you know, get good outcomes for everybody.
So appreciate the invite again and look
forward to talking to you. Thank you.
We are next going to hear from Christian
Riza, who's from the he's the Utah chapter
president of Stand with Crypto. And for
those who aren't aware, the crypto
enthusiasts I think are pretty excited
about the decentralized identity approach.
And the Utah Blockchain Association has
gone way out of way out of way out of way
to bring together stakeholders and even
many in this room that they've been
working with for years to help educate
them on SEDI and bring their support to
help make this happen. So Christian.
So I do I represent Stand with Crypto. I
am the chapter president for the state of
Utah. And it's my it's my responsibility
to represent the 20,000 pro crypto voters
in the 20,000 pro crypto voters in the
state of Utah and mobilize them on
initiatives that really align with our
values. Now you're probably thinking,
okay, crypto that has nothing to do with
SEDI. Cryptocurrency has nothing to do
with SEDI. Why, you know, why are you
here? What does this matter? You know, our
assets, our finances and our assets have
been digital for years. We've just never
had the ability to take ownership, to take
custody and to have those those in our
control. And likewise, our birth
certificates, our social security numbers,
all of these things are already digital.
They live in a in a database somewhere.
We've just never had the ability to have
true ownership and custody over those over
those pieces of our identity. Recently, I
had the opportunity to go to our community
and really ask them and have some honest
discussions and a bunch of different chats
throughout the state. And, you know, all
of these people, the crypto and blockchain
people are extreme skeptics when it comes
to this kind of stuff because frankly, you
know, all they know is we want to have
control over our assets, our finances, all
of these things. We don't want the
government involved in these things,
right? So at first gut reaction of, hey
guys, what do you think of this
initiative? It was, no, no, what? No,
please don't do it. What are you talking
about? Like, no, this is terrible. Like,
no, this is terrible. And what I did was
had everybody actually dig in and Will
Segos as well, which is he's here. We had
some conversations in deep, in-depth
conversations with a lot of these
community members and had them really dig
into the underlying protocols. They're
technical people, right? And after having
reviewed the information and the framework
and how it's being proposed, it was an
emphatic yes. And I I've got some quotes
here from some of these people, which in
this case, it seems great. It seems too
good to be true. I'm surprised the state
is backing this. Definitely the best
approach that I've seen, this actually
makes sense. I like it. There's no way the
state of Utah would go for it. And my
favorite one, if the state of Utah did
this, I would be proud. I'm not a
policymaker. I'm not a policymaker. I
don't come from, you know, I'm not here
representing a big tech enterprise or
anything like that. You know, these people
that we represent are just people, you
know, they're regular Joes, regular
community members, and like they deeply
care about their privacy, their control,
their ability to hold these different
things, parts of their lives, their
identity, their assets, and these things.
They deeply care about these issues. And
based on the SEDI framework, some of the
things that ACLU has said, you know, the
way that SEDI is structured and framed
today, the community emphatically wants to
support this. And so I guess I'm here to
say that, you know, as a community member,
as a person that represents people in the
community, you know, if you move forward
with SEDI in this way, the state of Utah
and other states that are here represented
that will support that. And we hope that
you will. So thank you.
Before our next speaker, I'm going to make
one comment. A lot of people don't know
this. And I'm not going to say which
company. We have had the first company
that is now reincorporating in Utah
because of what we're doing with SEDI. I'm
not going to say what state they're
leaving from. But this is a valuable
economic, it's a value add. People will
come to your state because they want
privacy. People are craving this type of
freedom. So you can think about that. What
is it that this offers that other states
or other countries can offer? And it
really will be an export, but it's going
to attract people to your state. And I
think for all of you, the message is
resounding. This is something people want.
We just have to work through and figure
out how we're going to get there. All
right. The last comments we are going to
hear from. I think this is probably the
coolest person we have in attendance
today. So we have Scott Stornetta, co
-inventor of the blockchain and mentioned
in the Satoshi paper for Bitcoin. Sorry,
where do we have Scott? Oh, right here in
front. I think
Stuart, my co-inventor is actually the
coolest person here. I'm Scott Stornetta.
I'm Scott Stornetta. I'm Scott Stornetta
and I speak for the trees. Actually not. I
just for years wanted a situation because
I'm such a Dr. Seuss fan to be able to
give that line, but whatever. I am
grateful for the opportunity to speak
briefly.
By way of introduction, Dr. Haber and I
began an effort more than 30 years ago at
Bell Communications Research, part of the
old Bell Labs family. As research
scientist, we published an influential
paper outlining a method to create
immutable digital records through widely
witnessed public events made through
widely witnessed events made public. This
is what we now call a blockchain. While I
don't endorse any specific cryptocurrency
or blockchain application, the data
integrity mechanisms that Stuart and I
pioneered have proven reliable and
reliable and reliable and reliable and
reliable and they now safeguard over $3
trillion in digital assets. That's
trillion with a T. What does this have to
do with identity? Well, let me address it
first philosophically and then
technically. Philosophically, the SEDI
initiative holds that a person's digital
identity is an inherent human right in the
digital age created and controlled by the
individual. Yet, as Locke and Rousseau.
Yet, as Locke and Rousseau argued,
individuals choose to enter a social
contract with a community governed by the
state. This creates a need to link
personal identity with state requirements,
hence the concept of state-endorsed
digital identity. Technically, this aligns
very well with the principles Stuart and I
use to construct the blockchain. To build
trust in immutable records without
immutable records without relying on any
single third party, we spread the trust
mechanism across the user community. This
is what is now commonly described as the
principle of decentralization. Similarly,
decentralizing digital identity, keeping
it under individual control, well reflects
the inalienable rights You know, they
wanted to correct Thomas Jefferson and
call those unalienable rights. But
Virginia prevailed on that one.
Inalienable rights articulated in
America's Declaration of Independence and
echoed in many declarations of human
rights both in Europe and in varying
degrees throughout the world. I must
emphasize that I did not participate in
any of the work leading to this summit. So
I'm offering an outstanding outsider's
perspective. Born in Maryland and a New
Jersey resident for over 30 years. My view
is not Utah-centric. Though I do confess
my wife is from Ogden and Dr. Haber
similarly confesses that he has at least
flown over the state in route from New
York to California many times. Okay? Point
is we've been entirely external to the
process, the legislation, and the
technical details. With that said, I
endorse this effort. Not because I agree
with every part of the legislation or
descriptions. Because no initiative is
perfect at birth. And this one is
evolving. I invite you to listen to a
later speaker today, Scott Kelly, who will
talk about the word iterative. I'm a fan
of it. But we shouldn't let the perfect be
the enemy to the good. And so I invite
you, especially those from other states,
to join this cause. To join this cause.
Not because it's flawless, but because
your involvement can refine it. Not
because you fully agree politics is the
art of the possible. And it often requires
compromise, but not compromise of
principle. But because good people united
in a good cause can achieve more together.
I close with a unifying phrase from late
17th century Europe, but I will spare you
that part. In necessary things, unity. In
undecided things, liberty. And in all
things, charity. If we're guided by this
principle, I'm confident that we
collectively can achieve something of
value to many, many people across the
world. the world. Thank you.
Okay. That concludes our lunch. We are
going to now move downstairs back into the
atrium we first met with and we will
continue from there. So if you could
please start moving downstairs.
!
Male Speaker 2-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1
-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1
-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1-1 Thank you.