testing.
Okay.
All right, we are going to go ahead and
get started.
Can have everyone take their seats.
All right, I want to thank everyone for
coming here today to Utah. Uh, you've
lucked out. We have some snow in the
mountains, so you've missed the fall
colors, and now we're into the next
season. Um, my name is Chris Bramwell.
I'm Utah's chief privacy officer,
director of Utah's Office of Data
Privacy, located in the Department of
Government Operations. Um, I want to
thank the Herbert Institute of Public
Policy, uh, the Department of Government
Operations, and the Utah Legislature for
all helping, uh, to host this event, and
also to UVU for allowing us to use their
facilities. Um, I also want to thank
UVU. We had uh, many employees and
students and interns helped to bring
this event together for the last few
months, and so we couldn't do this
without the work that they've been
putting in.
And I want to thank all of you for
coming to Utah to participate in this
event. We put a lot of thought into how
would we actually host an event to cause
change and um we thought about just
doing a virtual event and we knew that
it's going to take a lot of passion and
a lot of work to pull off what we're
going to be proposing today. So it was
important to see who can we get to come
in person that cares the most about it
to help us build what we are going to be
proposing. So I thank all of you from
coming for coming uh those from states
we have 12 states represented um those
from academia those from from um
executive branch agencies those from
legislators uh I think we have more than
a dozen companies represented we have
concerned citizens we have private
interest groups we have the national
ACLU so we have the start of what I
think is going to be a really great
consortium
Now the purpose of today is simple. We
invited you all to come here to one
receive an education about a very
complex topic is digital identity.
The second reason we've invited you is
to help help you understand the problem
and what we think is a really big
opportunity for America to lead out. And
the third and final reason that we've
invited you here today is to actually
invite you to join the SETI consortium,
the state endorsed digital identity
consortium, so that we can move forward
and work together on what we think is a
big opportunity for America.
Now, I am an optimist by nature and I'm
very optimistic about digital identity
if we do it right. And I believe that we
can build technology that reflects
American values, that protects freedoms
and strengthens families and builds
trust in the digital world. But I am
also a realist about why this effort is
needed. I am very concerned about some
of what I see happening not just in the
United States, but what is happening
around the world. There are many of you
in this room that have expressed those
same concerns. That is why
Representative Cutler and Senator
Kylemore sponsored Senate Bill 260 this
last session, the first state endorsed
digital identity bill in the na in the
nation to begin addressing these
concerns. So I want to share with you
some of our concerns. I am concerned for
my kids and your kids who can engage
online in video games and social media
and they do not know and we do not know
if the people they are engaging with are
actually who they say they are. I am
concerned for my and your elderly
parents and grandparents who continue to
be taken advant advantage of by
individuals pretending to be family
members in distress.
I am concerned for young men facing
exploitation and sextortion online.
This is one of the fastest growing
crimes in America and in Utah facing our
young men. They are being driven to
despair and even suicide in a world
where anonymity and manipulation coexist
without protection.
I am concerned that fraud enabled by
identity theft and impersonation is now
costing the United States hundreds of
billions of dollars a year.
I am concerned that algorithms based on
profiling and scoring are influencing
our behavior and quietly shaping the
concept of even freedom and free agency.
I am concerned that the free market is
being distorted, that those who control
personal data are facilitating
monopolistic behavior that maximizes
exploitation of individuals for profit
instead of driving a free market based
off of competition and best prices.
I am concerned that nation state attacks
on future digital digital identity
systems will occur and we have to assume
digital identity will be compromised.
I am concerned that government sponsored
digital identity systems both in the
United States and around the world have
been created that are capable of
tracking, surveilling and controlling.
I am concerned that governments,
corporations, and technologists are
rushing to create digital identity
systems that are compulsory and are
required and that these are being
created without the comprehensive
governance frameworks and protections
needed to protect individual rights.
And I am most concerned that in
democracies around the world, digital
identity systems are being designed and
implemented in ways contrary to the
first principles of America's founding.
And that is that individuals have
individual inalable rights that they are
endowed with that is innate to them
including identity. Government does not
give identity. Government does not
create identity and any identity system
built on the premise that government is
giving it to you means that they can
also take it away which is an opposition
to this founding principle.
So the truth is there is no trust in the
digital world today. We don't know who
or what is real. We do not know.
You do not control your digital
identity. Usernames, passwords, even
mobile driver's license can be taken
away. They can be compromised. There is
currently no national strategy for
digital identity. And we know that there
are many both foreign and abroad who
would love to control your digital
identity and compromise it for their own
gains. So the dile dilemma before us is
that if we do nothing, we will be left
with a system created by others that do
not share our same values. But this is
not the end of the story. It is the
reason that we are here. All of us in
this room are in a position to
influence. Some of you have the power to
create laws. Some of you have the power
to create and dictate public policy.
Some of you have the power to create
technology. Some of you have the power
to fund new businesses to create the
solutions that we need. Some of you have
the power to create governance
frameworks and some of you have the
power to create standards and some of
you just have the power to raise your
concerns and create trouble for the rest
of us which we need. So you all have
something to contribute that is needed
to create the solution necessary to
address our concerns and create a better
digital identity. So there is a path a
path forward by building digital
identity in a manner that prioritizes
rights and dignity. This is what state
endorsed digital identity is all about.
So I want you to imagine for a minute a
future a future 10 years from now after
we've put in a lot of hard work. We need
to agree today and in future summits
what that work is going to be. But a
future where our fears about digital
identity theft, manipulation,
impersonation, exploitation, loss of
control have been by been replaced by
trust and authenticity. Where parents
know their children are safe online.
Where our elderly are protected from
scams and impersonation.
Where there is trust that government is
protecting your digital identity and
rights above all other interests.
That is the world we need all of you to
help create. So through the SETI
consortium that we are proposing and
inviting you to join today, states will
work together to define an American
model for digital identity, one that
protects citizens. And instead of
importing surveillance and controlbased
standards and technology from abroad, we
will export freedom by design,
showing that privacy, security,
protection of rights and protection of
innovation of individual rights and
innovation can coexist.
The benefits and capabilities of SETI
will be profound. It will provide the
foundation for individuals and
businesses to derive value and utility
for the free market to create new and
innovative solutions. We know there will
be new solutions for proof of identity.
There will be new solutions for
replacements of usernames and passwords.
Imagine that if you don't have to worry
about your passwords being compromised.
There will be new solutions for consent
and management and agreements that
individuals control. There will be new
solutions for delegation empowering
families and guardians and organizations
to act safely on behalf of the vulner of
the vulnerable and those they serve.
There will be solutions for agentic AI
where artificial intelligence operates
with your explicit authorization and not
in your place extending your agency
rather than replacing it.
So many of you are probably wondering
how would we ever get from the current
state to that future state. And we do
that the same way all great things are
done. And we have to do that together.
We have to create a plan. We have to
agree on our values. We have to create a
structure. We have to roll up our
sleeves. And then, as my teenagers and
young kids like to say, we have to
grind. We're going to have to get out
there and actually do the work to make
it happen. And it is going to take a
long time. And under the SETI consortium
is where we can take the fruits of all
these labors that we are about to do and
give them away to everyone else so that
they can follow us. We know not
everybody is going to be able to do
this. We don't have all 50 states here.
Not everybody has the funding, but we
are public entities. We can create it
and we can give it to them for the good
of everyone. So the work we're going to
do is going to include comprehensive
governance frameworks, model
legislation, resolutions, executive
orders, defining SETI requirements,
technology and policy controls,
conformance programs, RFIs and RFPs.
We're going to have to do security
assessments. We're going to have to do
continuous engagement with civil rights
groups and watchd dogs. We're going to
have to have absolute transparency. And
we're going to have to do much much more
to move the digital identity market in
America to align with what are going to
be the SETI standards
the beginning.
So today you are here to learn about
digital identity and some of the
principles that will guide the creation
of state endorsed digital identity. you
will understand the concerns and the
opportunities ahead of us and I hope you
will accept our invitation to join. But
to end, I'm going to teach you just one
of the founding principles and
requirements of state endorsed digital
identity. This is the very first one
that we identified when Senate Bill 260
was written and this is probably the
most foundational and fundamental
difference compared to what you see
happening in the rest of the world.
Identity belongs to the person, not to
the government. The government's role is
not to create or control identity, but
to endorse and protect it as a matter of
public trust.
SETI recognizes it is the role of the
state to act as a trusted endorser
verifying an individual's digital
identity
and then issuing an endorsed credential
mathematically bound to a digital
identifi identifier that individuals
alone control. The state does not create
the individual identifier cannot revoke
it. The simple the state simply endorses
that the person is who they say they are
and then provides a credential that
empowers the individual to say to the
world that I am me and the world will
accept it because it has been endorsed
and backed by the state. The state will
have no control or ability to surveil or
to track the usage and the state cannot
take away the underlying digital
identifier. the state has no role to
take away anybody's digital identity.
So, with that said, we have a very busy
day ahead of us. This is mostly about
introductory education. This is going to
be a very fast-paced
um style to get you information. We'll
have a couple breakouts throughout the
day um where you can ask questions and
you can participate and learn what it
means to help define policy and
technical controls. We're going to end
at the end of the day with an hourlong
discussion of how can we actually move
forward together as states this morning.
The run of the show is we're going to
have Ryan Hurst speak to us and educate
you on what is digital identity. We will
then have Cindy George speaking to us
about her family's experience with
extortion and impersonation and the
impact it has had on them through their
son's suicide. We'll then have a
legislative panel of Senator Cullymore,
Representative Cutler, Representative
Chevier, and Representative Shepard to
discuss with you the importance of this
work, why they are supporting it, and
why you should be a part of the
consortium. We'll then hear from Daniel
Hardman, who will teach us about the
current lay of the digital identity
market. Phil Wley will explain why Utah
is the first state to formally take the
decentralized or first-person identity
approach. and Joe Jackson will teach you
why we are moving forward with backward
compatibility to help the entire market
move forward. So with that, Ryan, I'll
invite you to come up.
Uh nice to meet you all. Um as 10
minutes is a a short period of time to
get quite a bit done. Um I am uh looks
like this mic is live. So I'm going to
leave this here. Um I'll make this quick
here. So um I've been in uh working for
companies like Google, Microsoft, Amazon
and and others for the last 30ome years.
focusing on uh technologies like
authentication. And so today what I'm
going to talk to you about is what is
digital identity? And there's a little
little bit of bias in this um but uh I'm
going to try to get through about 30
years of lessons and what I have left
here. So um identity is not new. Uh this
is a picture of a clay tablet from 1900
B.CE. Merchants used to put their
thumbrint into these clay tablets so
that you could authenticate that this is
uh au uh legitimate. This is a um you
know just a point that uh authentication
is of transactions is something that
we've been worried with since the dawn
of time and this is the earliest example
I could find. Um, but we've been trying
over and over to solve this problem. And
each generation of uh has to approach
this problem slightly differently for
the environment that they exist in. I've
got a few examples that exist in this
timeline below here. We won't go through
them today, but at the end of this uh
presentation, I have a QR code that
talks a little bit about successes that
you can follow for a paper on successes
and failures in this space. As I'm going
to go fairly fast here. So, what
identity is not is as important as what
identity is. It is not a better
document. Um, digital identity is uh
materially different than the one-time
issuance of a of a a document that we
would use to authenticate um at a
government office or uh when traveling.
It is more of a living type of
credential that lives for a long period
of time. That living nature means that
this is a governance problem. This is uh
this is not a technology problem. Um so
why is this uh why is this important?
because seven out of ten of the projects
that I've looked at over the last
several decades and and you'll see those
in that white paper have failed and they
failed because they looked at this as a
govern not as a governance problem but
as a technology problem is it or
procurement um and and so that's why
it's important that we're all here today
and I'm really excited to be involved in
this conversation. So this is a model
shift. State issues document, you carry
it, verifier inspects it. That's what
we're all used to. But this the as we
look at what does it mean to have civic
digital identity. It's much larger than
just my name is Ryan Hurst, there's many
endorsements about Ryan Hurst that might
be material to the verification. I'm I'm
a motorcycle driver. That is certainly a
driver's license thing, but I also am a
parent. I also have uh other attributes
about me that are important and the
state is involved in many elements of
those and being able to prove that to
third parties is becoming increasingly
important and I'll talk a little bit
about some of those cases. This this
expanded role of identity um uh uh in
the online online world is something
that means that we have to change the
way we look at this problem and we have
to start with a set of guiding
principles which is why again I think
SETI is an important um project.
So, one of the biggest differences that
we'll see as we look at digital identity
versus their paper um history uh
historical analog is that they actually
codify the policy that you all come up
with. And this is important because now
when you make a change that digital
document and the systems that verify it
may also need to be changing. So, we
have to think a little bit more
holistically than that issuance moment.
We have to think about how are we going
to manage this over its entire life
cycle. Um, if we think of this as we
bought a a solution to print these
digital identities and declare victory,
we will fail. That's the number one
pattern we see when we look back at the
failed systems. Um,
so what is maintained over time? Well,
there's a lot of status changes.
Licenses get suspended, whether it be
medical or driver's license or uh
credentials may get compromised and may
need to be replaced. Um, algorithms may
need to be changed over time. These are
probabilistically secure methods to
prove these things and so we may may
have to change them. For example,
postquantum cryptography is coming in
the future. So uh and policies change
continuously faster than ever before and
and this all means that how we govern
these systems is going to become
increasingly uh important. So if we look
at these failure patterns um there's
there's many that we can point at. One
of the ones that I like to point at is
the German solution. um that Germany uh
came up with a a national ID card um
that was technically pure and perfect uh
from their definition of technically
pure and perfect and it was an abysmal
failure. Um nobody adopted it because
the governance model was not right. They
they put the burden on the the the
constituents. They made it very
complicated to adopt. They didn't have a
a core utility. So it was massive
amounts of money spent with no return on
investment. It's not something that we
can afford. UK is another great example.
Um I I can't go into the details today,
but they wasted $233 million in a decade
of time roughly um because they didn't
look at this problem holistically and
they didn't measure it in the right way.
Um some of the successes we can point at
Estonia. um they started with a list of
three or four utility scenarios that
they were going to enable and as a
result their system continues to exist.
We can look at Sweden. They looked at
what was practical to deploy and achieve
results with and their exist exists and
is is loved. Very rarely do you find a
government service that is loved. But I
think that it's fair to say that that
particular program is um US government
has its own as well. Um and and there's
others that have elements of success,
but uh we'll go into those later in that
paper I mentioned.
So why is this important? I'm from the
state of Washington. We have the honor
of I believe being the largest COVID
fraud for uh distribution of uh COVID
funds. Um I think Africa got more than
we did. Um so this is a big problem and
it's a problem because we didn't invest
ahead of time. We didn't build the
infrastructure to enable the government
to be able to identify its citizens
online. Um, and we can't let this
pattern repeat again. Um,
so why does this matter? Now I mentioned
CO, but it's much larger than CO. We can
look at AI for example. Today I can
generate a fake utility bill, birth
certificate, and whatever easily with
just a few types of on my keyboard that
you're going to believe is legitimate. I
can do real time deep fakes that are
nearly impossible to distinguish. The
voice will be the same. You cannot rely
on a video call to authenticate who
you're talking to anymore. Um, and so
this means that we have to invest in
infrastructure to be able to strongly
authenticate who we're dealing with so
that we're able to um prevent mistakes
like that one from happening again. I
also think it's important to note that
in the context of security breaches, 88%
of security breaches tracked by two
companies, roughly that figure, I think
they have two slight slightly different
numbers, but very very similar, were
just using stolen credentials. Um, they
didn't hack anything, they logged in.
And so it's important that we pick
strong technologies that solve for the
problems and don't have externalities
that make things worse. This is you are
the foundation of how the federal
government interacts with Americans. You
are the foundation of how the rest of
the world interacts with Americans
online. And we have to solve this
problem. This is not something that we
can ignore. So why does this uh matter
for you? Um you don't um you don't
manage digital identity in abstract.
There's a lot of different examples of
this that that exist inside of your
organizations. You may not think of them
as digital identity. Um, so different
people have different definitions of
this term, but I view all of these
things as part of the life cycle of
identity. A birth certificate is my my
child's um ID until they're old enough
to get a driver's license. Many of these
other elements, my my wife carries um
our marriage license because she's from
another country when we travel because
it's part of her digital identity. All
of these things are part of that package
that we have to use that the state
produces that the rest of the world
relies on to verify who we are. So
before you commit to any approach I
think it's an understand uh important to
understand what uh what uh what u
digital identity tells you well what
questions to ask that didn't word that
particularly well um so
since this is a codified thing the
question becomes when policy changes how
does the digital identity get affected
um because it's policy based like how
are you actually going to create demand
for this thing if you have no utility
function for your deployment So some
scenarios that are enabled that are
actually meaningful to your
constituents, they're not going to go
through the the hassle of doing it no
matter how beautiful the solution you
build is because it's uh how are you
going to maintain the entire life cycle
of this system. This is like any IT
investment in that respect. Um and
because it's civi civic identity, you
have to pay pay attention to who's
excluded. My parents are not
particularly good at using things online
anymore. Um and so we don't want to
exclude an entire segment of our
society. And there's of course other
examples as well. So what does success
look like? Um you've identified anchor
tenants. You've budgeted some amount for
continual governance. You've addressed
you know how are you going to deal with
interoperability with existing systems.
You understand, you know, how your
platform uh is related to the various
dependencies that you have and you
understand the equity implications for
this system and how are you going to
manage them and you've defined success
metrics and how you're going to
continually revise those metrics so that
you can make sure that your system is
delivering on the promises that you set
out set out to do. So that is my
presentations. Uh ladies and gentlemen,
I appreciate your time today.
Hi, my name is Cindy George and I'm here
to tell you about
my son's story and the horrific
experience that he went through.
First of all, I want you to get to know
my boy.
This is my Jake, my baby boy. One out of
my two kids. And um
Oh, those dimples.
Everyone commented on those cute little
dimples.
I was this fifth grade teacher, which
every kid's nightmare, right, to have
your mom as your teacher, but I was his
first um fifth grade teacher. So, I was
able to see what a kind-hearted,
thoughtful, and caring kid this was. Not
just as a mother, but as a teacher.
Um, I remember one day after school, he
came up to me and he kind of had glassy
eyes, you know, almost teary, and he
said, I said, "What's wrong?" And he
said, "Mom,
something happened today." And first, I
need to give you a little background. We
had a little boy in our class that had a
medical issue that didn't have control
of his bowels and oftent times he um
smelled and the kids really made fun of
him. He had no friends. Um he was picked
on don't touch. He's got cooties type
stuff. And um Jake was his friend.
Jake had a group of friends that he hung
out with that uh he loved and they loved
him, but he saw this little boy and
he befriended him. And after school one
day, he came up to me. He said, "Mom,"
he said, "they're being so mean to
Brian." And I said, I said, "What
happened?" He said, "Well, at school, at
recess," he said, I said, "Come on,
Brian. let's go out. And we we were
walking out on the playground and my
friends were like on the on the
basketball court and saying, "Jate, come
over. Come play with us." And he's like,
"Yeah, let's go play. Come on, Brian.
Let's go play." And we got over there
and they said, "Just you, Jake, not
Brian."
And I said, "Well, Jake, what did you
do? How did you handle that?" And he
said, "I just turned to him and I said,
"It's okay. Brian and I are going to
come play over here. And so he actually
gave up his friends
because he saw this little boy had no
friends. That's the kind of kid my Jake
was.
Um
when he was in middle school,
um he would spend his days off. He'd
say, "Mom, can I go to school with you?"
And even in high school, mom, can I go
to school with you on his days off? And
he would come to school with me. And he
would help tutor the kids. He would help
them with math or he'd read to them.
The kids in my class always knew Jake.
Um
Jake loved donuts. That was this was his
last birthday. I made him a cake out of
donuts and he said, "Mom, that was the
best cake ever."
He also loved Oh, about the donuts.
Every year um when he was in high school
and he had his own money, he would show
up on my birthday
and he would show up with three dozen
donuts so he could give donuts to my
class for my birthday.
That's the kind of kid Jake was.
He also was an animal lover. This was
his best buddy, Bosco. And he loved
dogs. He um he loved animals.
Um
he also loved music. When he was a
little toddler, he'd be in the back
seat. was amazing because I I'm big into
music. So, I'd have the music blaring
and he'd be in the back seat as a
toddler in his little car seat going
to the beat of the music. Just even as a
little toddler, he loved music. He loved
every and a big variety. He loved
Lincoln Park all the way to Elvis and
Buddy Holly. And I was like, "Wow,
that's a huge huge thing." Um,
one of my sweet memories is on Mother's
Day, he bought me tickets to the Sticks
Ario Speed Wagon concert, but it wasn't
for me to take just anyone. It I He gave
me one ticket and the other one was for
him. And we went as mother and son and
rocked out to Stigs and Ario Speedwagon.
That's the kind of kid Jake was. He was
a great student. He got his uh
associates degree while he was in high
school. Um which was a great
um achievement for him.
Most of all,
Jake loved his family.
My two nephews
were Jake's best friends and they did
everything together, including pranking
me. They that was their most favorite
thing to do. Um,
and then
I got my first grandbaby
and that
just made Jake an uncle and he was so
proud to be Uncle Jake now.
Um, sorry, I'm having issues. Okay.
Um
Jake and I
um had the fall break and so we went on
a road trip together just the two of us
and we went to the Grand Canyon, we went
to Bryce and just had mother and son
time. Um, these are
the pictures from our
road trip as well as the one that's up
here. This one, he had never seen the
Grand Canyon. And when we got there, it
was full of clouds. And so that was his
picture with the Grand Canyon was clouds
in the background. This right here was
our last trip together.
two weeks later
is where I'm going to pick up with the
story.
Um,
it was the day before Halloween
and I'm I was a teacher and I had a
teacher work day and I was sitting at my
desk
when I got a call from the Millow County
Police Department. I said, "Is is this
Cindy George?" And I said, "Yes." And he
said, "Do you have a son named Jake?"
And I said, "Yes." And do you have a
place in Kosh,
Utah? And I said, "Yes." And then it hit
me. Oh, Jake's at at our little place.
We had just a little getaway place
there. and he must have uh he must be
there and they must think that he's um
break breaking in or something like
that. And I said, "Yes, yeah, that's my
son." And they said, "He has taken his
life
in your home."
I just ar I argued with him. I said,
"You got the wrong kid." My kid was not
on drugs. My kid did not drink.
My kid was not depressed.
This did not make sense.
It couldn't be my kid.
And I argued with him until I they
described his car and explained that he
had taken a gun
and he was gone.
Um, the rest of the day was kind of a
blur
and why could couldn't even fathom how
this could happen.
And they um
the police department they faxed a
couple of his letters. He wrote seven
letters. This is kind of kid Jake was.
He wrote letters to his sister, to his
friend, to his nephews, or his cousins.
This one's to me. I'm just going to read
part of it. Says, "Dear mom, I love you
so much,
and it pains me to write this. I wish I
could live with what I did.
I know this will be hard for you, but I
need you to continue on with your life.
I hope you don't think too bad of me for
what I did. I know this is sudden, but
the hell that I went through Sunday
through Thursday was too much for me to
handle. I love you dearly, Mom.
You will always be my mother
and I will always be your baby boy.
Love, Jake.
It still didn't make sense. But what
could possibly
what could possibly make him do this?
And so 4 months later,
the police department gave me back his
phone
and the last letter that they held
and it says, "My dear, this is for
um all of its parents. I am sorry for
what I have done, but I have nothing to
live for anymore. I have made a huge
mistake that I can't live with. Look at
my phone
and read the messages that that are in
the kick app. Start with the girl
profile named Alone at home and then
move on to the profile just for fun.
These messages will explain everything.
From Sunday to Thursday, my life has
been a living hell and roller coaster of
emotion. the the one person that owns
these two profiles will be using
Facebook to ruin my life. There's a good
chance I will lose my job and get kicked
out of school as the person attacks me
there using Facebook. I urge you all to
control what happens on Facebook as much
as possible. This person claims that
they will copy some of your profiles and
attack your friends. Also,
this person attacked my three most
important things being my school, my
job, and my family.
Please don't change your lives for me.
Hold your children and grandchildren
close. I love you all. Jake
So, I'm just going to take you a little
timeline. Um,
I got his phone back and I read I was
the own I just took it aside and I read
the whole conversation
and I understood
the pressure
and the hell that they put him through.
This happened in five days. I was with
him on Sunday and Friday he was gone.
I read the conversation how the predator
talked him into sending him a nude photo
after grooming him. They talked him into
sending one new f one
nude photo
and kind of like I'll send you one, you
send me one. Talked him into it. I saw
the high pressure that they put him in
and then I saw how they sent him names
of family members and said, "We're going
after them next."
And I think that's where it put Jake
over the edge.
So, I'm going to take you a timeline
what his life went through in five days.
On Sunday,
they get him to send after grooming,
they got him to move to the kick app.
I'm not sure where the original source
came from because he was on some dating
sites and he was on Facebook. I believe
it came from Facebook, but I'm not sure
on that. But they got him to move to the
Kick app, which is
which is common for this type of a
thing. Um,
after they got him to move,
they said, "Now we've got you." Or after
they got him to send a picture, they
said, "Now we've got you." Just added
and saved all your Facebook friends on
my laptop. I am going to send them your
nude photo and post it all over your
friends Facebook timeline and also to
your job on UPS Facebook page. But I
will not do that if you send me the
money right now. Okay?
After constant threats, high pressure,
get there, get to the Walmart, get get
an application. Let me see the
application. Get to the ATM. Let me see
the money. That he was having to take
pictures of everything they were on him.
Just didn't give him time to even
process and think this through.
He finally at 7:06 that night, he makes
a payment of $300 to at a Walmart
at Saratobica Springs to a Marie a Brill
in the Philippines.
Then Jake asks for her to please
delete the picture like you said.
This was his response he got.
He said, they said, ' Do you know what a
genie is, Jake? And he said, 'Yes. He
says, 'Well, you are my genie today and
I have found you. So,
you have to grant me three wishes. And
he says, which are which you
means you're going to have to make three
pigments.
After begging for her to leave him
alone, saying, "I'm just a college kid.
Please leave me alone."
Jake ends up back at Walmart that night
to make another payment of $130.
The torment and constant threats
continued for the next few days.
Jake paid them everything he had,
$680.
And after fulfilling the three wishes
that she required of him, Jake then
begged her to now please delete the
photo.
And the reply was,
"You work at UPS. In two weeks, you'll
have another paycheck."
And Jake realized this is never going to
end.
Um,
he says, "Please delete it. I can't live
the next two weeks with you blackmailing
me. I gave you his his total that he had
just given his last payment." And he
said,
he said, "You won't get any more more
money if I'm not here.
The reply was, "Five guys committed
suicide because I posted their nudes and
ruined their life. But I never care
because it's their choice, not mine. You
will be the sixth and I still won't
care."
On Thursday,
Jake buys the garden hose
and heads
at a Home Depot in American Fork.
And then in Richfield,
he buys a Rema paper and a box of
envelopes and he goes to a hotel.
And I assume that's where he wrote all
of his
letters.
And he left one
on the desk in the hotel saying, "The
person that was in this room is going to
take their life. Please contact."
and he said Brandon George, which was my
husband at the time, his brother that
lived in Kosh, and said, "Please contact
him. I'm going to be out in the West
Desert."
Um
then on his way out of town
he bought a helium tank
which was later found empty in his car
along with when I got in his car I found
the hose and it was black on one end
and the helium tank was empty and I
think that he tried to take his life
using that method and I think it was
just taking too long and he could not do
it.
And he knew
that my husband at the time had a
shotgun
in Kanach and he found the key
and he um took his life.
the hell that I go through thinking of
those last moments as he's sitting there
in so much torment
and have to pull that trigger
because of these evil people and what
they did.
No mother should have to bury their son.
And it was so pointless.
I could not catch this person. I was
told because it came from the
Philippines. There was nothing that
could be done.
Um there's a there's a program on the
National Geographic called Trafficking
with Mariana Vanzellar.
They contacted me out of the blue. I
don't know how they found me. And they
said, "We want to do your son's story
and we want to go to the Philippines and
try and find who did this." And so she
came to my house. They did the interview
and then they proceeded to investigate
and they
found the source in the Philippines
and it was a call center,
a huge call center.
This is going on
and hitting so many of our children.
It's a big business there.
She actually talked to one of the people
that does this and he was hooded so all
you could see was his eyes. She said,
"Do you know that people are killing
themselves because of that?" And he
said, "Yeah, I watched one of them do
it."
That's the kind of evil we're talking
about here.
Something has to be done.
Um, Brandon Guffy, a state
representative in South Carolina that I
have spoken to, had lost his son Gavin,
his 17-year-old son Gavin, to sextortion
after his after his son died. He
actually got
um contact he was contacted
by the perpetrator
and they sent him a laughing emoji
and it said, "Did I tell you your son
begged for his life?"
That's the kind of evil we're talking
about here.
This is coming from Nigeria.
This is coming from the Ivory Coast.
This is coming from here.
Um,
we need to do something to warn these
kids. I cannot I cannot catch the people
that did this to my son. Um, Brandon
Guffy, I saw on his Facebook about six
months ago.
He and his wife were holding a set of
handcuffs on his page
and they have Gavin's name etched in the
in the handcuffs
and they went to Nigeria and they found
who did this to their son
and they extradited them and they've
been charged.
What a great thing that they were able
to do that. the Philippine uh
government were not so uh accommodating
when the National Greek Geographic went
over there. They found they know who
started the whole thing in the
Philippines and
she's been arrested and then let out.
Um
I asked for your help because I can't
catch them.
My son died so needlessly.
I can't catch them. But only thing I can
do is warn others. Please talk to your
grandkids,
your kids, your neighbors, your nephews.
Talk to them so they won't take the
bait. That's the only thing we can do is
educate so they won't take the bait.
And we need to also talk to them and let
them know no matter what no matter what
is happening in your life that they can
come to you. I wish Jake would have been
able to come to me.
I wish I could have comforted him and
said, "It's okay. They can't destroy
your life with that picture."
Don't ever think this can ever happen to
my child, my nephew,
because I can testify to you that it can
happen to the best of kids.
Thank you.
All
right, we are going to start with our
four champions
that have been actually working on SETI
for the last couple years. Um, I'm going
to make some comments about a little bit
of the history. Um there were
stakeholders in this room that actually
asked legislative leadership um I think
it was almost three years ago of can we
do digital identity and the whole point
of it is to solve impersonation problems
like Cindy just told us about. There are
real harms happening and our kids our
grandparents our parents are going to
come into these scenarios where people
are pretending to be things and people
that they are not. So the legislature
uh they actually told us um well some of
the legislature have you got to get the
right groups on board na nationwide
there are people who distrust digital
identity they distrust government and
it's for good reason it can do a lot of
harm and so that's why we put so much
thought into SETI so representative
Chevier before she was even a
representative she she was influential
in politics and they said Kristen
Chevier has to support what we're doing
and they also said Lisa Shepard has to
support what we're doing and they're
both two of our newest representatives
and uh and so you both supported the
SETI approach before it was even a bill.
Can you each tell us just quickly why
you are supporting SETI?
So, for me, I've had um I've been
working in healthc care advocacy, trying
to help people have the right to
informed consent. And um
for several years now there's been an
effort to consolidate data
and healthcare data specifically into
data lakes so that there can be
interoperability and people can work
together and get records more quickly.
And I know that's an issue. I know that
it's more it's better for them to be
able to access the records quickly. But
I've been fighting it for the last 10
years because of the dangers that are
involved in centralizing that data. And
so that is the biggest issue for me is
that I wanted a way for us to be able to
make data accessible without
compromising privacy.
I have it on. Is it on? It's on. Okay.
Thank you. For me, there's a lot of
distrust in digital platforms that are
going on right now. And there's, as you
saw today, and as you already have
known, there's been many people that do
bad things that will will really scare
people. And one of the things for me is
that your personal data is just
scattered. and having the opportunity to
have Utah lead in this area and to be
able to make it that we and recall that
we own our data. The government doesn't
own our data. We own our data or we
should at least. So, it's important to
me that we have privacy, autonomy, and
and with our state having the consent of
the govern. I have many constituents who
reach out to me even as of yesterday
telling me a digital ID is not the way
to go. But as you'll hear today, there
is many reasons why we should go with
it. And I have a firm belief that uh
even before I took office that we have
the right people in the right place here
and I think our other states need to
join us with this one and making sure
that we don't do like other countries
have done with our data.
Senator Colmore, Representative Culler,
you got SB260 passed unanimously through
the House and the Senate. A couple years
after there was a different digital
identity bill, which I've heard there
were pitchforks in committee hearing and
it did not come out. Um, why are you
supporting and championing SETI?
I'll start. I I've been fortunate to be
able to work on technology policy in the
Senate over the last several years. Um
it started with data privacy uh just in
the consumer aspect and and recognizing
how important that is. Um we we've since
passed a government data privacy, the
first of its kind, which I think is also
important. But in the middle there,
we're also working on social media bills
and social media policy because
government with technology typically is
always well, government by its nature is
reactionary, which I don't think is
necessarily a bad thing. But in some of
these technology policies, it moves so
fast that we are we are not in front of
this and we are allowing people to be
exploited.
And the the way the internet came up is
was using data. The way this has been
monetized is using our data.
Facebook, Instagram, Snapchat,
Google, any of these services are free
to us because as we all know, you are
what's being sold. You are the
commodity.
And that that that in and of itself is
scary. And that's what we're have.
That's what we're having to deal with as
social media right now is social media
companies have exploited that to the b
to the detriment of our kids. They're
not only affecting their mental health,
but they're causing actual real world
harm like we just heard about. And it's
and it's terrible. And putting that same
type of power into the government's
hands that has even more control over
over so many aspects of our lives is
just super scary and something that we
need to avoid. We need to flip the
script of how this is being developed
and what what this actually means. We
need to put the power back into the
citizenry into people. People are not
commodities. And and that is what the
digital age has has has created. We are
all commodities now. And I think that's
one of the fundamental evils of of our
day and age is when we commoditize human
life, that's problematic. And if
government is going to do that, that's
even more problematic. And so we needed
to find a way to flip the script. SETI
the bill that we passed is really just
the first fundamental step. It's it's
it's laying the foundation for flipping
the script and saying no the power is
back in the people. The power is back in
the individual.
If we look back at history,
history shows us that fighting techn
technology advancement is often a feudal
effort. Whether you're a a buggy whip m
maker trying to put laws to stop the
automobile or trying to fight
industrialization that technology is
going to move forward because there are
so many benefits to society. So we have
a choice to be proactive and influence
and control these standards or we can
stick our head in the sand and say no I
don't want this. I don't I want to fight
it and I I choose to
try to be part of the solution.
Digital identity is coming. I think we
all especially everyone in this room
recognizes that. And the only choice is
do we want to influence the standards
and the adoption of this to protect
freedom and individual liberties or will
we acquis to efficiency and and
monetization.
There are bold visions out there for
artificial intelligence, especi
acting on uh uh behalf of an entity or
or a software
uh program.
The security concerns are very real. You
are not going to feel a smart security
person will not allow uh an agent to
take on uh a a task on their behalf if
there is not trust and as has been
talked about our digital trust structure
is under constant attack right now and
in in many areas it fails. So we have
got to come up with a better system for
verifiable credentials for trusting
uh people and eventually entities if
this agentic uh future has any chance of
of making a real impact without doing
incredible harm in our society.
I'm going to go off script here for the
rest of the time.
Um, Utah in my view has been unique
compared to what I've heard actually
from many in the audience and how we
work together between branches of
government. Um, we have CIOS in the
audience. We have chief privacy officers
in the audience. We have legislators in
the audience. Uh, we have uh civil
rights groups in the audience. And and
I've heard them comment of how is Utah
able to do these things it's doing. So
I'm I'm going to ask this to Senator
Colmore. What is it that Utah is doing
differently than other states? And what
should they know so they can go back to
their states and replicate the success
we're having across our government on
both sides of the aisle?
Well, you know, we have to put we have
to set aside our our trying to be humble
here because there are some things that
that work really well here here in Utah
and we call it the Utah way. But the
Utah way really is just recognizing that
that we are here as, you know, public
servants. We're servants of the people
and and when you approach these types of
policies, you you have to have a little
bit of humility to say, you know, I I
don't know everything. And that's
especially true in technology, right?
Like I I I fundamentally believe I
fundamental fundamentally believe in
certain principles, but I don't actually
know how the technology actually works,
right? And so sometimes you you want to
implement a law and we're talking about
very basic things right here. But but
whether it's like whatever the type of
law is, I think it's critically
important that you bring in all the
stakeholders and and who best than than
the private sector and academia. And so
whenever we've worked on these policies,
we have good working relationships
between the Senate and the House. We
have good working relationships between
the legislature and the executive
branch, the regulators who are actually
enforcing this or implementing uh
implementing the laws that we pass. And
and it's important because you know the
policy does not actually work if the
imple has their own idea and goes goes a
certain direction. And none of this
actually works because most of the time
people in government don't have the
technical expertise to know what they're
actually talking about. And so we have
one of the shortest sessions,
legislative sessions in the country. is
45 days, begins in the middle of January
and goes to about the first weekend of
March. And we are a part-time
legislature. Um, that is becoming less
and less a reality. We're becoming more
and more full-time because really that
that January to March, that's game time,
but it's happening all year round. And
so, we're we're meeting with
stakeholders. And most of the best
policy that we pass
involves academia people who who have
the the research and the background on
their the private sector people who are
actually developing these technologies
or deploying these technologies or or or
using them within their business uh
policy makers and and the executive
branch. And so I don't think we've
passed any tech technological policy in
the state of Utah without input from
from all of them. And sometimes it takes
takes time. the consumer data privacy
bill that we passed, I think we were the
fourth state in the nation to pass it,
but it ran for three years and it and we
were getting input from everybody and it
and it gets whittleled down. We we
passed a digital asset uh uh bill that
recognizes what digital assets are and
it started out as 16 pages even when it
when it was introduced in the session
and because of input it got whittleled
down and said no let's let's boil this
down to the fundamental principles and
then build build on that and I think
that's what we've done here with SETI is
we haven't we haven't made this I I mean
it's it's it's policy it's agnostic to
what the technology is and in fact the
technology is not even out there right
now that that could be impleimement
mented, but it's it's steering the boat
and it's steering the the direction of
how that technology is going to be
implemented. And so, um I this the
opposite of being humble, but you know,
using humility to get to these to to
these policy decisions, I think is what
what helps drive uh you know, the
advancements that we've seen in Utah.
Chris, I'd love to comment on that. I I
think we have been successful as Senator
Colmore and he deserves a lot of the
credit for bringing people together as
as do you and and making some policy,
but it's premature to pat ourselves on
the back yet and say that this that this
is great. We we have some good policy,
but we haven't seen adoption and we
can't do adoption on our own. We can't
do adoption by just the legislature
passing a policy. adoption requires
industry to come up with tools and use
cases that are compelling
and because also because Utah is small
to be successful. We need your help. We
need other states to join together and
show that we have uh enough of a
consortium to to get attention from the
big players to say this matters and
privacy and security and individual
rights are important. So while we've had
a little bit of success, we need to
replicate that by
having you join us and trying and
agreeing on some key principles and some
key standards where we can move forward
together and have a a larger coalition.
Representative Chevier and Shepard, I'm
actually going to ask you the the same
question. you two probably represent
some of the most conservative areas in
the nation in Utah County. Um
and and the fact that this bill is
passed unanimously
um I think one is is representative of
the work done, but what is it that's
different about this approach that is
helping to win over or at least gain the
trust of those that each of you
represent?
Do you want to go first? I can go first.
So, I think this this is going to be off
topic for a second, but it's really on
topic. Um, we have a system of
government in Utah that is different
from most other states and that is the
caucus convention system which makes it
so that the grassroots are far more
involved with their legislators than
they are in most states.
And I think that that's been a huge
factor because both Representative
Shepard and I have been very involved in
the party and in the caucus convention
system.
um we have built trust in that arena
that allows us to help transfer that
trust to the legislature and to this
technology that we're talking about. So
because we have that opportunity to
build trust, um I think that makes it
easier for us to to help people
understand because they're willing to
listen to us because we have built trust
with them through that system.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
Prior to being elected, I had a town
hall and it I had experts in this area
come and and speak to those who came.
And yes, of course, we use it through
the caucus convention system that we
have that allows us to have a direct
report and be held accountable by
delegates.
And that is where you get the biggest
push back and honesty. delegates are
very engaged and they know issues and
you can't hide and it's it's a great
actually a really great process and I
appreciate that. I appreciate the
accountability the delegates and and my
voters that I have talked to about this
by knocking on the doors. They want us
to leave them alone. They want to be
able to be safe in this community, not
only physically but also digitally.
And I believe that the relationships
that um having served on a state level
and in my my party and and served just
across the entire state and and worked
in some national areas, I believe that
that that does open the door to when I
bring experts to my district that
they're willing to take a chance and
listen. And it has changed the hearts of
some of them to actually listen.
Sometimes we get stuck in our ways and
think that we have the answers and
something is the boogeyman. But honestly
when you listen and and Chris Bramwell
has come to my district along with
Timothy Ruff and when they have when
they have spoken
people in my district have listened and
that's what I really appreciate. It's
the opportunity to bring these experts
as the good senator to my left here has
mentioned to bring these experts and to
and to trust them. We have to have trust
in the experts and our people are that
we represent have to have trust in us.
It's quite the partnership that we have.
Chris, can I add one thing to that? I
think your policy of engaging with
critics has been key to some of the
success. There are sometimes where in
politics where you don't engage with the
critics, you say, "I have a majority.
I'm just going to pass this through."
But that hasn't been how the privacy
legislation that Senator Kolmore has has
has helped with or this uh legislation
has been handled. You've held town halls
where you invited critics to come and
poke holes and things. You've brought in
key members of staff and industry to
come and engage and you slowed down the
process to help convince the critics
that this is the right way forward and I
think that made a big difference.
Thank you.
We have six minutes. I actually I'd like
to ask does anybody have any questions?
Any questions of maybe
I I can do I can do it. I'm so What is
this? The Murray show. Is that what
Hi, my name is Sarah Tunberg. I'm the
director of the Colorado Digital
Service. Thank you for having us. We are
watching very closely the work you've
done and are talking about our own
legislative agenda as the legislature
that legislators that moved a lot of
this forward. Do you have any
recommendations for those of us to take
home with us how we can model lessons
learned things now in retrospect you
think maybe we would have done it
differently?
I'm not sure about the done it
differently, but I'll tell you what
we've done that has been working and it
and Paul we well we've all talked a
little bit about it, but Chris has been
very proactive in interacting with the
people who are most likely to be the
critics. And so Lisa and I have been
able to set up these town halls where we
can bring Chris in and have him explain
to people. We've set up meetings with
individuals who are
all at night and on weekends by the way.
Yes, it is out of regular business hours
always. Um, but we've been able to have
discussions with the most vocal critics,
people who have large followings on
social media, and we've been able to
help them understand what it is we're
actually doing because the reaction is
visceral. I had somebody on Facebook
this morning say to me that having you
endorse digital identity was not on my
bingo card.
It wasn't on mine either, but here I am
because I believe that this is the right
system and I believe that we either have
to choose a system that is going to
respect privacy or we're going to get
the other one.
And so we need to make the choice and we
need to make it soon. I'm going to make
a comment too. You need a champion in
your state. Um when Senator Colmore and
Moss created the CPO role, they
empowered it to be a champion. You need
every government entity fights for
certain rights for the public. Public
safety is to proide safety. Lands is to
protect the public lands. Health and
human services is to ensure there's
public health and human service. Do you
have a privacy or digital identity
champion in your state that is empowered
to even fight for this issue? It's a
it's a balancing and that's part of the
governance framework. So, if you don't
have that, get it going or be the
champion.
So, I I'll just add, you know, as as
state legislators, what's awesome about
being uh in in state policy is that you
can pass a bill and then you see the
effects of it like almost immediately.
And that's that's pretty rewarding.
The the downside of that is you you want
to do everything right now, you know,
and and that's just not possible in
these types of bills. You know, we we
could have said you will implement these
policies and forced it upon all the
government agencies and all the
political subdivisions of the state and
cities and counties and it would have
fell on its face and we would have got
zero adoption because there's no way to
even adopt it right now. Uh we're doing
about that with government data privacy.
We wanted all of the cities, the
counties, the state agencies, our
schools and everything like that to
adopt all these things. And you will you
will implement data privacy right now
and you will implement all these
retention policies and you'll get rid of
this stuff. And it's just it's just
impractical and and you're setting
yourself up for failure. And so you do
have to reel back a little bit and say,
you know what, I'm just going to let's
just pass this right now and let's build
that. And and even as Chris said, you
know, we we did a data private or we did
the chief privacy officer a few years
ago and and we just keep slowly building
on that. And so you do have to have
patience, which is not always a virtue
among state legislators.
Good morning. I'm Shannon Durant with
the Department of Public Safety. Thanks
for having us. I have a question
particularly for the representatives.
You say you've had a lot of town halls.
I'm curious about how often you're
having them and how much you're
publicizing them because you say that
we're we're talking to a lot of people
who are social media influencers, but um
for example, um Representative Cutler,
my parents are actually some of your
neighbors, so they've never heard about
this until I talked to them. So how how
much are is there public to more than
just you know social media and advocacy
groups and what can we do on our side as
public uh entities as state entities to
assist in that but also give other
solutions to help you with an enhanced
identity and what can we bring to the
table in order to make it better.
Thanks for thanks for the question. I
think that's important. So when I
mentioned all these town halls, they
were they were fairly targeted and the
efforts to focus on the policy have been
targeted with those who are probably the
the fiercest advocates either for or
against.
Let's let's be honest, most regular pe
most people
this this issue hasn't hit them yet
because there there is nothing for them
to adopt today. Yes, they they could
adopt our mobile driver's license which
they may or may not be able to get
through homeland security.
They they there are but there they
cannot we don't have a digital identity
for them to adopt yet. So the efforts
for advocy advocacy were targeted at the
key stakeholders, those who are most
concerned about privacy, those who are
most concerned about the technology
used. And the the next wave once once we
have a solution ready to be adopted
would be to go out to all the citizens
and explain how this is used, how this
helps your life, how this can help
verify ages on social media, how it
helps protect their family from online
fraud, which are real pressing problems
that we all recognize and we're all
trying to deal with. And we've got to
get to a point where we have a solution
for them. So, we have a policy solution
today. We do not have a market solution
until we get your help to agree on a
standard and and products.
I just and I know we're out of time, but
it's it's a little bit of a catch22,
right? Because if you go to a town hall,
you you've got,
you know, I I'll publish a town hall for
thousands of people and and the same 12
people show up and they're a little bit
older oftent times and they're not techn
technologically savvy. And I would bring
up some of these topics and my wife
would be there and she'd be like, "You
you've got to stop talking about that."
Like like like they don't care. It goes
over their head and I think you're just
scaring them anyways. So So it's a
little bit hard, right? because you have
to find these focus groups of people who
are like keyed in on this, tuned in. But
but to your point, we we've got to find
a way that people understand that I I do
believe this is critically important.
And as we're moving into this digital
age, if government does not get out in
front of this, it's going to be a
problem. It's going to undermine
democracy. So,
I will say the approach for
communication though has been to
communicate with every elected official
where a town hall is being held. So, UVU
was partnered with for that. So they
emailed every uh elected uh senator,
representative, county commissioner,
mayors in every one of the areas where
the town halls were. So it was very much
focused toward who are the people
actually elected to represent the people
and then they were asked to communicate
it out. Um the other thing I'll say
though is this approach we're talking
about SETI doesn't even exist yet. We're
so early in bringing the public in. Yep.
29 states already going down a digital
identity path with mobile driver's
license or with W3C credentials or
others in California or Colorado. Um,
this is unique of how early this is
happening and people don't realize the
train has already left the station in
some way and we're having to to move the
market to try to move everything in this
direction and we're needing to now come
in with new policies and standards that
we need to have all of that stuff now go
back and be compared to to make sure it
can meet them.
Let's uh let's end 15 seconds. What's
your pitch for states to come and join
the consortium?
I'll I'll I'll throw out on this. Many
of us recognize that we let uh uh tech
giants and the market determine the
principles by which social media
operates and is distributed and affects
our families. I think we have a lesson
learned from that that we need to think
carefully about uh in in this AI world
how do we want to change that or
influence how we control digital
identity so we don't have the mistake of
people who are our kids accessing things
they shouldn't u so this is a chance to
help solve that problem with youth
identity and to solve the economic
problem of how do I inc how do I
put Greece in the system to allow
economic transactions with trust to
happen uh across the world.
Okay. Go ahead, Lisa.
I think we need 49 more Chris Bramwell
uh across the country.
That's that's a definite statement. and
his team. I've seen the hard work that
that they do and the innovation. Utah's
famous for being innovative and we need
the other states to join us. We can't do
this alone. I think uh get your get your
states to get a data privacy expert and
an officer, a director, whatever your
role is, all of the above. And and get
your teams of the experts in the field.
I'll tell you, I was on a panel here for
synthetic data.
I'm just a normal person just carrying
the voice of the people and I sat there
and every other person had a PhD. I'm
looking at one right now and they are
incredibly brilliant. They are the ones
that are come up with the solutions.
We're the ones up here that are helping
to implement those across the country.
So, we need your help.
Are you going to go?
I'll go. Sure.
So I have zero confidence in Congress
getting anything done in this space.
I have to the extent they get anything
done, I have less confidence that it's
going to be done right and not
influenced by the big tech giants that
are looking to again commoditize our
data and our people.
We need to get back to the principles of
America that made us great. We are the
laboratories of democracy and if we want
to push this policy, we need a critical
mass of states that align with these
policies, adopt these principles and we
will see mass implementation and mass
adoption of these types of principles
and policies because the states are
going to lead out and and that's why
that's why you're here. We need you to
help us. We need you to join with us and
your idea might might look just a little
bit different and that's okay. But if
the states are working together and
leading this effort, the
interoperability that people are
concerned about will happen naturally
because we're working together. And we
don't have to rely on the federal
government, nor should we. That's not
how our that's not how our country was
set up. We can find the solution here.
And and we encourage you to join us.
So I think since I'm last, this is what
I want to say. Um, we have worked
together as as a group in our state and
we would like to now extend that out to
other states and start bringing each of
you in. We'll talk to you oneon-one.
That's what we've done here. Anytime
there's somebody who has questions,
Chris will go and talk to them. Now,
there's only one Chris, so we can't we
can't uh we we don't want to spend him.
But what we can do is help people to
understand this one-on-one. Nobody that
we've talked to that I'm aware of has
been opposed to this once they
understood it. So, I think the key is
educating people on what it is we're
trying to do and what the stakes are.
And the stakes are very high. So for
future generations, let's work together
and let's get this done.
Thank you. Let's give him a round of
applause.
Bless you.
Hello. Okay, great. Uh, my name is
Daniel Hard. I am CTO of a company that
um is in the tele space. I've been
working in identity for many years and
um I got an almost impossible assignment
uh from uh Christopher and crew uh which
is to try to summarize the state of the
identity landscape
um in 10 minutes
and uh that's almost impossible because
there's so much that's happening and
that has been happening. So, uh, you
know, being a progressive thinker here,
I I said, I'll ask AI to help me find a
list of things that are going on in the
space. Now, I knew that this was going
to generate massive amounts of stuff.
So, I said, just find um 40 headlines
um that uh have been in the news
recently in English about things that
are going on in identity that have been
widely reported. So um
this is what it came up with and this is
uh of course an AI summary but the point
of this is not the specific headlines.
The main point of it is how many of them
there are and how hard it was even for
the AI to pick from uh all the different
things that are going on in the space.
Um and as I was watching this uh list
come in from AI, what was going through
my head is that Billy Joel song, We
Didn't Start the Fire. you know what I'm
talking about. Um there's just so much
that's happening and it's virtually
impossible or overwhelming to keep track
of it all. So, uh to summarize in 10
minutes is very hard. But what I'm going
to do is I'm going to try to explain how
it looks to me as a practitioner in the
space um at a high level. I'm going to
make some generalizations.
These generalizations are partly
subjective. Um, but I think they're a
useful mental model for uh for uh people
to understand if you're not thinking
about identity all the time and you want
to kind of wrap your brain around it.
So um uh my generalizations basically
say that there have been three waves of
innovation in identity and um I would
start the really and this is digital
identity by the way. I would start these
waves going back to something like maybe
the Diffy Helman. Uh Diffy Helman was a
cryptographic technique that was
invented in 1976. You could possibly go
back to email which was a little bit
earlier than Diffy Helman, but anyway.
And then um I I would say that there's a
uh these three bands of or waves of
innovation and they have characteristics
that are
common or commonalities in the way they
think about things.
um these aren't exactly
um you know uh perfectly aligned
technologies in each of these bands, but
they have these common characteristics.
So
um not sure what happened there. Maybe
my No, my laptop's still alive. Um I'm
going to keep talking. Um uh maybe we
can get it to come back up.
Okay. So, um the first band here, um
central or federated governance, um it
was an assumption that uh when you built
identity systems initially, um there was
going to be some central body that did
it for you. And um it was an assumption
that you were going to use this brand
new cool thing called Diffy Helman and
this brand new cool thing called
asymmetric cryptography and all that
kind of good stuff. And that you were
going to use keys and certificates. that
was kind of the the uh new kid on the
block that was cool at the beginning and
a lot of innovation has happened since
then that kind of keeps those key
assumptions.
Um, and by the way, when I represent
these uh three bands here, I'm not
saying that there's, you know, bad and
and okay and and better so much as I'm
saying it's kind of like uh a classic
car that had a carburetor and then a car
that has a fuel injector and a computer
and then an electric car or something.
These are these are waves of technology.
Okay. There are reasons though why we
learn from our experience.
And so um there is thinking in these
later bands that looks back at what was
done in the earlier bands and says there
might be a better way to do this and
there's advantages uh to you know
tweaking our me mental model. So the
second band of identity uh innovation I
would kind of track back HIPPA is kind
of an outlier in the fact that it it
came about pretty early and by the way
HIPPA has Utah roots. I didn't know that
until yesterday I was talking to
somebody but anyway um really kind of
when when blockchain started impinging
on people's consciousness
um there were a number of things that
people said oh wait a minute that means
there's a different way that we could do
this. Oh there's a different way we
could do that. and a comp there were
some dominoes that fell and it brought
about this yellow band of thinking. And
um the thing that's different mainly
between the red and the yellow is that
we're using generation 2 techniques.
We're we're not identifying people by
keys now. We're identifying people by
identifiers
and um we're using probably upgraded
cryptography like elliptic curve and so
forth. And um there's a lot of
blockchain, although it's not all
blockchain oriented in in the yellow
band. Um but there's a lot of the notion
of uh wallets, digital wallets was a big
deal. And then um there a lot of
dissonance around privacy issues uh as
this yellow band kind of came about.
The third wave of thinking here, this
green band is typified in my mind by a
much more sophisticated and nuanced view
about the um governance uh that has to
be in place.
Um and that doesn't mean that people be
that are, you know, making yellowbanded
stuff or red banded stuff are ignorant
about uh governance by any means, but uh
it's kind of like playing a symphony.
There's a lot of different instruments
and I think in the green band the full
range of instruments is now um much more
apparent
and um big emphasis on auditability of
what's going on in a system and a big
inf uh emphasis on recoverability.
If something goes wrong and you assume
in the green band that things will go
wrong. So the question becomes what do
you do when things go wrong? Not how do
you prevent things from going wrong
which is an unrealistic question in some
ways.
Um and um there's different
cryptographic primitives. There's
identifiers yes but they're upgraded to
autonomic identifiers which have certain
uh desirable properties
so forth. Uh and an emphasis on uh look
postquantum is going to be a reality
soon. Are we ready for it? It would be
really foolish to build an identity
system that's not ready for postquantum
at this point when um NIST has already
announced postquantum uh standards.
Okay, so enough on that slide. I can't
spend that much time because there's
just uh like I said 10 minutes is nearly
impossible here. Um what I see in the
market is that there's major tensions.
Um there's uh things that are pulling uh
solutions to the yellow and the red
bands and uh you can see what I've said
roughly uh kind of argues for uh yellow
and red solutions today.
And then there's things that pull people
towards the green uh direction when
they're designing solutions.
Um enough said on that. I I I could go
into this for hours, but um let me just
talk about the two biggest forces that I
see in the market today.
Um I uh just returned from living in
Europe for several years. So I've lived
personally through the uh EUDI
initiative a little bit and uh what's
going on there. And the EUDI initiative
uh has enormous
enormous momentum. It's a juggernaut in
Europe.
Um but it doesn't it's not without its
challenges. Um uh many different
countries have built systems and they
kind of don't all get along. Um but
they're trying really hard and um
the uh the state of play in the United
States is a little bit different. You
have um
state level initiatives which is why
this conference makes so much sense.
States are making the decisions, not a a
central government. There are things
that are being built with um generation
one solutions or generation 2 solutions
in the United States. Absolutely. Um
SETI is an example of a generation 3
solution. Um and there's reasons why I
think that's really exciting.
Um the strategic trends that I'm aware
of, uh I'll I'm not going to, you know,
say them all, but you can read them
there. I'll just say that uh the thing I
would bet on uh bet my bottom dollar on
is that last bullet.
Security pressures are going to grow and
legal pressures are going to grow. I
guarantee that's going to be true if
nothing else that I can forecast. That
one's for sure. Remember um what that
might imply about what kinds of
solutions are wise.
Um I'd like to end with a a thought here
and that is um we sometimes hear
solutions described in terms of formats.
So you're going to hear today about ISO
mobile drivers licenses and you're going
to hear about W3C verifi verifiable
credentials and so forth. I think that's
the wrong way to think about decisions.
Um up here you have two pictures of the
same person and uh one of them is the
lossless view that you get off of a
digital camera when you take an image
and the other one is a JPEG. Now are
JPEGs bad? No. We use them all the time
and they're very useful. But if you're a
professional graphic artist, you would
never want to deal in JPEGs when you as
inputs to your graphic projects. So they
have different uses
and I'd like to suggest that permanent
evidence
needs to be lossless evidence and there
are a number of um dimensions to
losslessness. There's time related
dimensions like how long does this
evidence persist.
There's governance related dimensions to
evidence.
There's postquantum cryptography related
dimensions to evidence and losslessness.
There's all kinds of stuff. So, I'd like
to just suggest that as you um run into
conversations about this, don't make it
a debate about formats.
Make it a debate about how to solve
problems. And you'll find that the
format questions fall out.
Thank you. That's all I'm going to do.
My
like
to know things about the subjects of the
identity system. The identity is
centralized. It's owned and it's
private. When I say private, I don't
mean privacy. I mean it's private to
Amazon. They own it. We call these
administrative identity systems because
they're designed to administer identity
for a specific purpose in a specific
domain.
Um in this case it's Amazon, but you
know there are millions of them. The
system, the identifiers, how they work,
are owned and controlled by Amazon.
They're the subject of Amazon's terms
and conditions.
They're useful for establishing trust
within a domain, but they're not useful
for establishing trust across domains.
People are party to dozens, hundreds,
thousands of these things. I have over a
thousand entries in my one password.
In contrast, decentralized identity
flips that model. The person becomes the
center of trust and credentials about
that trust flow through protocols rather
than platforms.
Unlike decentralized the decentralized
identity model, decentralized identity
provides a consistent experience for
interacting with all of the
relationships in your digital life. But
decentralization alone isn't enough.
What we really need is what I think is
called per first person identity. A way
for people to act as themselves online,
not as managed accounts. I like the term
first person identity better than
decentralized because it's more clearly
distinguishes that identity is based on
the individual the first party in a
relationship. First person describes an
idea that most people understand
naturally. We're taught about we're
taught this in grade school.
First person is I, me, myself, mine.
First person describes precisely the
kind of thinking that will allow people
to create their own online relationships
without an intermediating administrator
like a social network. In first person
identity, you might have relationships
and credentials from your employer, from
your bank, from your school, from the
driver's license bureau, and so on. You
can use these alone or in combination to
prove things about yourself. In
first-person identity, people are the
integration point for information about
themselves.
Now, why does this matter so much? It
matters because something essential is
missing in our digital lives.
Maybe
There we go. The real challenge online
isn't utility or convenience. It's
proximity. In the physical world, we're
next to each other. We rely on tacit
knowledge that we gain from our senses
to see. When we see and speak with
people, we use this tacit information to
establish trust.
We don't have that online. Online, we
interact at a distance through screens
and systems and platforms that usually
are not controlled by us. Our
relationships are mediated by companies
rather than being direct.
Let's talk about what that distance
costs us and how endorsement rather than
control can close it.
Deart didn't say I have a Google login
therefore I am.
He said I think therefore I am. We exist
independent of anything else around us.
Now
that's where endorsement comes in.
It it bridges the gap of distance. It
allows people
or anything half a world away
to trust who you are because you your
own state endorses
what you're saying your assertions that
you're making. SETI state endorsed
digital identity doesn't give you an
identity. You already have one.
Rather SETI endorses it. provides the
assurance we need to act confidently
across digital distances. So the problem
isn't that we lack digital IDs. We've
got plenty of those. I've got a
thousand. It's that we lack standing in
the online world. We are ghosts
existing only through the grace of some
company.
We are not embodied autonomous agents.
Saidi changes that. Again, it doesn't
create your identity. It endorses it and
gives you the ability to act across
distance
that can lead to something much bigger.
A chance to reclaim our digital freedom.
Firsterson identity represents a chance
for us to declare our independence in
the digital realm
to regain the freedom to act as
ourselves. SETI enables that by
supporting the individual and giving
each of us a place to stand online.
Freedom in a digital world begins when
we act from our own identity, not one
assigned to us and mediated by someone
else.
This is our moment to build a digital
world that honors human dignity.
a world where we are free to live and
act as ourselves
as digital citizens rather than digital
subjects.
If we don't build it, someone else will
and it will reflect their goals. Goals
that probably don't align with the ones
we think they should have.
For Utah, this is a chance to lead by
example, demonstrating that trust in
identity can scale without surveillance.
Across the US, SETI can mark a shift
from digital subjects to digital
citizens, people who live effective
online lives with agency and respect. We
have the opportunity to build a digital
world that respects human dignity. A
world where people are free to live and
act for themselves. Let's not squander
that opportunity.
All right, we're going to see if I get
to keep my geek card here.
Yes.
Okay. Uh today I want to talk about the
evolution of technology and how backward
compatibility is essential for growth.
Technologies are in a constant state of
change and they're always adding new
features and enhanced functionality to
meet growing demands.
The three phones that you see here are a
perfect illustration of this. Uh they
represent the dramatic evolution of the
simple telephone over just the last 30
years. uh from from a device tethered to
a wall to a portable gadget for calls
and eventually text messages uh to the
powerful computer we all carry in our
pockets now. The infrastructure to
support the corded and uh the corded and
smartphones are still in place today,
but the first generation of mobile
devices no longer function. This
progression is a familiar story, but it
holds important lessons for the future
of other technologies, including digital
identity. And the progress shown here is
not always guaranteed.
So I want to talk about two ubiquitous
internet technologies that we all use
every day but don't think about. Some of
you may not even know these exist. Um
but they were both introduced around 30
years ago and their path to adoption
have been significantly different. The
first is IPv6 and was introduced in
December of 1995 and it's so
foundational to the internet that it's
literally called the internet protocol.
Um, IPv6 is the successor to the
original internet protocol and it has
struggled to gain traction only reaching
about 50% market share today despite
decades of effort and superior
capabilities. The second technology is
802.11,
also known as Wi-Fi. It was first
introduced and standardized in 1997
and then Wi-Fi has been a massive
success. It's been it's seen seven major
releases each one faster and more
capable than the last and has become an
indispensable part of our daily lives.
So why the difference in adoption?
Backward compatibility. Uh Wi-Fi was
designed from the ground up to be
backward compatible. Each new generation
of Wi-Fi routers and devices could still
communicate with the older ones. This
created a smooth, seamless upgrade path
for everyone. IPv6 however was not
backward compatible with its
predecessor. This meant that the
transition
uh required a complete and often costly
overhaul of network infrastructure.
Uh this major difference is the primary
reason why Wi-Fi's adoption has
progressed so smoothly while IPv6's
adoption has been a long slow struggle.
Another way to allow for continuous
improvement of technologies is to ensure
compatibility with alternative
standards. Uh to illustrate this, think
of the audio codecs that power our
digital music and podcasts. Many
different standards like Flack, Meg, and
Opus coexist today. For the vast
majority of us, the complex process of
encoding and decoding audio is
completely transparent. We just push
play. Each codec is optimized for a
specific situation, whether it's
streaming highfidelity music or ensuring
a clear voice call over a weak
connection. While this isn't ideal, the
ecosystem works because applications
have the ability to handle the different
types of audio files seamlessly
switching codecs as needed. New codecs
can be added to the ecosystem while old
ones are eventually retired.
So just like these other technologies,
digital identity is at a crossroads. We
have a mix of established legacy systems
and emerging innovative solutions. The
challenge is figuring out how to move
forward without immediately abandoning
the significant events investments we've
already made and without destroying the
user experience or preventing progress.
A core principle of the SETI framework
is to support backward compatibility. We
believe the only viable path forward is
one that embraces interoperability with
existing options without being confi
confined by them. This approach will
allow organizations to continue using
their existing investments and
infrastructure while providing a clear
path to upgrade to newer, more secure
and more capable technologies over time.
It ensures that progress doesn't require
starting from scratch or forcing
adoption of a single solution across the
ecosystem.
To show you what this looks like in
practice, we're going to do live demos.
We realize the risk in that. Um, so I'm
I'm pleased to introduce the
participants for our technical
demonstrations today. Um, and I'll
invite them to start coming up on the
stage here. Uh, in the upcoming demos
for this session and and later this
afternoon, they'll showcase how several
of the currently available identity
technologies can be used together in a
cohesive and interoperable ecosystem.
While no technologies for study have
been chosen, they will present possible
scenarios utilizing several different
technologies working together for the
first time. You'll notice how the user
experience is similar despite
differences in the underlying
technologies. Um, so if you could start
making your way to the stage as I as I
introduce you. Um,
first we have
Spruce ID. They're a US-based company
whose mission is to give people control
over their identity and data across all
digital interactions. Here you go,
Wayne. Um, Wayne Chang is here. And
their software powers secure
standardsbased credentials such as
mobile driver's licenses and verifiable
digital credentials that can be used
both online and in person across
government and enterprise services. As a
leader in the decentralized identity and
credential interoperability space,
Spruce's technology supports selective
disclosure, unlinkability, and no phone
home verification. Their work with
states, federal agencies, and standards
bodies demonstrates how digital identity
can enhance access to services,
strengthen security, and preserve user
autonomy in a connected world. Um, get
Group North America uh is a US-based
company specializing in identity
management solutions with over 40 years
of experience supporting governments
worldwide and has been a leader in
digital identity since 2017. get was
selected to deploy the technology for
Utah's mobile driver's license in 2021,
helping Utah citizens securely share
their MDL details, prove their age, and
maintain their privacy. The company has
worked with government agencies and
businesses to accept and verify MDLs,
including the TSA, Utah Highway Patrol,
UCCCU, and AFCU AFCU credit unions. And
then last, they'll be presenting later,
but their technology is used in these
demonstrations. The Cardano Foundation
is not is a notfor-profit organization
based in Switzerland which provides
promotes the education, development and
adoption of decentralized technologies
to build futurep proof industry
solutions. Vidian is an open- source
digital identity platform developed by
the foundation that delivers secure
enterprise ready verification services
which protect user data and prevent
fraud. Um, Ver Vidian's credential ma
management platform led by Thomas
Mayfield implements self-s sovereign
identity for individuals and
organizations and Vidian's core
objective is to ensure authentic
communications and verifiable identity
protocols are easily accessible to all.
So, I want to personally thank all of
the presenters um for our technical
demonstrations today. They put this
together in a matter of weeks and um
we're really excited to see these
technologies working together for the
first time. So I'll turn the time over
to them.
Thanks so much Joe. Really grateful for
the opportunity to be here and talk more
about the different approaches
especially in the context of how do we
start with individual rights, think
about the policy before we rush to the
technology, right? because there's an
implicit social contract, right? That is
the use of these digital identity
systems and it is much better for that
to be an explicit one rather than one
that is the most convenient or imposed
or anything else, right? So, I think
we're all here for the same thing and
being able to move towards that. I have
a pretty nerdy quote actually that I
want to start with uh from a fantasy
novel by Brandon Sanderson.
Then be wise about it. There are two
kinds of important people, Shalon. Some
when the boulder of time rolls towards
them, plant themselves before it and
throw out their hands. All their lives
they've been told how great they are.
They assume the world itself will bend
to their whims as a caregiver once did
when fetching a fresh cup of milk. Those
people end up squished. Others step to
the side as the boulder passes, but are
quick to say, "See what I did? I made it
roll there. Don't make me do it again."
These are the ones who get everyone else
squished. Is there not a third type of
person? There is, but they are rare.
These know they can't stop the boulder.
They walk beside it, study it, and b
their time. Then they nudge it ever so
slightly to bend its path. These are the
ones who actually change the world. And
they terrify me. For people never see as
far as they think they do. And I think
the wisdom in that is it takes a
diversity of thought, approaches, and
use cases and opinions to actually
consider all the different facets of
this. It's an enormously complex and
ambitious undertaking to build digital
identity in a way that minimizes the
harms, but we're able to derive most of
the benefits. So, I'm really happy that
we're in a room with a ton of diverse
thinkers from people who are experts on
individual rights, what constituents
care about, what people actually feel,
the technology itself, including the
cryptography, security and privacy
aspects of it, adoption, change
management, and user experience. Right?
So uh I think that um we're very excited
to show how these concepts from SETI
where you start with the policy and the
rights and then the technology is
figured out after that right that's
really what we want to showcase and how
it can help our existing investments uh
we can derive value from those and um
especially in uh as we saw with the
adoption right MDL it's in uh I think 17
states at this point uh a lot of invest
ment. A lot of great security people
have been thinking about that model. The
TSA spent over $250 million uh on
machines that can accept the MDL, right?
So, is that all to waste if it doesn't
comply or what are we thinking about
here? Right? What about everything else?
And fortunately, uh you might even be
able to shed some more light on this.
Yeah, thanks and thanks for taking all
our five minutes. uh but uh uh it it's
been uh actually an honor honor to uh
work uh with Utah uh excellent team,
excellent people. It it has been uh a
fantastic experience and we're really
happy of course with all the work that
they perform and we had the honor to
support them to have a successful MDL uh
issued and being used and utilized in uh
many not enough uh use cases and relying
parties including TSA and credit unions
and law enforcement. But uh we're happy
to be also part of this group uh that
Chris put together to uh assist the best
we can with our experience and knowledge
and technology to make whatever next uh
steps Utah chooses to take successful.
So
it's easy.
So what are we seeing over there?
Um that's a verifier. A verifier is
something that a reliant party would
have. A reliant party being anything
anyone that accepts and consumes a
digital identity and MDL. Uh, and that
can be a government agency that ask for
your ID. It can be law enforcement, it
can be anyone in the private sector,
could be a bank, could be age restricted
alcohol sales, tobacco and so on.
whenever they ask uh for that uh ID card
of yours, driver license, uh you can
present the MDL or at least that is the
purpose and you can use verifiers as
simple as an app uh or in a fix point
with a scanner uh or eventually online.
Uh all that technology exists and
hopefully it's going to be part of the
ecosystem we all operate in. Can you
talk about what's going to happen
between this SETI wallet um and what
what kind of you know how is the data
transmitted um what happens between this
application running on your phone and
application that holds a credential on
my phone? Well, um, yeah, originally the
ISO standard, which is what the UTM MDL
is complying to, along with close to 20
other jurisdictions that issue an MDL
that complies to the ISO
18013-5,
which is the in-person uh standard. Um,
it had a phone home, it had a connection
to the system of record that is no
longer the case. And similarly uh any
verification we would conduct with the
city it will only consume whatever you
have on the phone and you um present
and it goes uh this could work in the
mountains right if there's no internet
or anything
it will be it will be done offline
because again it it will
cryptographically
uh analyze whatever you have provisioned
in your phone as your digital identity.
I always really like this part where it
goes over Bluetooth and NFC proximity
technologies that involve no servers,
right? It's just peer-to-peer over
device. That's actually the best privacy
profile you could hope for, right? So,
there are parts that have had
extraordinary investments that are
really valuable from a privacy and
usability perspective. And what we see
in that wallet is not an MDL. There's no
driving privileges there. It is uh a
credential that is solely focused on
identification, right? And that the
reason that it is a SETI credential is
that it conforms to the code in SETI
right is the idea. So if we start
looking over here, I told you it would
be a nerdy presentation, right? We look
in the Utah code, right? And there is
SETI enshrined in it as statutes. And
when you click end, you're able to see
the different definitions and
requirement from Senate Bill 260 that
was signed into law by Governor Coxin
earlier this spring. Uh and thank you
to, you know, Representative and Senator
for the work uh and the whole coalition.
So it's really about controls. It's
really about these are the things we're
expecting this credential to do and
operate, right? That's what it
represents.
So data formats, everything else, those
are things to figure out. But making it
policy based and starting it from there
is the most important part because that
is the social contract, right? To
express the will of a people and have
those as the agreed upon controls if
someone is to participate in the system.
So we just wanted to demonstrate that
this model right can also work with the
corpus of investment for existing
systems that have been significant and
growing in adoption. So we have looked
into the mobile driver's license
technical specification.
Sure.
We have looked at the subcomponent
called a mobile document or an MDO and
that is just a data format that doesn't
describe how to use it or anything else.
And there are other pieces that we can
build up to that we can agree with and
are aligned to the SETI framework.
Right? So that is the idea and what
you're going to see with this
demonstration.
And similar of course any digital
identity the the benefits are you're not
using your card. You don't share your
card. You don't show any information.
It's not copied. You don't flash past
so-cal whatever it is on the phone. uh
and it respects the privacy of the user
and you only share what you choose. So
uh if you want just your age uh to enter
a bar or alcohol sales that's that is
all you share, not the entire ID. Unless
of course you're at a bank, you're
applying for a loan or law enforcement
is asking for the entire uh ID. That is
when you share if you choose uh the
entire information.
That's right. And the MD do data format
to your point supports selective
disclosure as part of that base. We like
that. We're like, "Okay, that sounds
pretty good. Let's take that part."
Right. So, we're gonna demonstrate.
And there's no contact. You you can do
it's a QR barcode uh uh scanning uh it
is uh via Bluetooth uh through a good
range or a tap NFC just like as everyone
is familiar with the uh Apple Pay and so
on.
Yep. So let's say that we're in a use
case where let's call it law
enforcement. Let's say there is
warranted uh ability to request
information, right? So uh there's going
to be a lot of it being requested.
You can see there it says all info. So
I'm asking for uh all of the information
from the user.
But this can be tailored to different
profiles depending on the context. And
that's the really important policy work
we need help with to figure out.
So, I'm going to share the identity by
um creating a QR code. You can either
tap or create a QR code to share it.
What it does is it brokers a secure
connection over Bluetooth. So, the adds
encryption on top of Bluetooth because
Bluetooth itself has challenges. That's
how the MDL protocol worked. That part
of the MDO and standard seemed to be
pretty promising. And we were able to
show a QR code. So we're bringing up the
scanner
uh no contact
and uh actually it's going to consume.
Yep. I get to decide what I share or
not. Um over here on this screen those
are the fields requested as the user. I
get to make the determination. That's
another feature of the protocol that was
supported. And when I press approve,
it's transmitted over uh basically the
Bluetooth connection peer-to-peer. So
this would work in the mountains without
any kind of external connectivity,
right? And again, this is being used at
a ton of airports already, right? So
we're just able to make sure that that
part of the technology can also work for
STI credentials.
So um you can see that uh I'm seeing the
information that he shared. I can bring
up the picture, do one last visual check
if I wish. Um, and it has a document
information, so I know it's from Utah,
the document number,
and and that's about it. Yeah.
As simple as that. Plus, of course, I
have the verification on the age
verification.
Yeah. Well, let's say I'm at a bar,
right, at night, and I want to show I'm
over 21, but kind of don't want you to
know my full name and where I live, my
address, right? How do we do that?
So, um I will just uh the one that is
asking for the information can can ask
only for the age.
Yeah.
So, unlike of what you choose, I can
only ask for the age and whatever you
share, I would only get the age. Um and
of course, as you saw, once my I leave
that uh verified information I had uh is
is gone. It's not saved. It's not
tracked, none of that. And you cannot
get a screenshot.
Yeah. So the policy consideration here
is that there are many different
attributes that you could add to this
thing and ask for. Right. So those are
the really important decisions to be
made. Can we add veteran status,
disability rating, can we add how many
dependents you have? These are all
really relevant for programs like Wix
and others that require expedient
access, but we also want to eliminate
the fraud, right? So, and because it's
the user consenting to display the
information, you don't really have to go
with one of these very complex inter
agency data sharing agreements. If we
faithfully present an opportunity
consent for people, right? So, if it's
tough to do across agencies and
coordinate, just give it to the person
and let them decide. Right.
All right. So, um I know your age, you
you're looking too young to me.
Thank you.
Oh. Um, is this the right one that
you've requested? Did you configure it
to just select the age only?
Just the age.
Well, see, now I have the opportunity to
deny all this.
If you agree, I want to only see the
the age.
You can up
try again.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
the the old info.
Yeah, because uh there is an option also
to request identifying info or uh to
toggle that off,
right?
Because that was on.
Oh, for age. Okay.
Yeah.
Okay. So now I can let him in.
So you turn on the safety.
Um age over 18. Got a different set of
things requested. But you know what? I'm
really just going to get rid of all
these things except for my portrait and
age and uh that's all you're going to
get and uh there the verify will have to
deal with it. So I think there is a
setting where I've definitely seen it
work with this app though.
So you want to try again?
Sure.
Yeah. Let's give it a try.
And you you say okay.
So um those are the only data fields
that ever left the wallet right during
that specific interaction. So yeah um
see us after we'll definitely show that
you can do an age uh demonstration. I
think that um I have a version of the GT
mobile app where I can just ask for the
age of mine but um you'll see other for
uh you'll see other profiles where we
can get it. So
great. We have uh two more things to
show you uh really quickly
and one of them has to do
step. Okay, great.
And that was I'm on by the way.
Yeah.
Okay. Thanks.
Welcome. Thank you. All right. So
the other two use cases.
One is banking and uh it's very
important for people to get access to
financial services. many of the same
methods are more or less used uh for
benefits distribution when you're trying
to figure out eligibility and identity
verification for some of those things.
Right? So, this is a generally useful
flow. In fact, um
NIST has this national cyber security
center of excellence, right? and we're
trying to figure out how are we going to
do banking KYC with the mobile driver's
license. I see some folks in here who
are actually formal participants in this
program. So that's great because a lot
of federal agencies and other states are
going to look to the output of this
program and how that's going to work.
There are a lot of banks, a lot of tech
companies, a lot of other actors and uh
basically we're trying to figure out how
do we preserve privacy but also allow
for these kinds of use cases.
They're even talking about shapes that
it's going to work, but right now it's
just called the MDL program. There's no
reason why it needs to be. It could just
be digital identities, right? But that's
kind of the only thing that popped up,
right? So to have a credential that has
SETI controls over it would be very
interesting I think.
But back to our banking example and this
is where a lot of tech companies have
invested a ton of effort. their best UX
people, their best uh you know security
folks. How do we make this really good?
And uh the interface is mostly for the
MDL but those technologists have agreed
that hey you know other things might be
acceptable here passports eids in Europe
are not driver's licenses right so MDL
isn't so strongly applicable in some
areas so how do we allow a diversity of
different credential types to be
accepted and uh there have been great uh
strides in the user experience towards
this so we're going to basically open a
fictitious bank account.
And um I'm also going to make sure that
I can show you what happens in the
wallet alongside that. If I can figure
out how to make this small again.
There we go.
So, we're at Arch's Bank. We're going to
open an account. We're going to begin
our banking application
and type in our email.
I'll just uh
imagine that I get a confirmation code.
You've probably done this before. Go to
your email, you find the code, you put
it in. Want multiffactor. So, right now
it's a phone number, but you know,
future approaches like pass keys and
digital credentials will hopefully
relieve the need for this. So, put a
phone number in there. Same deal. Again,
many banking systems just work like this
today.
And a social security number is required
by Fenson's customer identification
program. So that's a bank secrecy act
requirement. So you know you'll just see
it as a requirement for banks. But at
this stage it's part of identity
verification, right? And what a lot of
institutions do today is they say, "Hey,
upload a picture of your driver's
license or upload a picture of your
utility bill." And none of those
security features are actually valid
when you just take a picture of it,
right? Like that's the new world of
security needs to be built on things
that AI is bad at. That's showing up in
person. That's breaking cryptography,
especially post-quantum cryptography.
That's making very complex computational
predictions about physics and how light
refracts on things or how um you know
something can change geomet
geometrically and that's what a lot of
the livveness algorithms are about. But
it all starts with having a really um
strongly certified credential.
And when you want to verify with it,
then it uses the operating system level
controls to say, "Hey, do you want to
share your data?" It's built on the same
technologies as pass keys. Actually, if
you look under the hood,
we want to share it. QR code comes up.
We see on the wallet. I'll scan it. You
won't be able to see everything. I think
there are some like privacy protections
with the screen share, but you'll be
able to see the important parts. So, it
tells me only connect to devices you
trust. And when I connect, what happens?
You'll see a lower popover.
This is kind of like the Apple Pay
experience or the Google Pay experience.
It's part of the operating system and
you get to pick which wallet it comes
out of, right? You've been requested a
credential from somewhere. We're going
to agree. And again, we have that
opportunity to consent what gets sent,
right? If we send it then what happens
is instantaneously a cryptographic
payload is sent along with the data
fields and that can be verified by a
server. So it goes to from the phone to
the laptop goes from the laptop to the
server and then uh it gets verified way
easier and more secure than uploading
all those different documents. You
submit and you're good to go.
So getting easy access to financial
services, benefits, a slew of other
things requires really good UX, but we
can't compromise on individual rights.
We can't compromise on security as we
get there, right? So let's take those
existing investments that companies put
their best UX and security people on and
apply it to a framework that is
individual rights driven. Right? So
that's the proposal for ensuring
backwards compatibility to a lot of
these systems. A lot of the time you
think legacy old experience but these
are actually some really great
experiences happening right and the last
thing I'll show is interoperability with
a completely different system. Uh this
uh is the same technology harness. Um
thank you for the Vidian team for
providing their issuance portal for this
part of the demo. So different company
not Spruce ID. It's not like one company
built all this stuff. These are
interoperable protocols and there's
something called the global legal entity
identifier foundation that is able to do
identification for organizations to a
high degree of proofing so that we can
know who we're doing business with if a
company wants to get a benefit or
something else. Right? So basically I
want to have another credential on my
phone where I can have that employee
badge or proof that I'm part of an
organization. Let's say I'm going to ask
someone else for a credential or I want
to open a business banking account.
These are useful to understand what
entity I'm associated with. What if
you're part of LEO and you want to show
that you're a real cop and you're not
trying to just co someone to do
something, right? So, you can issue a
credential for this.
There's some numbers as part of it. I'll
put my name. We'll just say employee
and we'll issue the credential. This is
a totally different technology stack
built on Kerry and AC/DC's uh which were
protocol and format invented right here
in Utah. You get to accept it and a new
credential shows up as an official
organization role. And then when we want
to go request it, we can request a
presentation from that wallet.
The wallets have been linked uh prior.
It's a demo.
Request a presentation.
we will see the request happening and
approving it we'll see the request is uh
updated right and these are different
data formats entirely but following the
same control principles right so that's
the end of my demo and my time thank you
so much for your attention And
our presentation by Representative
Cutler
on the role of the state and how to keep
the feds out of our business.
That was that'll be a later discussions.
My boss is here. Marvin Dodge. I hope
that joke didn't get me in trouble.
You don't last long with a personality
like mine.
Uh
so this is going to uh be 10 minutes and
then we're actually going to do break
out into two uh breakouts uh before
lunch. I'll give some instructions after
this for that.
Fantastic. Thank you. Thanks for putting
the break. I think the sound will work.
I I will see if the sound works. We uh
if not, we'll bring our live demo team
back up here to help. So I I I brought a
couple of friends with me to uh to help.
Let's seeuh what they have to say. And
the sound did not work.
Your sound up.
It's going to be off.
Little thing next to it.
You already
It was It was uh muted though.
Okay,
one more. One more try.
Welcome to Utah, folks.
Digital identity is fabulous.
We can
It's really great.
You're going to want one. What is
uh move forward without the sound? Uh
we had the president. Well,
you want to try one more time?
Sure.
What is Oh, hey. All right.
Welcome to Utah, folks. Digital identity
is fabulous. It's really great. You're
going to want one. What is the state's
role in digital identity? Wait, am I not
in charge of all the digital identity
around here?
Wait, if you if you
if you see him, tell him he is in
charge. That'll be just fine.
We we've all seen lots of evidence of
the challenges uh with digital identity,
the breaches that are happening around
the world uh often with governments
involved uh in these and uh let's talk
about what the role of the state is
compared to the role of the federal
government or the role of of private
industry and I would uh suggest to you
that the role of the state as we have
heard so many times s is not to control
or to create but to endorse and the
reason it's important for the state to
be involved is a matter of trust. Uh in
our society some of our largest tech
companies have lost the trust and the
trust needs to come back to the
individual and as as uh Phil Wley
presented put the individual back in
control. So uh let's uh try this again
and on on what the state's role is.
Look, this is important. Um the role of
the state is to endorse, verify,
authenticate, protect and guarantee an
individual's digital identity. This is
even more important. Personally, I
really like control, but the role of the
state is not to own, create, control,
gatekeep, or surveil an individual's
digital identity.
Right? We in the age of AI, you know,
even a legislator can create terrible
videos, right? That that could fool
somebody who's not paying attention.
But uh I I think we uh understand the
the the points there.
Historically, the state has had a
significant role in identity. Often we
think of oh well you know the feds have
a passport the feds provide a social
security number but it this goes back to
the presentation before the root is
typic the root of the identity is
typically a state endorsed credential.
We often start with a birth certificate
that in most cases is issued by a state
and the state handles most of the vital
records. They're often used by others in
private industry or by the feds, but the
vital records is primarily a state
responsibility.
Uh
this was mentioned earlier, but I think
this is really important in the crux of
our argument for a state endorsed
digital identity. In the tech world
where many of us live, there is often uh
a call for expediency h and for
efficiency. It's more efficient to use
this or it's easier to adopt VHS than
beta. It's easier to adopt uh or some
people believe, you know, they like the
Android interface or the iPhone uh or
iOS interface.
If we start with
efficiency as our value, then we will
get a completely different set of
products than if we value protection,
security, and privacy.
I think if there's anything we've
learned over the past few years and when
we think about social media, we think
about online fraud is that we have to be
more purposeful in designing our
identity systems and in the systems that
are going to be used by millions and
millions of people because if we make a
mistake
that that mistake scales again and
again. So our argument is to think
carefully about your values. What are
your values as a state? What are your
values as an individual? Do we do we put
our rights protecting our children at
the top of our list? I many people would
argue that in designing social media,
child protection was not the top value.
And and over the years, we've had to pay
a price for that as things have changed.
and that because that wasn't the most
important value in designing these
systems.
Our argument is that we should protect
the vulnerable.
You've all read the articles of people
uh vulnerable adults, vulnerable
children getting scammed by people. But
we heard a heartbreaking story today of
what can happen uh when
a a bad actor takes advantage of
somebody. We must look at our values and
put our most important personal values,
our most important moral values at the
top of the list and not let efficiency,
interoperability or profit take over the
design of our identity systems. Those
of you in the in the world of designing
systems understand that
we have to think big and we have to
consider a lot of different elements in
our uh governance framework. We've got
to consider how are we going to audit
these systems. What are the open
protocols? Because historically we have
to agree on a protocol and a standard to
get mass uh adoption.
We have to think about how will this be
enforced. We we saw an example just a
minute ago. Okay. If if the enforcement
and the verifier is so uh ubiquitous
that it can be put on a mobile app
that'll reduce the cost to install
readers uh in in all of our places.
uh should we
have a right to paper? That's going to
be a debate that I think many of us uh
will experience. Our friends in the UK
have said everybody gets a digital
identity. We have some people who don't
want a digital identity. How do we help
them move forward when 95% or 99% of the
world is moving to digital transactions?
Can we build transparency into the
system so we can identify fraud? Will we
prevent all fraud? You of all people
know
preventing all fraud is impossible. But
can we make the systems transparent so
that we can identify that fraud earlier
and quicker so we can take uh steps to
reduce that fraud uh as as we go
forward. Okay. Uh la last I'll leave you
with this thought is that comparing the
state controlled identity which we've
been talking about and and certainly we
have some examples of that in in other
countries compared to uh a user
controlled or a liberty based model
and we discussed many of those key
elements. selective disclosure. One
issue we haven't talked a lot about but
is really important as we think big is
the guardianship.
We've seen the importance of
guardianship in social media. Should a
parent be able to control what apps a a
youth has access to? should with
vulnerable adults. How do we design
systems to take into account that there
are going to be adults in our lives that
we have guardianships over or youth and
we've got to have that as a key uh
mechanism to have a guardianship uh
capability.
So though those are the key things that
uh I wanted to present to you.
It's been mentioned by my good friend
Senator Cmore that if we leave this up
to the federal government, we're going
to be stuck in in
uh in my we're not moving forward.
If we leave it to our friends in
industry,
their hierarchy of values is different.
They have fiduciary responsibility to
make money. And in some cases they will
view making money as more important or
interrupt elability as more important
than protecting the vulnerable and
protecting individual rights. It is our
responsibility to
exert our constitutional and moral
principles of liberty,
self-determination, and individual
autonomy. Thank you for coming and for
participating in this. And I think we're
moving to the breakouts. Chris
Um, we had a couple questions come up
about will this all be available. We are
going to make slides and this is all
being recorded and will be available
online. Uh, we are now going to break
out into two different breakouts. Uh, we
will be having lunch upstairs. So, we're
actually going to just move up there now
for the breakouts. So, if you exit
through these doors, you can take the
stairs or the elevators. We have some uh
UVU interns out there that will help
guide you. So, if you go to room
upstairs uh room 405 is going to be
having a breakout discussion on the
proper role of the state versus the
federal government. So, those who love
big government, head up there and
advocate for your for your what you
want. Um and then we're also going to
have an amazing uh discussion le led by
Will Seos uh of the SETI impact on
destination economies and how it's going
to help economies grow. So that's going
to be in room 408. So 405 for the
government policy discussion, 408 for
economic and then um we'll take it from
there. Uh those are both at the same
time right now. You have to pick one or
the other.
No, lunch is after.