Thank you.
Thank you. the Herbert Institute of Public
Policy, the Department of Government
Operations, and the Utah Legislature for
all helping to host this event and also to
UVU for allowing us to use their
facilities. I also want to thank UVU. We
had many employees and students and
interns help to bring this event together
for the last few months. And so we
couldn't do this without the work that
they've been putting in. And I want to
thank all of you for coming to Utah, to
participate in this event. We put a lot of
thought into how would we actually host an
event to cause change. And we thought
about just doing a virtual event. And we
knew that it's going to take a lot of
passion and a lot of work to pull off what
we're going to be proposing today. So it
was important to see who can we get to
come in person that cares the most about
it to help us build what we are going to
be proposing. So I thank all of you for
coming. Those from states, we have 12
states represented. Those from academia,
those from executive branch agencies,
those from legislators. I think we have
more than a dozen companies represented.
We have concerned citizens. We have
private interest groups. We have the
national ACLU. So we have the start of
what I think is going to be a really great
consortium.
Now the purpose of today is simple. We
invited you all to come here to receive an
education about a very complex topic is
digital identity. The second reason we've
invited you is to help help you understand
the problem and what we think is a really
big opportunity for America to lead out.
And the third and final reason that we've
invited you here today is to actually
invite you to join the SEDI consortium,
the state endorsed digital identity
consortium, so that we can move forward
and work together on what we think is a
big opportunity for America. Now, I am an
optimist by nature and I'm very optimistic
about digital identity if we do it right.
And I believe that we can build technology
that reflects American values, that
protects freedoms and strengthens families
and builds trust in the digital world. But
I am also a realist about why this effort
is needed. I am very concerned about what
I see happening not just in the United
States but what is happening around the
world. There are many of you in this room
that have expressed those same concerns.
That is why Representative Cutler and
Senator Kullimore sponsored Senate Bill
260 this last session, the first state
endorsed digital identity bill in the
nation to begin addressing these concerns.
So I want to share with you some of our
concerns. I am concerned that I am
concerned for my kids and your kids who
can engage online and video games and
social media and they do not know and we
do not know if the people they are
engaging with are actually who they say
they are. I am concerned for my and your
elderly parents and grandparents who
continue to be taken advantage of by
individuals pretending to be family
members in distress. I am concerned for my
and your elderly parents. I am concerned
for my and your elderly parents. I am
concerned for young men facing
exploitation and sextortion online. This
is one of the fastest growing crimes in
America and in Utah facing our young men.
They are being driven to despair and even
suicide in a world where anonymity and
manipulation coexist without protection. I
am concerned that fraud enabled by
identity theft and impersonation is now
costing the United States hundreds of
billions of dollars a year. I am concerned
that algorithms based on profiling and
scoring are influencing our behavior and
quietly shaping the concept of even
freedom and free agency. I am concerned
that the free market is being distorted,
that those who control personal data are
facilitating monopolistic behavior that
maximizes exploitation of individuals for
profit instead of driving a free market
based off of competition and best prices.
I am concerned that nation-state attacks
on future digital identity systems will
occur and we have to assume digital
identity will be compromised. I am
concerned that government-sponsored
digital identity systems both in the
United States and around the world have
been created that are capable of tracking,
surveilling, and controlling. I am
concerned that governments, corporations,
and technologists are rushing to create
digital identity systems that are
compulsory and are required and that these
are being created without the
comprehensive governance frameworks and
protections needed to protect individual
rights. And I am most concerned that in
democracies around the world, digital
identity systems are being designed and
implemented in ways contrary to the first
principles of America's founding. And that
is that individuals have individual
inalienable rights that they are endowed
with that is innate to them including
identity. Government does not give
identity. Government does not create
identity. And any identity system built on
the premise that government is giving it
to you means that they can also means that
they can also take it away which is in
opposition to this founding principle. So
the truth is there is no trust in the
digital world today. We don't know who or
what is real. We do not know. You do not
control your digital identity. Usernames,
passwords, even mobile driver's license
can be taken away. They can be
compromised. There is currently no
national strategy for digital identity.
And we know who or what is real. We do not
control your digital identity. And we know
that there are many both foreign and
abroad who would love to control your
digital identity and compromise it for
their own gains. So the dilemma before us
is that if we do nothing we will be left
with a system created by others that do
not share our same values. But this is not
the end of the story. It is the reason
that we are here. All of us in this room
are in a position to influence. Some of
you have the power to create laws. Some of
you have the power to create and dictate
public policy. Some of you have the power
to create technology. Some of you have the
power to fund new businesses to create the
solutions that we need. Some of you have
the power to create governance frameworks.
And some of you have the power to create
standards. And some of you just have the
power to raise your concerns and create
trouble for the rest of us which we need.
So you all have something to contribute
that is needed to create the solution
necessary to address our concerns and
create a better digital identity. So there
is a path a path forward by building
digital identity in a manner that
prioritizes rights and dignity. This is
what state endorsed digital identity is
all about. So I want you to imagine for a
minute a future. A future 10 years from
now after we've put in a lot of a hard
work. We need to agree today and in future
summits what that work is going to be be.
But a future where our fears about digital
identity theft manipulation,
impersonation, exploitation, loss of
control have been replaced by trust and
authenticity. Where parents know their
children are safe online. Where our
elderly are protected from scams and
impersonation. Where there is trust that
government is protecting your digital
identity and rights above all other
interests. That is the world world we need
all of you to help create. So through the
SEDI consortium that we are proposing and
inviting you to join today. States will
work together to define an American model
for digital identity. One that protects
citizens and instead of importing
surveillance and control based standards
and technology from abroad we will export
freedom by design. Showing that privacy,
security, protection, protection of
rights, protection of rights and
protection of individual rights and
innovation can coexist. The benefits and
capabilities of SEDI will be profound. It
will provide the foundation for
individuals and businesses to derive value
and utility for the free market to create
new and innovative solutions. We know
there will be new solutions for proof of
identity. There will be new solutions for
replacements of usernames and passwords.
Imagine that if you don't have to worry
about your passwords being compromised.
You don't have to worry about your
passwords being compromised. There will be
new solutions for consent and management
and agreements that individuals control.
There will be new solutions for
delegation, empowering families and
guardians and organizations to act safely
on behalf of the vulnerable and those they
serve. There will be solutions for agentic
AI where artificial intelligence operates
with your explicit authorization and not
in your place, extending your agency
rather than replacing it. So many of you
are replacing it. So many of you are
probably wondering how would we ever get
from the current state to that future
state. And we do that the same way all
great things are done and we have to do
that together. We have to create a plan.
We have to agree on our values. We have to
create a structure. We have to roll up our
sleeves and then as my teenagers and young
kids like to say we have to grind. We're
going to have to get out there and
actually do the work to make it happen and
it is going to take a long time. And under
the SETI consortium is where we can take
the fruits of all these labors that we are
about to do and give them away to everyone
else so that they can follow us. We know
not everybody is going to be able to do
this. We don't have all 50 states here.
Not everybody has the funding but we are
public entities. We can create it and we
can give it to them for the good of
everyone. So the work we're going to do is
going to include comprehensive governance
frameworks, model legislation,
resolutions, executive orders, defining
SETI requirements, technology and policy
controls, conformance programs, RFIs and
RFPs. We're going to have to do security
assessments. We're going to have to do
continuous engagement with civil rights
groups and watchdogs. We're going to have
to have absolute transparency and we're
going to have to do much, much more to
move the digital identity market in
America to align with what are going to be
the SETI standards.
the beginning. So today you are here to
learn about digital identity and some of
the principles that will guide the
creation of state-endorsed digital
identity. You will understand the concerns
and the opportunities ahead of us and I
hope you will accept our invitation to
join. But to end, I'm going to teach you
just one of the founding principles and
requirements of state-endorsed digital
identity. This is the very first one that
we identified when Senate Bill 260 was
written and this is probably the most
foundational and fundamental difference
compared to what you see happening in the
rest of the world. Identity belongs to the
person, not to the government. The
government's role is not to create or
control identity but to endorse and
protect it as a matter of public trust.
SEDI recognizes it is the role of the
state to act as a trusted endorser,
verifying an individual's digital identity
identity and then issuing an endorsed
credential, and then issuing an endorsed
credential mathematically bound to a
digital identifier that individuals alone
control. The state does not create the
individual identifier, cannot revoke it.
The state simply endorses that the person
is who they say they are and then provides
a credential that empowers the individual
to say to the world that I am me and the
world will accept it because it has been
endorsed and backed by the state. The
state will have no control or ability to
surveil or to track the usage and the
state cannot take away the underlying
digital identifier. The state has no role
to take away anybody's digital identity.
So with that said, we have a very busy day
ahead of us. This is mostly about
introductory education. This is going to
be a very fast-paced style to get you
information. We'll have a couple breakouts
throughout the day where you can ask
questions and you can participate and
learn what it means to help define policy
and technical controls. We're going to end
at the end of the day with an hour-long
discussion of how can we actually move
forward together as states. This morning,
the run of the show is we're going to have
Ryan Hurst speak to us and educate you on
what is digital identity. We will then
have Cindy George speaking to us about her
family's experience with extortion and
impersonation and the impact it has had on
them through their son's suicide. We'll
then have a legislative panel of Senator
Kullimore, Representative Cutler,
Representative Chevrier, and
Representative Shepherd to discuss with
you the importance of this work, why they
are supporting it, and why you should be a
part of the consortium. We'll then hear
from Daniel Hardman who will teach us
about the current lay of the digital
identity market. Phil Winley will explain
why Utah is the first state to formally
take the decentralized or first person
identity approach and Joe Jackson will
teach you why we are moving forward with
backward compatibility to help the entire
market move forward. So with that, Ryan,
I'll invite you to come up. Thank you.
I'm going to turn
to you. working for companies like Google,
Microsoft, Amazon and others for the last
30 something years focusing on
technologies like authentication. And so
today what I'm going to talk to you about
is what is digital identity and this was a
little bit of bias in this but I'm going
to try to get through about 30 years of
lessons in what I have left here. So
identity is not new. This is a picture of
a clay tablet from 1900 BCE. Merchants
used to put their thumbprint into these
clay tablets so that you could
authenticate that this is legitimate. This
is a point
that authentication of transactions is
something that we've been worried with
since the dawn of time and this is the
earliest example I could find. But we've
been trying over and over to solve this
problem and each generation has to
approach this problem slightly differently
for the environment that they exist in.
I've got a few examples that exist in this
timeline below here. We won't go through
them today but at the end of this
presentation I have a QR code that talks a
little bit about successes that you can
follow for a paper on successes and
failures in this space as I'm going to go
fairly fast here. So what identity is not
is as important as what identity is. It is
not a better document. Digital identity is
materially different than the one-time
issuance of a document that we would use
to authenticate at a government office or
when traveling. It is more of a living
type of credential that lives for a long
period of time and that living nature
means that this is a governance problem.
This is not a technology problem. So why
is this important? Because seven out of
ten of the projects that I've looked at
over the last several decades and then
you'll see those in that white paper have
failed and they failed because they looked
at this as a governance problem as a
technology problem as IT or procurement.
And so that's why it's important that
we're all here today and I'm really
excited to be involved in this
conversation. So this is a model shift.
State issues document, you carry it,
verifier inspects it. That's what we're
all used to. But as we look at what does
it mean to have civic digital identity,
it's much larger than just my name is Ryan
Hearst. There's many endorsements about
Ryan Hearst that might be material to the
verification. I'm a motorcycle driver.
That is certainly a driver's license thing
but I also am a parent. I also have other
attributes about me that are important and
the state is involved in many elements of
those and being able to prove that to
third parties is becoming increasingly
important and I'll talk a little bit about
some of those cases. This expanded role of
identity in the online world is something
that means that we have to change the way
we look at this problem and we have to
start with a set of guiding principles
which is why again I think SEDI is an
important project. So one of the biggest
differences that we'll see as we look at
digital identity versus their paper
history historical analog is that they
actually codify the policy that you all
come up with and this is important because
now when you make a change that digital
document and the systems that verify it
may also need to be changing. So we have
to think a little bit more holistically
than that issuance moment. We have to
think about how are we going to manage
this over its entire life cycle. If we
think of this as we bought a solution to
print these digital identities and declare
victory, we will fail. That's the number
one pattern we see when we look back at
the failed systems.
So what is maintained over time? Well,
there's a lot of status changes. Licenses
get suspended whether it be medical or
driver's license credentials or
credentials may get compromised or
credentials may get compromised and may
need to be replaced. Algorithms may need
to be changed over time. These are
probabilistically secure methods to prove
these things and so we may have to change
them. For example, post-quantum
cryptography is coming in the future. So
and policies change continuously faster
than ever before and this all means that
how we govern these systems is going to
become increasingly important. So if we
look at these failure patterns There's
there's many that we can point at one of
the ones that I like to point at one of
the ones that I like to point at is the
German solution. The Germany came up with
a national ID card that was technically
pure and perfect from their definition of
technically pure and perfect and it was an
abysmal failure. Nobody adopted it because
the governance model was not right. They
put the burden on the constituents. They
made it very complicated to adopt. They
didn't have a core utility. So it was
massive amounts of money spent with no
return on investment. So not something
that we can afford. UK is another great
example. I can't go into the details
today, but they wasted $233 million in a
decade of time roughly because they didn't
look at this problem holistically and they
didn't measure it in the right way. Some
of the successes we can point at Estonia.
They started with a list of three or four
utility scenarios that they were going to
enable. And as a result, their system
continues to exist. We can look at Sweden.
They looked at what was practical to
deploy and achieve results with and their
existing exists and is loved. It's very
rarely do you find a government service
that is loved, but I think that it's fair
to say that that particular program is. US
government has its own as well and there's
others that have elements of success, but
we'll go into those later in that paper I
mentioned. So why is this important? I'm
from the state of Washington. We have the
honor of I believe being the largest COVID
fraud for distribution of COVID funds. I
think Africa got more than we did. So this
is a big problem and it's a problem
because we didn't invest ahead of time. We
didn't build the infrastructure to enable
the government to be able to identify its
citizens online and we can't let this
pattern repeat again. So why does this
matter now? I mentioned COVID. COVID but
it's much larger than COVID. We can look
at AI for example. Today I can generate a
fake utility bill, birth certificate and
whatever easily with just a few types of
on my keyboard that you're going to
believe is legitimate. I can do real-time
deep fakes that are nearly impossible to
distinguish. The voice will be the same.
You cannot rely on a video call to
authenticate who you're talking to
anymore. And so this means that we have to
invest in infrastructure to be able to
strongly authenticate who we're dealing
with so that we're able to prevent
mistakes like that one from happening
again. I also think it's important to note
that in the context of security breaches,
88% of security breaches tracked by two
companies roughly that figure I think they
have two slightly different numbers but
very similar were just using stolen
credentials. They didn't hack anything.
They logged in. And so it's important that
we pick strong technologies that solve for
the problems and don't have externalities
that make things worse. This is you are
the foundation of how the federal
government interacts with Americans. You
are the foundation of how the rest of the
world interacts with Americans online and
we have to solve this problem. This is not
something that we can ignore. So why does
this matter for you? You don't manage
digital identity in abstract. There's a
lot of different examples of this that
exist inside of your organizations. You
may not think of them as digital identity.
Different people have different
definitions of this term but I think I
view all of you all of these things as
part of the life cycle of identity. A
birth certificate is my child's ID until
they're old enough to get a driver's
license. Many of these other elements. My
wife carries our marriage license because
she's from another country when we travel
because it's part of her digital identity.
All of these things are part of that
package that we have to use that the state
produces that the rest of the world relies
on to verify who we are. So before you
commit to any approach, I think it's an
understand important to understand what
digital identity and what digital identity
tells you what questions to ask. I didn't
word that particularly well.
Since this is a codified thing, the
question becomes when policy changes, how
does the digital identity get affected?
Because it's policy-based, how are you
actually going to create demand for this
thing? If you have no utility function for
your deployment, some scenarios that are
enabled that are actually meaningful to
your constituents, they're not going to go
through the hassle of doing it no matter
how beautiful the solution you build is.
How are you going to maintain the entire
life cycle of this system? This is like
any IT investment in that respect. And
because it's civic identity, you have to
pay attention to who's excluded. My
parents are not particularly good at using
things online anymore. And so we don't
want to exclude an entire segment of our
society. And there's of course other
examples as well. So what does success
look like? You've identified anchor
tenants, you've budgeted some amount for
continual governance, you've defined,
you've
defined
success metrics, you've defined success
metrics and how you're going to
continually revise those metrics so that
you can make sure that your system is
delivering on the promises that you should
have set out to do. So that is my
presentations. Ladies and gentlemen, I
appreciate your time today.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Hi. Thank you. Oh, those dimples. Oh,
those dimples. Everyone commented on those
cute little dimples. I was this fifth
grade teacher, which every kid's
nightmare, which every kid's nightmare,
right? To have your mom as your teacher.
But I was this first fifth grade teacher.
So I was able to see what a kindhearted,
thoughtful and caring kid this was. Not
just as a mother, but as a teacher. I
remember one day after school, he came up
to me and he kind of had glassy eyes, you
know, almost teary. And he said, I said, I
said, what's wrong? And he said, mom,
something happened today. And first I need
to give you a little background. We had a
little boy in our class that had a medical
issue that didn't have control of his
vowels. And oftentimes he smelled and the
kids really made fun of him. He had no
friends. He was picked on. Don't touch.
He's the guy cooties type stuff.
And Jake was his friend. Jake had a group
of friends that he hung out with that he
loved and they loved him. But he saw this
little boy and he befriended him. And
after school one day he came up to me and
he said, mom, he said, they're being so
mean to Brian. And I said, I said, what
happened? He said, well, at school, at
recess, he said, I said, come on, Brian,
let's go out. And we, we were walking out
on the playground and my friends were like
on the, on the basketball court and
saying, Jake, come over, come play with
us. And he's like, yeah, let's go play.
Come on, Brian, let's go play. And we got
over there and they said, just you, Jake,
not Brian. And I said, well, Jake, what
did you do? How did you handle that? And
he said, I just turned to him and I said,
nah, it's okay. Brian and I are going to
go play over here. And so he actually gave
up his friends because he saw this little
boy had no friends. That's the kind of kid
my Jake was.
When he was in middle school, he would
spend his days off. He'd say, mom, can I
go to school with you? And even in high
school, mom, can I go to school with you
on his days off? And he would come to
school with me and he would help tutor the
kids. He would help them with math or he'd
read to them. The kids in my class always
knew Jake.
Jake loved donuts. That was, this was his
last birthday. I made him a cake out of
donuts and he said, mom, that was the best
cake ever. He also loved, oh, and about
the donuts every year when he was in high
school and he had his own money. He would
show up on my birthday and he would show
up with three dozen donuts so he could
give donuts to my class for my birthday.
That's the kind of kid Jake was. He also
was an animal lover. This was his best
buddy Bosco and he loved dogs. He loved
animals.
He also loved music. When he was a little
toddler, he'd be in the backseat. It was
amazing because I'm big into music so I'd
have the music blaring and he'd be in the
backseat as a toddler in his little car
seat going to the beat of the music. Just
even as a little toddler. Just even as a
little toddler. He loved music. He loved
everything and a big variety. He loved
Linkin Park all the way to Elvis and Buddy
Holly and I was like, wow, that's a huge,
huge thing. One of my sweet memories is on
Mother's Day he bought me tickets to the
Styx REO Speedwagon concert, but it wasn't
for me to take just anyone. Just anyone.
He gave me one ticket and the other one
was for him. And we went as mother and son
and rocked out to Styx and REO Speedwagon.
That's the kind of kid Jake was. He was a
great student. He got his associate's
degree while he was in high school which
was a great achievement for him. Most of
all, Jake loved his family. Jake loved his
family. My two nephews were Jake's best
friends and they did everything together
including pranking me. That was their most
favorite thing to do. And then I got my
first grandbaby and that just made Jake an
uncle and he was so proud. I'm allowed to
be Uncle Jake now.
Sorry, I'm having issues. Okay.
Jake and I had the fall break and so we
went on a road trip together. Just the two
of us. And we went to the Grand Canyon. We
went to Bryce and we went to Bryce and
just had mother and son time. These are
the pictures from our road trip as well as
the one that's up here. This one he had
never seen the Grand Canyon and when we
got there it was full of clouds and so
that was his picture with the Grand Canyon
was clouds in the background. This right
here was our last trip together. Two weeks
later is where I'm going to pick up with
this story.
It was
the day before Halloween and I'm I was a
teacher and I had a teacher work day and I
was sitting at my desk when I got a call
from the middle of the night before
Halloween and I got a call from the middle
of the night before Halloween and I got a
call from the Millow County Police
Department. I said is this Cindy George
and I said yes and he said do you have a
son named Jake and I said yes and I said
yes
and that hit me. Jake's at our little
place. We had just little getaway place
there and he must have he must be there
and they must think that he just think
that he's breaking in or something like
that. I said yes, that's my son and they
said he has taken his life in your home.
I just I argued with him. I said, you got
the wrong kid. My kid was not on drugs. My
kid did not drink. My kid was not
depressed. just did not make sense. It
couldn't be my kid. And I argued with him
until they described his car and explained
that he had taken a gun and he was gone.
The rest of the day was kind of a blur.
And why? Couldn't even fathom how this
could happen. And the police department,
they faxed a couple of his letters. He
wrote seven letters. This is kind of kid
Jake was. He wrote letters to his sister,
to his friends, to his nephews, or his
cousins. This one's to me. I'm just going
to read part of it. It says, Dear Mom, I
love you so much. And it pains me to write
this. I wish I could live with what I did.
I know this will be hard for you, but I
need you to continue on with your life. I
hope you don't think too bad of me for
what I did. I know this is sudden, but the
hell that I went through Sunday through
Thursday was too much for me to handle was
too much for me to handle. I love you
dearly, Mom. You will always be my mother.
And I will always be your baby boy. Love,
Jake. It still didn't make sense. What
could possibly make him do this? And so
four months later, the police department
gave me back his phone and the last letter
that they held. And it says, My dear, this
is poor.
All of his parents. I'm sorry for what I
have done, but I have nothing to live for
anymore. I have made a huge mistake that I
can't live with. Look at my phone and read
the messages that are in the KICK app.
Start with the girl profile named Alona
Home and then move on to the profile just
for fun. These messages will explain
everything. From Sunday to Thursday, my
life has been a living hell and roller
coaster of emotion. The one person that
owns these two profiles will be using
Facebook to ruin my life. There's a good
chance I will lose my job and get kicked
out of school as the person attacks me
there. using Facebook. I urge you all to
control what happens on Facebook as much
as possible. This person claims that they
will copy some of your profiles and attack
your friends also. This person attacked my
three most important things being my
school, my job, and my family.
Please don't change your lives for me.
Don't change your lives for me. Hold your
children and grandchildren close. I love
you all. Jake.
So, I'm just going to take you a little
timeline.
I got his phone back and I read. I was the
only, I just took it aside and I read the
whole conversation and I understood the
pressure and the hell that they put him
through. This happened in five days. This
happened in five days. I was with him on
Sunday and Friday. He was gone.
I read the conversation how the predator
talked him into sending him a nude photo.
After grooming him, they talked him into
sending one nude photo. And kind of like,
I'll send you one nude photo. You send me
one. Talked him into it. I saw the high
pressure that they put him in. And then I
saw how they sent him names of family
members and said, we're going after them
next. And I think that's where it put Jake
over the edge. So, I'm going to take you a
timeline what his life went through in
five days. On Sunday, they get him to
send. They get him to send after grooming.
They got him to move to the Kik app. I'm
not sure where the original source came
from because he was on some dating sites
and he was on Facebook. I believe it came
from Facebook, but I'm not sure on that.
But they got him to move to the Kik app,
which is common for this type of a thing.
After they got him to move. After they got
him to move. They said, now we've got you.
Or after they got him to send a picture,
they said, now we've got you. Just added
and saved all your Facebook friends on my
laptop. I am going to send them your nude
photo and post it all over your friends
Facebook timeline and also to your job on
UPS Facebook page. But I will not do that
if you send me the money right now. Okay?
After constant threats, high pressure, get
there, get to the Walmart, get an
application. Let me see the application.
Get to the ATM. Let me see the money. He
was having to take pictures of everything.
They were on him. Just didn't give him
time to even process and think this
through. He finally at 7.06 that night, he
makes a payment of $300. at a Walmart at
Saratoga Springs to a Marie's Abril in the
Philippines. Then Jake asked for her to
please delete the picture like you said.
This was the response he got. He said,
they said, do you know what a genie is,
Jake? And he said, yes. He says, well, you
are my genie today. You are my genie
today. And I have found you. So you have
to grant me three wishes. And he says,
which are which you mean so you're going
to have to make three payments.
After begging for her to leave him alone,
saying I'm just a college kid, please
leave me alone. Jake ends up back at
Walmart that night. to make another
payment of $130. The torment and constant
threats continued for the next few days.
Jake paid them everything he had $680.
And after fulfilling the three wishes that
she required of him, Jake then begged her
to now please delete the photo.
And the reply was, you
work at UPS. In two weeks, you'll have
another paycheck. And Jake realized this
is never going to end.
He says, please delete it. I can't live
the next two weeks with you blackmailing
me. I gave you his total that he had just
given his last payment. And he said, he
said, you won't get any more money if I'm
not here.
The reply was, five guys committed suicide
because I posted their nudes and ruined
their life. But I never care. But I never
care. Because it's their choice, not mine.
You will be the sixth. And I still won't
care. On Thursday, Jake buys a garden hose
and heads at a Home Depot in American
Fork. And then in Richfield, he buys a
ream of paper and a box of a box of
envelopes and he goes to a hotel. And I
assume that's where he wrote all of his
letters. And he left one on the desk in
the hotel saying, the person that was in
this room is going to take their life.
Please contact. And he said, Brandon,
George, George, George, which was my
husband at the time, his brother that
lived in Kanosh and said, please contact
him. I'm going to be out in the West
desert.
Then on his way out of town, he bought a
helium tank, which was later found empty
in his car. Along with when I got in his
car, I found the hose and it was black on
one end. And the helium tank. And the
helium tank was empty. And I think that he
tried to take his life using that method.
And I think it was just taking too long
and he could not do it. And he knew that
my husband at the time had a shotgun in
Kanosh and he found the key and he took
his life. And he took his life. The hell
that I go through thinking of those last
moments as he's sitting there in so much
torment and having to pull that trigger
because of these evil people and what they
did. No mother should have to bury their
son. And it was so pointless.
I could not catch this person. I was told
because it came from the Philippines.
There was nothing that could be done.
There's a program on the National
Geographic called Trafficking with Mariana
Van Zeller. They contacted me out of the
blue. I don't know how they found me. And
they said, we want to do your son's story.
And we want to go to the Philippines and
we want to go to the Philippines and try
and find who did this. And so she came to
my house. They did the interview. And then
they proceeded to investigate. And they
found the source in the Philippines. And
it was a call center. A huge call center.
This is going on. And hitting so many of
our children. It's a big business there.
She actually talked to one of the people
that does this. And he was hooded. So all
you could see was his eyes. She said, do
you know that people are killing
themselves because of that? And he said,
yeah. I watched one of them do it. That's
the kind of evil we're talking about here.
Something has to be done. Brandon Guffey,
a state representative in South Carolina
that I have spoken to, had lost his son
Gavin, his 17-year-old son Gavin to sex
extortion. After his son died, he actually
got contact. He was contacted by the
perpetrator by the perpetrator. And they
sent him a laughing emoji. And it said,
did I tell you your son begged for his
life? That's the kind of evil we're
talking about here.
This is coming from Nigeria. This is
coming from the Ivory Coast. This is
coming from here. We need to do something
to warn these kids. I cannot catch the
people that did this to my son. Brandon
Guffey, I saw on his Facebook about six
months ago. He and his wife were holding a
set of handcuffs on his page. And they
have Gavin's name. etched in the
handcuffs. And they went to Nigeria. And
they found who did this to their son. And
they extradited them. And they've been
charged. What a great thing that they were
able to do that. The Philippine government
were not so accommodating when the
National Geographic went over there. They
know who started the whole thing went over
there. They know who started the whole
thing in the Philippines. And she's been
arrested and then let out.
I asked for your help because I can't
catch them. My son died so needlessly. I
can't catch them. But the only thing I can
do is warn others. Please talk to your
grandkids. Your kids. Your neighbors. Your
neighbors. Your neighbors. Your nephews.
Talk to them so they won't take the bait.
That's the only thing we can do is educate
so they won't take the bait. And we need
to also talk to them and let them know no
matter what, no matter what is happening
in your life, that they can come to you. I
wish Jake would have been able to come to
me. I wish I could have comforted him and
said, it's okay, it's okay. They can't
destroy your life with a picture.
Don't ever think this can ever happen to
my child, my nephew. Because I can testify
to you that it can happen to the best of
kids. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
I'm Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild the
likes so that there can be
interoperability and people can work
together and get records more quickly. And
I know that's an issue. I know that it's
more it's better for them to be able to
access the records quickly. But I've been
fighting it for the last 10 years because
of the dangers that are involved in
centralizing that data. And so that is the
biggest issue for me is that I wanted a
way for us to be able to make data
accessible without compromising privacy.
Do I have it on? Is it on? It's on. Okay.
Thank you. For me, there's a lot of
distrust in digital platforms that are
going on right now. And there's, as you
saw today, and as you already have known,
there's been many people that do bad
things that will really scare people. And
one of the things that for me is that your
personal data is just scattered and having
the opportunity to have Utah lead in this
area and to be able to make it that we and
recall that we own our data. The
government doesn't own our data. We own
our data or we should at least. So it's
important to me that we have privacy,
autonomy, and and with our state having
the consent of the governed. I have many
constituents who reach out to me even as
of yesterday telling me a digital ID is
not the way to go. But as you'll hear
today, there's many reasons why we should
go with it. And I have a firm belief that
even before I took office that we have the
right people in the right place here. And
I think our other states need to join us
with this one and making sure that we
don't do like other countries have done
with our data. Senator Collin Moore
representative. You got SB260 passed
unanimously through the House and the
Senate a couple years after there was a
different digital identity bill which I've
heard there were pitchforks in committee
hearing and it did not come out. Why are
you supporting and championing SEDI?
I'll start. I've been fortunate to be able
to work on technology policy in the Senate
in the Senate in the Senate over the last
several years. It started with data
privacy just in the consumer aspect and
recognizing how important that is. We've
since passed a government data privacy the
first of its kind which I think is also
important. But in the middle there we're
also working on social media bills and
social media policy because government
with technology typically is always well
government by its nature is reactionary
which I don't think is necessarily a bad
thing. But in some of the bad thing. But
in some of these technology policies it
moves so fast that we are not in front of
this and we are allowing people to be
exploited. And the way the internet came
up is was using data. The way this has
been monetized is using our data.
Facebook, Instagram, Snapchat, Google, any
of these services are free to us because
as we all know you are what's being sold.
You are the commodity. And that in and of
itself is scary and that's what we're
having to deal with as social media right
now is social media companies have
exploited that to the detriment of our
kids. They're not only affecting their
mental health but they're causing actual
real world harm like we just heard about
and it's terrible. And putting that same
type of power into the government's hands
that has even more control over over over
so many aspects of our lives is just super
scary and something that we need to avoid.
We need to flip the script of how this is
being developed and what this actually
means. We need to put the power back into
the citizenry into people. People are not
commodities and that is what the digital
age has created. We are all commodities
now. And I think that's one of the
fundamental evils of our day and age is
when we commoditize human life that's
problematic. And if government is going to
do that, that's even more problematic. And
so we needed to find a way to flip the
script. SEDI, the bill that we passed is
really just the first fundamental step.
It's laying the foundation for flipping
the script and saying no, the power is
back in the people. The power is back in
the individual.
If we look back at history, history shows
us that fighting technology advancement is
often a futile effort is often a futile
effort. Whether you're a buggy maker
trying to put laws to stop the automobile
or trying to fight industrialization, that
technology is going to move forward
because there are so many benefits to
society. So we have a choice to be
proactive and influence and control these
standards or we can stick our head in the
sand and say no, I don't want this. I
don't want to fight it. I want to fight
it. And I choose to try to be part of the
solution. Digital identity is coming. I
think we all, especially everyone in this
room recognizes that. And the only choice
is do we want to influence the standards
and the adoption of this to protect
freedom and individual liberties or will
we acquiesce to efficiency and
monetization? There are bold visions out
there for artificial intelligence. We hear
all around us, hey, the future is agentic.
Agentic AI. We're going to have all these
agents acting on our behalf, acting on
behalf of an entity or software program.
The security concerns are very real. So
you are not going to be a smart security.
You are not going to be a smart security
person will not allow an agent to take on
a task on their behalf if there is not
trust. And as has been talked about, our
digital trust structure is under constant
attack right now. And in many areas it
fails. So we have got to come up with a
better system for verifiable credentials
for trusting people and eventually
entities if this agentic future has any
chance of making a real impact without
doing incredible harm in our society. I'm
going to go off script here for the rest
of the time.
Utah in my view has been unique compared
to what I've heard actually from many in
the audience and how we work together
between branches of governments. We have
CIOs in the audience. We have chief
privacy officers in the audience. We have
chief privacy officers in the audience. We
have civil rights groups in the audience
and I've heard them comment of how is Utah
able to do these things it's doing? I'm
going to ask this to Senator Collomoere.
What is it that Utah is doing differently
than other states and what should they
know so they can go back to their states
and replicate the success we're having
across our government on both sides of the
aisle? Well, you know, we have to put we
have to set aside our trying to be humble
here because there are some things that
work really well here in Utah and we call
it the Utah way. But the Utah way really
is just recognizing that that we are here
as, you know, public servants. We're
servants of the people. And when you
approach these types of policies, you have
to have a little bit of humility to say,
you know, I don't know everything. And
that's especially true in technology,
right? Like I fundamentally believe, I
fundamentally believe in certain
principles, but I don't actually know how
the technology actually works, right? And
so sometimes you want to implement a law
and we're talking about very basic things
right here, but whether it's like whatever
the type of law is, I think it's
critically important that you bring in all
the stakeholders and who best than the
private sector and academia. And so
whenever we've worked on these policies,
we have good working relationships between
the Senate and the House. We have good
working relationships between the
legislature and and the executive branch,
the regulators who are actually enforcing
this or implementing the laws that we
pass. And it's important because, you
know, the policy does not actually work if
the implementer just has their own idea
and goes a certain direction. And none of
this actually works because most of the
time people in government don't have the
technical expertise to know what they're
actually talking about. And so we have one
of the shortest sessions, legislative
sessions in the country. It's 45 days,
begins in the middle of January and goes
to about the first weekend of March. And
we are a part-time legislature. And we are
a part-time legislature. That is becoming
less and less a reality. We're becoming
more and more full-time because really
that January to March, that's game time,
but it's happening all year round. And so
we're meeting with stakeholders. And most
of the best policy that we pass involves
academia, people who have the research and
the background on their private sector,
people who are actually developing these
technologies or deploying these
technologies or using them within their
business, policymakers, and the business,
policymakers, and the executive branch.
And so I don't think we've passed any tech
technological policy in the state of Utah
without input from all of them. And
sometimes it takes time. The consumer data
privacy bill that we passed, I think we
were the fourth state in the nation to
pass it, but it ran for three years. And
we were getting input from everybody and
it gets whittled down. We passed a digital
asset bill that recognizes what digital
assets are. And it started out as 16 pages
even when it was introduced in the
session. And because of input, it got
whittled down and said, no, let's boil
this down to the fundamental principles
and then build on that. And I think that's
what we've done here with SEDI is we
haven't made this. I mean, it's policy.
It's agnostic to what the technology is.
And in fact, the technology is not even
out there right now. That could be
implemented. But it's steering the boat
and it's steering the direction of how
that technology is going to be
implemented. And so this is the opposite
of being humble. But using humility to get
to these policy decisions, I think is what
helps drive the advancements that we've
seen in Utah. Chris, I'd love to comment
on that. I think we have been successful
as Senator Kolemore, and he deserves a lot
of the credit for bringing people together
as do you and making some policy. But it's
premature to pat ourselves on the back yet
and say that this this is great. We have
some good policy. We haven't seen
adoption. And we can't do adoption on our
own. We can't do adoption by just the
legislature passing a policy. Adoption
requires industry to come up with tools
and use cases that are compelling. And
also because Utah is small, to be
successful, we need your help. We need
other states to join together to join
together and show that we have enough of a
consortium to get attention from the big
players to say this matters and privacy
and security and individual rights are
important. So while we've had a little bit
of success, we need to replicate that by
having you join us and agreeing on some
key principles and some key standards
where we can move forward together and
have a larger coalition.
Representative Chevrier and Shepard, I'm
actually going to ask you the same
question. You two probably represent some
of the most conservative areas in the
nation in Utah County. And the fact that
this bill is passed unanimously, I think
one is representative of the work done.
But what is it that's different about this
approach that is helping to win over or at
least gain the trust of those that each of
you represent?
Do you want to go first? I can go first.
So I think this is going to be off topic
for a second, but it's really on topic. We
have a system of government in Utah that
is different from most other states and
from most other states and that is the
caucus convention system which makes it so
that the grassroots are far more involved
with their legislators than they are in
most states. And I think that that's been
a huge factor because both Representative
Shepard and I have been very involved in
the party and in the caucus convention
system. We have built trust in that arena
that allows us to help transfer that
allows us to help transfer that trust to
the legislature and to this technology
that we're talking about. So because we
have that opportunity to build trust I
think that makes it easier for us to help
people understand because they're willing
to listen to us because we have built
trust with them through that system. Does
that make sense? Okay.
Part of being elected I had a town hall
and it I had experts in this area come and
speak to those who came and yes of course
we use it through the caucus convention
system that we have that allows us to have
a direct report and be held accountable by
delegates and that is where you get the
biggest pushback and honesty delegates are
very engaged and they know issues and they
know issues and they know issues and you
can't hide and it's a great actually a
really great process and it's a great
actually a really great process and I
appreciate that I appreciate the
accountability. The delegates and my
voters that I have talked to about this by
knocking on the doors they want us to
leave them alone. They want to be able to
be safe in this community not only
physically but also digitally and I
believe that the relationships that having
served on the relationships that having
served on a state level in my party and
served just across the entire state and
worked in some national areas I believe
that that that does open the door to when
I bring experts to my district that
they're willing to take a chance and
listen and it has changed the hearts of
some of them to actually listen. Sometimes
we get stuck in our ways and think that we
have the answers and something is
something is the boogeyman but honestly
when you listen and Chris Bramwell has
come to my district along with Timothy
Ruff and when they have when they have
spoken people in my district have listened
and that's what I really appreciate. It's
the opportunity to bring these experts as
the good senator to my left here has
mentioned to bring these experts and to
trust them. We have to have trust in the
experts and our people that we represent
have to have trust in have to have trust
in us. It's quite the partnership that we
have. Chris can I add one thing to that? I
think your policy of engaging with critics
has been key to some of the success. There
are some times where in politics where you
don't engage with the critics you say I
have a majority I'm just going to pass
this through but that hasn't been how the
privacy legislation that Senator Kohler
Moore has helped with Kohler Moore has
helped with or this legislation has been
handled. You've held town halls where you
invited critics to come and poke holes and
things. You've brought in key members of
staff and industry to come and engage and
you slowed down the process to help
convince the critics that this is the
right way forward and I think that made a
big difference. Thank you. We have six
minutes. I actually I'd like to ask does
anybody have any questions? Any questions
of maybe how?
I can do it. I'm this is what is this the
Murray show? Hi, my name is Sarah
Thunberg. I'm the director of the Colorado
Digital Service. Thank you for having us.
We are watching very closely the work
you've done and are talking about our own
legislative agenda as the legislature that
legislators that moved a lot of this
forward. Do you have any recommendations
for those of us to take home with us how
we can model lessons learned things now in
retrospect you think maybe we would have
done it differently?
I'm not sure about the done it differently
but I'll tell you what we've done that has
been working in it and Paul we well we've
all talked a little bit about it but Chris
has been very proactive in interacting
interacting with the people who are most
likely to be the people who are most
likely to be the critics and so Lisa and I
have been able to set up these town halls
where we can bring Chris in and have him
explain to people we've set up meetings
with individuals who are all at night and
on weekends by the way. Yes, it is out of
regular business hours always but we've
been able to have discussions with the
most vocal critics people who have large
followings followings on social media and
followings on social media and we've been
able to help them understand what it is
we're actually doing because the reaction
is visceral. I had somebody on Facebook
this morning say to me that having you
endorsed digital identity was not on my
bingo card. It wasn't on mine either but
here I am because I believe that this is
the right system and I believe that we
either have to choose a system that is
going to respect privacy or we're going to
get the other one. And so we need to make
the choice and we need to make it soon.
I'm going to make a comment too. You need
a champion in your state. When Senator
Kallamore and Moss created the CPO role
they empowered it to be a champion. You
need every government entity fights for
certain rights for the public. Public
safety is to provide safety. Lands is to
protect the public lands. Health and human
services is to ensure there's public
health and human service.! Do you have a
privacy or digital identity champion in
your state that is empowered to even fight
for this issue? It's a balancing and
that's part of the governance framework.
So if you don't have that get it going or
be the champion. I'll just add you know as
as state legislators what's awesome about
being in in state policy is that you can
pass a bill and then you see the effects
of it like almost immediately and that's
that's pretty rewarding. The the downside
of that is you want to do everything right
now you know and and that's just not
possible in these types of bills you know
we we could have said you will implement
these policies and forced it upon all the
government agencies and all the political
subdivisions of the state and cities and
counties and it would have fell on its
face and we would have got zero adoption
because there's no way to even adopt it
right now. We're doing about that with
government data privacy. We wanted all of
the cities, the counties, the state
agencies, our schools and everything like
that to adopt all the state. We want to
adopt all these things and you will
implement data privacy right now and you
will implement all these retention
policies and you'll get rid of this stuff
and it's just impractical and you're
setting yourself up for failure and so you
do have to reel back a little bit and say
you know what I'm just gonna let's just
pass this right now and let's build that
and even as Chris said you know we did a
data private or we did the chief privacy
officer a few years ago and and we just
keep slowly building on that and so you do
have to have patience. which is not always
a virtue among state legislatures.
Good morning. Good morning. I'm Shanna
Durant with the Department of Public
Safety. Thanks for having us. I have a
question particularly for the
representatives. You say you've had a lot
of town halls. I'm curious about how often
you're having them and how much you're
publicizing them because you say that
we're talking to a lot of people who are
social media influencers but for example
Representative Cutler, my parents are
actually some of your neighbors. so
they've never heard about this until I
talked to them. So they've never heard
about this until I talked to them. So how
much are is their public outreach to more
than just you know social media and
advocacy groups and what can we do on our
side as public entities as state entities
to assist in that but also give other
solutions to help you with an enhanced
identity and what can we bring to the
table in order to make it better. Thanks
for Thanks for the question. I think
that's important. So when I mentioned all
these town halls that they were fairly
targeted and the efforts to focus on the
policy have been targeted with those who
are probably the fiercest advocates either
for or against. Let's be honest. Most
regular people most people this issue
hasn't hit them yet because there is
nothing for them to adopt today. Yes, they
could adopt our mobile driver's license
which they may or may not be able to get
through Homeland Security. They they there
are but there they cannot we don't have a
digital identity for them to adopt yet. So
the efforts for advocacy advocacy were
targeted at the key stakeholders those who
are most concerned about privacy those who
are most concerned about the technology
used and the next wave once once once once
we have a solution ready to be adopted
would be to go out to all the citizens and
explain how this is used how this helps
your life how this can help verify ages on
social media how it helps protect their
family from online fraud which are real
pressing problems that we all recognize
and we're all trying to deal with and
we've got to get to a point where we have
a solution for them. So we have a policy
solution today. We do not have a market
solution until we get to a market solution
until we get your help to agree on a
standard and products. And I know we're
out of time but it's a little bit of a
catch-22 right because if you go to a town
hall you've got you know I'll publish a
town hall for thousands of people and the
same 12 people show up and they're a
little bit older oftentimes and they're
not technologically savvy and I would
bring up some of these topics and my wife
would be there and she'd be like you
you've got to stop talking about that like
like they don't care it goes over their
head and I think you're just scaring them
anyways. So it's a little bit hard right
because you have to find these focus
groups of people who are like keyed in on
this tuned in but to your point we've got
to find a way that people understand that
I do believe this is critically important
and as we're moving into this digital age
if government does not get out in front of
this it's going to be a problem. It's
going to undermine democracy. So I will
say the approach for communication though
has been to communicate with every elected
official where a town hall is being held.
So UVU was partnered with for that. So
they emailed every elected senator,
representative, county commissioner,
mayors in every one of the areas where the
town halls were. So it was very much
focused toward who are the people actually
elected to represent the people and then
they were asked to communicate it out. The
other thing I'll say though is this
approach we're talking about SEDI doesn't
even exist yet. We're so early in bringing
the public in. You have 29 states already
going down a digital identity path with
mobile driver's license or with W3C
credentials or others in California or
Colorado. This is unique of how early this
is happening and people don't realize the
train has already left the station in some
way and we're having to move the market to
try to move everything in this direction
and we're needing to now come in with new
policies and standards that we need to
have all of that stuff now go back and be
compared to to make make sure you can meet
them. Let's end 15 seconds. What's your
pitch for states to come and join the
consortium? I'll throw out on this. Many
of us recognize that we let tech
giants and the market determine the
principles by which social media operates
and is distributed and affects our
families. communities. I think we have a
lesson learned from that we need to think
carefully about in this AI world how do we
want to change that or influence how we
control digital identity so we don't have
the mistake of people who are kids
accessing things they shouldn't. So this
is a chance to help solve that problem
with youth identity and to solve the
economic problem problem of how do I put
Greece in the system to allow economic
transactions with trust to happen across
the world. Okay. Go ahead Lisa. I think we
need 49 more Chris Bramwell across the
country. That's a definite statement and
his team. I've seen the hard work that
that work that that they do and the
innovation Utah's famous for being
innovative and we need the other states to
join us. We can't do this alone. I think
get your get your states to get a data
privacy expert and an officer a director
whatever your role is all of the above and
and get your teams of the experts in the
field. I'll tell you I was on a panel here
for synthetic data. I I'm just a normal
person just carrying the voice of the
people and I sat there and every other
person had a PhD. I'm looking at one right
now and they are incredibly brilliant.
They are the ones that have come up with
the solutions. We're the ones up here that
are helping to implement those across the
country. So we need your help. Are you
going to go? I'll go. Sure. So I have zero
confidence in Congress getting anything
done in this space. I have to the extent
they get anything done. I have to the
extent they get anything done. I have less
confidence that it's going to be done
right and not influenced by the big tech
giants that are looking to again
commoditize our data and our people. We
need to get back to the principles of
America that made us great. We are the
laboratories of democracy and if we want
to push this policy we need a critical
mass of states that align with these
policies adopt these principles and we
will see mass implementation and mass
adoption of these types of these types of
these types of principles and policies
because the states are going to lead out
and that's why you're here. We need you to
help us. We need you to join with us and
your idea might look just a little bit
different and that's okay but if the
states are working together and leading
this effort the interoperability that
people are concerned about will happen
naturally because we're working together
and we don't have to rely on the federal
government nor should we. That's not how
our country was set up. We can find the
solution here and we encourage you to join
us. So I think since I'm last this is what
I want to say. We have worked together as
a group in our state and we would like to
now extend that out to other states and
start bringing each of you in. We'll talk
to you one-on-one. That's what we've done
here. Anytime there's somebody who has
questions, Chris will go and talk to them.
Now there's only one Chris so we can't we
can't we don't want to spend him but what
we can do is help people to understand
this one-on-one. Nobody that we've talked
to that I'm aware of has been opposed to
this once they understood it. So I think
the key is educating people on what it is
we're trying to do and what the stakes are
and the stakes are very high. So for
future generations let's work together and
let's work together and let's get this
done. Thank you. Let's give them a round
of applause. applause applause applause
applause applause
applause applause applause Thank you.
Thank you.
Hello. Okay, great. My name is Daniel
Hardman. I am a CEO of a company that is
in the totem space. I've been working in
identity for many years. And I got an
almost impossible assignment from
Christopher and crew, which is to try to
summarize a state of the identity
landscape in 10 minutes. And that's almost
impossible because there's so much that's
happening and that has been happening. So,
you know, being a progressive thinker
here, I said, I'll ask AI to help me find
a list of things that are going on in the
space. Now, I knew that this was going to
generate massive amounts of stuff. So, I
said, just find 40 headlines that have
been in the news recently in English about
things that are going on in identity that
have been widely reported. So, this is
what it came up with. And this is, of
course, an AI summary, but the point of
this is not the specific headlines. The
main point of it is how many of them there
are and how hard it was even for the AI to
pick from all the different things that
are going on in the space. And as I was
watching this list come in from AI, what
was going through my head is that Billy
Joel song, We Didn't Start the Fire. You
know what I'm talking about? There's just
so much that's happening and it's
virtually impossible or overwhelming to
keep track of it all. So, to summarize in
10 minutes is very hard, but what I'm
going to do is I'm going to try to explain
how it looks to me as a practitioner in
the space at a high level. I'm going to be
a practitioner in the space at a high
level. I'm going to make some
generalizations. These generalizations are
partly subjective, but I think they're a
useful mental model for people to
understand if you're not thinking about
identity all the time and you want to kind
of wrap your brain around it. So, my
generalizations basically say that there
have been three waves of innovation in
identity and I would start the really and
this is digital identity and this is
digital identity by the way. I would start
these waves going back to something like
maybe the Diffie-Hellman. Diffie-Hellman
was a cryptographic technique that was
invented in 1976. You could possibly go
back to email which was a little bit
earlier than Diffie-Hellman. But anyway,
and then I would say that there's these
three bands of or waves of innovation and
they have characteristics that are common
or commonalities in the way they think
about things. these aren't exactly
perfectly
aligned technologies in each of these
bands but they have these common
characteristics. So, I'm not sure what
happened there. Maybe my laptop is still
alive. I'm going to keep talking. Maybe we
can get it to come back up. Okay. So, the
first band here central or federated
governance. It was an assumption that when
you built identity systems initially there
was going to be some central body that did
it for you. And it was an assumption that
you were going to use this brand new cool
thing called Diffie-Hellman and this brand
new cool thing called asymmetric
cryptography and all that kind of good
stuff and that you were going to use keys
and certificates. That was kind of the new
kid on the block that was cool at the
beginning and a lot of innovation has
happened since then that kind of keeps
those key assumptions. And by the way when
I represent these three bands here I'm not
saying that there's you know bad and and
okay and better so much as I'm saying it's
kind of like a classic car that had a
carburetor and then a car that has a fuel
injector and a computer and then an
electric car or something. These are waves
of technology. Okay. There are reasons
though why we learn from our experience.
And so there is thinking in these later
bands that looks back at what was done in
the earlier bands and says there might be
a better way to do this and there's
advantages to tweaking our mental model.
So the second band of identity innovation
I would kind of track back HIP is kind of
an outlier in the fact that it came about
pretty early and by the way HIPA has Utah
roots. I didn't know that until yesterday
I was talking to somebody. But anyway
really kind of when blockchain started
impinging on people's consciousness there
were a number of things that people said
oh wait a minute that means there's a
different way that we could do this. Oh
there's a different way we could do that.
And there were some dominoes that fell and
it brought about this yellow band of
thinking. And the thing that's different
mainly between the red and the yellow is
that we're using generation two techniques
where we're not identifying people by keys
now we're identifying people by
identifying people by identifying people
by identifiers and we're using probably
upgraded cryptography like elliptic curve
and so forth and there's a lot of
blockchain although it's not all
blockchain oriented in the yellow band.
But there's a lot of the notion of wallets
digital wallets was a big deal. And then
there are a lot of dissonance around
privacy issues as this yellow band kind of
came about. The third wave of thinking
here this green band is typified in my
mind by a much more sophisticated and
nuanced view about the governance that has
to be in place. And that doesn't mean that
people that are making yellow banded stuff
or red banded stuff are ignorant about
governance by any means. But it's kind of
like playing a symphony. There's a lot of
different instruments and I think in the
green band and I think in the green band
the full range of instruments is now much
more apparent. And big emphasis on
auditability of what's going on in a
system and a big emphasis on
recoverability. If something goes wrong
and you assume in the green band that
things will go wrong. So the question
becomes what do you do when things go
wrong? not how do you prevent things from
going wrong? Not how do you prevent things
from going wrong? Which is an unrealistic
question in some ways. And there's
different cryptographic primitives.
There's identifiers, yes, but they're
upgraded to autonomic identifiers which
have certain desirable properties and so
forth. And an emphasis on look post
-quantum is going to be a reality soon.
Are we ready for it? It would be really
foolish to build an identity system that's
not ready for post-quantum at this point
when NIST has already announced post
-quantum standards.
Okay, so enough on that slide. I can't
spend that much time because there's just
like I said 10 minutes is nearly
impossible here. What I see in the market
is that there's major tensions. There's
things that are pulling solutions to the
yellow and the red band. hands. And you
can see what I've said roughly kind of
argues for yellow and red solutions today.
And then there's things that pull people
towards the green direction when they're
designing solutions. Enough said on that.
I could go into this for hours. But let me
just talk about the two biggest forces
that I see in the market today. I just
returned from living in Europe for several
years. So I've lived personally through
the EUDI initiative a little bit and
what's going on there. And the EUDI
initiative has enormous momentum. It's a
juggernaut in Europe. But it doesn't it's
not without its challenges. Many different
countries have built systems and they kind
of don't all get a long but they're trying
really hard. But they're trying really
hard. And the state of play in the United
States is a little bit different. You have
state level initiatives which is why this
conference makes so much sense. States are
making the decisions not a central
government. There are things that are
being built with generation one solutions
or generation two solutions in the United
States. Absolutely. SEDI is an example of
generation three solution and there's
reasons why I think that's really
exciting. The strategic trends that I'm
aware of I'm not going to say them all but
you can read them there. I'll just say
that the thing I would bet on bet my
bottom dollar on is that last bullet.
Security pressures are going to grow and
legal pressures are going to grow. I
guarantee that's going to grow. I
guarantee that's going to be true. If
nothing else that I can forecast that
one's for sure. Remember what that might
imply about what kinds of solutions are
wise. I'd like to end with a thought here
and that is we sometimes hear solutions
described in terms of formats. So you're
going to hear today about ISO mobile
driver's licenses and you're going to hear
about W3C verifiable credentials and so
forth. I think that's the wrong way to
think about decisions. I think that's the
wrong way to think about decisions. Up
here you have two pictures of the same
person and one of them is the lossless
view that you get off of a digital camera
when you take an image and the other one
is a JPEG. Now are JPEGs bad? No. We use
them all the time and they're very useful.
But if you're a professional graphic
artist you would never want to deal in
JPEGs when you as inputs to your graphic
projects. So they have different uses. And
I'd like to suggest that permanent
evidence needs to be lossless evidence.
And there are a number of dimensions to
losslessness. There's time related
dimensions like how long does this
evidence persist? There's governance
related dimensions to evidence. There's
post quantum cryptography related
dimensions to evidence and losslessness.
There's all kinds of stuff. So I'd like to
just suggest that as you run into
conversations about this don't make it a
debate about formats. Make it a debate
about how to solve problems and you'll
find that the format questions fall out.
Thank you. That's all I'm going to do.
Thank you.
I'm Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Amazon. They own
it. We call these administrative identity
systems because they're designed to
administer identity for a specific purpose
in a specific domain. In this case, it's
Amazon, but you know, there are millions
of them. The system, the identifiers, how
they work are owned and controlled by
Amazon. They're the subject of Amazon's
terms and conditions. They're useful for
establishing trust within a domain but
they're not useful for establishing trust
across domains. People are party to
dozens, hundreds, thousands of these
things. I have over a thousand entries in
my one password.
In contrast, decentralized identity flips
that model. The person becomes the center
of trust and credentials about that trust
flow through protocols rather than
platforms. Unlike decentralized, the
decentralized identity model,
decentralized identity provides a
consistent experience for interacting with
all of the relationships in your digital
life. But decentralization alone isn't
enough. What we really need is what I
think is called first person identity. A
way for people to act as themselves
online, not as managed accounts. I like
the term first person identity better than
decentralized because it's more clearly
distinguishes that identity is based on
the individual, the first party in a
relationship. First person describes an
idea that most people understand
naturally. We're taught about we're taught
this in grade school. First person is I,
me, myself, mine. First person describes
precisely the kind of thinking that will
allow people to create their own online
relationships without an intermediating
administrator like a social network. Like
a social network. In first person
identity, you might have relationships and
credentials from your employer, from your
bank, from your school, from the driver's
license bureau, and so on. You can use
these alone or in combination to prove
things about yourself. In first person
identity, people are the integration point
for information about themselves. Now, why
does this matter so much? It matters
because something essential is missing in
our digital lives. Maybe.
There we go. The real challenge online
isn't utility or convenience, it's
proximity. In the physical world, we're
next to each other. We rely on tacit
knowledge that we gain from our senses
when we see and speak with people. We use
this tacit information to establish trust.
We don't have that online. Online, we
interact at a distance through screens and
systems and platforms that usually are not
controlled by us. Our relationships are
mediated by companies rather than being
direct. In fact, let's talk about what
that distance costs us and how endorsement
rather than control can close it.
Descartes didn't say, I have a Google
login, therefore I am. He said, I think,
therefore I am. We exist independent of
anything else around us. Now, that's where
endorsement comes in. It bridges the gap
of distance. It bridges the gap of
distance. It allows people or anything
half a world away to trust who you are
because you your own state endorses what
you're saying, your assertions that you're
making. SEDI, state endorsed digital
identity doesn't give you an identity. You
already have one. Rather, SEDI endorses
it. It provides the assurance we need to
act confidently across digital distances.
So the problem isn't that we lack digital
IDs. We've got plenty of those. I've got a
thousand. It's that we lack standing in
the online world. We are ghosts existing
only through the grace of some company. We
are not embodied autonomous agents. SEDI
changes that. Again, it doesn't create
your identity. It doesn't create your
identity. It endorses it and gives you the
ability to act across distance that can
lead to something much bigger. A chance to
reclaim our digital freedom. First person
identity represents a chance for us to
declare our independence in the digital
realm. To regain the freedom to act as
ourselves. SEDI enables that by supporting
the individual and giving each of us a
place to stand a place to stand online.
Freedom in a digital world to gain a place
to stand online. Freedom in a digital
world begins when we act from our own
identity, not one assigned to us and
mediated by someone else. This is our
moment to build a digital world that
honors human dignity. A world where we are
free to live and act as ourselves. As
digital citizens rather than digital
subjects. If we don't build it, someone
else will. If we don't build it, someone
else will. And it will reflect their
goals. Goals that probably don't align
with the ones we think they should have.
For Utah, this is a chance to lead by
example. Demonstrating that trust in
identity can scale without surveillance.
Across the US, SEDI can mark a shift from
digital subjects to digital digital
citizens. People who live effective online
lives with agency and respect. We have the
opportunity to build a digital world that
respects human dignity. A world where
people are free to live and act for
themselves. Let's not squander that
opportunity.
All right. We're going to see if I get to
keep my geek card here.
Okay. Today, I want to talk about the
evolution of technology and how backward
compatibility is essential for growth.
Technologies are in a constant state of
change and they're always adding new
features and enhanced functionality to
meet growing demands. The three phones
that you see here are a perfect
illustration of this. They represent the
dramatic evolution of the simple telephone
of the simple telephone over just the last
30 years from a device tethered to a wall
to a portable gadget for calls and
eventually text messages to the powerful
computer we all carry in our pockets now.
The infrastructure to support the corded
and the corded and smartphones are still
in place today, but the first generation
of mobile devices no longer function. This
progression is a familiar story, but it
holds important lessons for the future of
other technologies, including digital
digital identity. And the progress shown
here is not always guaranteed. So I want
to talk about two ubiquitous internet
technologies that we all use every day,
but don't think about. Some of you may not
even know these exist. But they were both
introduced around 30 years ago and their
paths to adoption have been significantly
different. The first is IPv6 and was
introduced in December of 1995 and it's so
foundational to the internet that it's
literally called the internet protocol.
IPv6 is the successor to the original
internet protocol. IPv6 is the successor
to the original internet protocol and it
has struggled to gain traction. Only
reaching about 50% market share today
despite decades of effort and superior
capabilities. Second technology is 802.11
also known as Wi-Fi. It was first
introduced and standardized in 1997 and
then Wi-Fi has been a massive success.
It's been it's seen seven major releases,
each one faster faster and more capable
than the last and has become an
indispensable part of our daily lives. So
why the difference in adoption? Backward
compatibility. Wi-Fi was designed from the
ground up to be backward compatible. Each
new generation of Wi-Fi routers and
devices could still communicate with the
older ones. This created a smooth seamless
upgrade path for everyone. IPv6 however
was not backward compatible with its
predecessor. This meant that the
transition required required required
required required a complete and often
costly overhaul of network infrastructure.
This major difference is the primary
reason why Wi-Fi's adoption has progressed
so smoothly while IPv6's adoption has been
a long slow struggle. Another way to allow
for continuous improvement of technologies
is to ensure compatibility with
alternative standards. To illustrate this,
think of the audio codecs that power our
digital music and podcasts. Many different
standards like FLAC, MPEG, and OPUS
coexist today. For the vast majority of
us, the complex process of encoding and
decoding audio is completely transparent.
We just push play. Each codec is optimized
for a specific situation whether it's
streaming high fidelity music or ensuring
a clear voice call over a weak connection.
While this isn't ideal, the ecosystem
works because applications have the
ability to handle the different types of
audio files seamlessly switching codecs as
needed. New codecs can be added to the
ecosystem while old ones are eventually
retired.
So just like these other technologies,
digital identity is at a crossroads. We
have a mix of established legacy systems
and emerging innovative solutions. The
challenge is figuring out how to move
forward without immediately abandoning the
significant investments we've already made
and without destroying the user experience
or preventing progress. A core principle
of the SEDI framework is to support
backward compatibility. We believe the
only viable path forward is one that
embraces interoperability with existing
options without being confined by them.
This approach will allow organizations to
continue using their existing investments
and infrastructure while providing a clear
path to upgrade to newer, more secure, and
more capable technologies over time. It
ensures that progress doesn't require
starting from scratch or forcing adoption
of a single solution across the ecosystem.
To show you what this looks like in
practice, we're going to do live demos. We
realize the risk in that. So I'm pleased
to introduce the participants for our
technical demonstrations today and I'll
invite them to start coming up on the
stage here. In the upcoming demos for this
session and later this afternoon, they'll
showcase how several of the currently
available identity technologies can be
used together in a cohesive and
interoperable ecosystem. While no
technology technologies for SEDI have been
chosen, they will present possible
scenarios utilizing several different
technologies working together for the
first time. You'll notice how the user
experience is similar despite differences
in the underlying technologies. So if you
could start making your way to the stage
as I introduce you. First we have Spruce
ID. They're a US-based company whose
mission is to give people control over
their identity and data across all digital
interactions. Here you go Wayne. Wayne
Chang is here and their software powers
secure standards-based credentials such as
mobile driver's licenses and verifiable
digital credentials that can be used both
online and in person across government and
enterprise services. As a leader in the
decentralized identity and credential
interoperability space, Spruce's
technology supports selective disclosure,
unlinkability, and no phone home
verification. They work with states,
federal agencies, and standards bodies,
demonstrates how digital identity can
enhance access to services, strengthen
security, and preserve user autonomy in a
connected world. GET Group North America
is a US-based company specializing in
identity management solutions with over 40
years of experience supporting governments
worldwide and has been a leader in digital
identity since 2017. GET was selected to
deploy the technology for Utah's mobile
driver's license in 2021 helping Utah
citizens securely share their MDL details,
prove their age, and maintain their
privacy. The company has worked with
government agencies and businesses to
accept and verify MDLs including the TSA,
Utah Highway Patrol, UCCU, and AFCU credit
unions. And then last they'll be
presenting later but their technology is
used in these demonstrations. The Cardano
Foundation is a not-for-profit
organization based in Switzerland which
promotes the education development and
adoption of decentralized technologies to
build future-proof industry solutions.
Veridian is an open source digital
identity platform developed by the
foundation that delivers secure enterprise
- ready verification services which
protect user data and prevent fraud.
Veridian's credential management platform
led by Thomas Mayfield implements self
-sovereign identity for individuals and
organizations. Veridian's core objective
is to ensure authentic communications and
verifiable identity protocols are easily
accessible to all. So I want to personally
thank all of the presenters for our
presenters for our technical
demonstrations today. They put this
together in a matter of weeks and we're
really excited to see these technologies
working together for the first time. So
I'll turn the time over to them.
Thanks so much, Joe. Really grateful for
the opportunity to be here and talk more
about the different approaches especially
in the context of how do we start with
individual rights, think about the policy,
before we rush to the technology, right?
Before we rush to the technology, right?
Because there's an implicit social
contract, right? That is the use of these
digital identity systems and it is much
better for that to be an explicit one
rather than one that is the most
convenient or imposed or anything else,
right? So I think we're all here for the
same thing and being able to move towards
that, I have a pretty nerdy quote actually
that I want to start with from a fantasy
novel by Brandon Sanderson. Then be wise
about it. There are two kinds of important
people, Shalon. Some when the boulder of
time rolls towards them, when the boulder
of time rolls towards them, plant
themselves before it and throughout their
hands. All their lives they've been told
how great they are. They assume the world
itself will bend to their whims as a
caregiver once did when fetching a fresh
cup of milk. Those people end up squished.
Others step to the side as the boulder
passes but are quick to say, see what I
did? I made it roll there. Don't make me
do it again. These are the ones who get
everyone else squished. Is there not a
third type of person? There is, but they
are rare. These are rare. These know they
can't stop the boulder. They walk beside
it, study it, and bide their time. Then
they nudge it ever so slightly to bend its
path. These are the ones who actually
changed the world. And they terrify me for
people never see as far as they think they
do. And I think the wisdom in that is it
takes a diversity of thought, approaches,
and use cases and opinions to actually
consider all the different facets of this.
It's an enormously complex and ambitious
undertaking to build digital identity in a
way that minimizes the harms but we're
able to derive most of the benefits. So
I'm really happy that we're in a room with
a ton of diverse thinkers from people who
are experts on individual rights, what
constituents care about, what people
actually feel, the technology itself,
including the cryptography, security and
privacy aspects of it, adoption, change
management, and user experience, right? So
I think that we're very excited to show
how these concepts from SEDI where you
start with the policy and the rights and
then the technology is figured out after
that, right? That's really what we want to
showcase and how it can help our existing
investments. We can derive value from
those and especially in as we saw with the
adoption, right? MDL it's in I think 17
states at this point. A lot of investment,
a lot of great security people have been
thinking about that model. The TSA spent
over $250 million on machines that can
accept the MDL, right? So is that all to
waste if it doesn't comply or what are we
thinking about here, right? What about
everything else? And fortunately, you
might even be able to shed some more light
on this. Yeah, thanks, Søren. Thanks for
taking all our five minutes. But it's been
actually an honor to work with Utah.
Excellent team, excellent people. It has
been a fantastic experience and we're
really happy of course with all the work
that they perform and we had the honor to
support them to have a successful MDL
issued and being used and utilized in many
not enough use cases and relying parties
including TSA and credit unions and law
enforcement. But we're happy to be also
part of this group that Chris put together
to assist the best we can. with our
experience and with our experience and
with our experience and knowledge and
technology to make whatever next steps
Utah chooses to take successful. So it's
amazing. So what are we seeing over there?
That's a verifier. A verifier is something
a relying party would have. A relying
party being anything anyone that accepts
and consumes a digital identity and MDL a
digital identity. And that can be a
government agency that asks for your ID.
It can be law enforcement. It can be
anyone in the private sector. It could be
a bank. It could be AIDS restricted
alcohol sales, tobacco and so on. Whenever
they ask for that ID card of your driver's
license you can present the MDL or at
least that is the purpose. And you can use
verifiers as simple as an app or in a
fixed point with a scanner. or eventually
online. All that technology exists and
hopefully it's going to be part of the
ecosystem we all operate in. Can you talk
about what's going to happen between this
SEDI wallet and what kind of you know how
is the data transmitted what happens
between this application running on your
phone and application that holds a
credential on my phone? Well, yeah,
originally the ISO standard which is what
the Utah MDL is complying to along with
our close to 20 other jurisdictions that
issue an MDL that complies to the ISO
18013-5 which is the in-person standard.
It had a phone home. It had a connection
to the system on record. That is no longer
the case. And similarly, any verification
we would conduct with the SEDI, it will
only consume whatever you have on the
phone and you present. And it goes, this
could work in the mountains, right? If
there's no internet or anything. Correct.
It will be done offline because again, it
will cryptographically analyze whatever
you have provisioned in your phone as your
digital identity. I always really like
this part where it goes over Bluetooth and
NFC proximity technologies that involve no
servers, right? It's just peer-to-peer
over device. That's actually the best
privacy profile you could hope for, right?
So there are parts that have had
extraordinary investments that are really
valuable from a privacy and usability
perspective. And what we see in that
wallet is not an MDL. There's no driving
privileges there. It is a credential that
is solely focused on identification,
right? And that the reason that it is a
SEDI credential is that it conforms to the
code in SEDI, right? Is the idea. So if we
start looking over here, I told you it
would be a nerdy presentation, right? I
told you it would be a nerdy presentation,
right? We looked in the Utah code, right?
And there is SEDI enshrined in it as
statutes. And when you click in, you're
able to see the different definitions and
requirement from Senate Bill 260 that was
signed into law by Governor Cox earlier
this spring. And thank you to, you know,
representative and senator for the work
and the whole coalition. So it's really
about controls. It's really about these
are the things we're expecting this
credential to do and operating, right?
This credential to do and operate, right?
That's what it represents. So data
formats, everything else, those are things
to figure out, but making it policy-based
and starting it from there is the most
important part because that is the social
contract, right? To express the will of a
people and have those as the agreed upon
controls if someone is to participate in
the system. So we just want to demonstrate
that this model, right, can also work with
the corpus of investment for existing
systems that have been significant and
growing in adoption. So we have looked
into the mobile driver's license technical
specification. Sure. We have looked at the
sub component called a mobile document or
an MDoc and that is just a data format.
That doesn't describe how to use it or
anything else. And there are other pieces
that we can build up to that we can agree
with and are aligned to the SEDI
framework, right? So that is the idea and
what you're going to see with this
demonstration. And similar of of course,
any digital identity, the benefits are
you're not using your card, you don't
share your card, you don't show any
information, it's not copied, you don't
flash pass so-called whatever it is on the
phone, and it respects the privacy of the
user and you only share what you choose.
So if you want just your age to enter a
bar or alcohol sales, that's that is all
you share, not the entire ID. Unless of
course you have a bank or you're applying
for a loan or law enforcement is asking
for the entire ID, that is when you share
if you choose the entire information.
That's right. And MDoc data format to your
point supports selective disclosure as
part of that base. We like that. We're
like, okay, that sounds pretty good. Let's
take that part, right? So we're going to
demonstrate. And there's no contact. You
can do it's a QR barcode scanning. It is
via Bluetooth through a good range or a
tap NFC. Just like everyone is familiar
with Apple Pay and so on. Yep. So let's
say that we're in a use case where let's
call it law enforcement. Let's say there
is warranted ability to request
information, right? So there's going to be
a lot of it being requested. And you can
see there it says all info. So I'm asking
for all of the information from the user.
But this can be tailored to different
profiles depending on the context. And
that's the really important policy work we
need help with to figure out. So I'm going
to share the identity by creating a QR
code. You can either tap or create a QR
code to share it. What it does is it
brokers a secure connection over
Bluetooth. So it adds encryption on top of
Bluetooth because Bluetooth itself has
challenges. That's how the MDL protocol
worked. That part of the MDoc and standard
seemed to be pretty promising. And we were
able to show a QR code. So we're bringing
the scanner. So we're bringing up the
scanner. No contact.
And actually it's going to consume. Yep. I
get to decide what I share or not over
here on this screen. Those are the fields
requested as the user. I get to make the
determination. That's another feature of
the protocol that was supported. And when
I press approve, it's transmitted over
basically the Bluetooth connection peer to
peer. So this would work in the mountains
without any kind of external connectivity.
Right? And again, this is being used at a
ton of airports already. Right? So we're
just able to make sure that that part of
the technology can also work for SEDI
credentials. So you can see that I'm
seeing the information that he shared. I
can bring up the picture of the one last
visual check if I wish. And it has a
document information. So I know it's from
Utah. The document number number and
that's about it. Yeah. As simple as that.
Plus of course I have the verification on
the age verification. Yeah. Well, let's
say I'm at a bar right at night and I want
to show I'm over 21 but kind of don't want
you to know my full name and where I live
my address. Right? How do we do that? So I
will just the one that is asking for the
information can can ask only for the age.
Yeah. So unlike of what you choose. I can
only ask for the age. I can only ask for
the age. And whatever you share, I will
only get the age. And of course, as you
saw, once my I leave that verified
information I have is gone. It's not
saved. It's not tracked. None of that. And
you cannot get a screenshot. Yeah. So the
policy consideration here is that there
are many different attributes that you
could add to this thing and ask for.
Right? So those are the really important
decisions to be made. Can we add veteran
status, disability rating? Can we add how
many dependents you have? These are all
really relevant for programs like Wix and
others that require expedient access, but
we also want to eliminate the fraud.
Right? So and because it's the user
consenting to display the information, you
don't really have to go with one of these
very complex interagency data sharing
agreements if we faithfully present an
opportunity consent for people. Right? So
if it's tough to do a cross agencies and
cross agencies and coordinate, just give
it to the person and let them decide.
Right? All right. So I know your age,
you're looking too young to me. Thank you.
Oh, is this the right one that you've
requested? Did you configure it to just
select the age only? Just the age only.
Well, see, now I have the opportunity to
deny all this stuff. If you agree, I'm
going to have an point. I only see the
point. You can only see the age. You can
apply again. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. The all-in-point. Yeah.
Yeah. Because there is an option also to
request I need find info or to publish
that part. Right. Because that was on. Oh,
for age. Okay. Yeah. Okay. So now I can
let him in. So you turn on the safety.
Wild
Okay. And you say okay. So those are the
only data fields that ever left the
wallet, right? During that specific
interaction. So yeah. See us after will
definitely show that you can do an age
demonstration. I think that I have a
version of the GT mobile app where I can
just ask for the age of mine. But you'll
see other four you'll see other profiles
where we can get it. So great. We have two
more things to show you really quickly.
And one of them has to do… Okay, great.
And those I'm on Derek by the way. Yeah.
Okay. Welcome. Thank you. All right. So
the other two use cases.
One is banking and it's very important for
people to get access to financial services
many of the same methods are more or less
used for benefits distribution when you're
trying to figure out eligibility and
identity verification for some of those
things, right? So this is a generally
useful flow. In fact, NIST
has this National Cybersecurity Center of
Excellence, right? And we're trying to
figure out how are we going to do banking
KYC with the mobile driver's license? I
see some folks in here who are actually
formal participants in this program. So
that's great because a lot of federal
agencies and other states are going to
look to the output of this program and how
that's going to work.
There are a lot of banks, a lot of tech
companies, a lot of other actors, and
basically we're trying to figure out how
do we preserve privacy but also allow for
these kinds of use cases.
They're even talking about shapes that
it's going to work. But right now it's
just called the MDL program. There's no
reason why it needs to be. It could just
be digital identities, right? But that's
kind of the only thing that popped up,
right? So to have a credential that has
steady controls over it would be very
interesting, I think. But back to our
banking example, and this is where a lot
of tech companies have invested a ton of
effort. They're best UX people, they're
best you know, security folks. How do we
make this really good? And the interface
is mostly for the MDL, but those
technologists have agreed that, hey, you
know, other things might be acceptable
here. Passports, EIDs in Europe are not
driver's licenses, right? So MDL isn't so
strongly applicable in some areas. So how
do we allow a diversity of different
credential types to be accepted? And there
have been great strides in the user
experience towards this. So we're going to
basically open a fictitious bank account.
And I'm also going to make sure that I can
show you what happens in the wallet
alongside that. If I can figure out how to
make this small again. There we go. So
we're at Arch's bank. We're going to open
an account. We're going to begin our
banking application. And type in our
email. I'll just imagine that I get a
confirmation code. You've probably done
this before. Go to your email, you find
the code, you put it in. Multi-factor. So
right now it's a phone number, but you
know, future approaches like pass keys and
digital credentials will hopefully
alleviate the need for this. So put a
phone number in there. Same deal. Again,
many banking systems just work like this
today. And a social security number is
required by FinCEN's customer
identification program. So that's a bank
secrecy act requirement. So, you know,
you'll just see it as a requirement for
banks. But at this stage, it's part of
identity verification, right? And what a
lot of institutions do today is they say,
hey, upload a picture of your driver's
license or upload a picture of utility
bill. And none of those security features
are actually valid when you just take a
picture of it, right? Like that's the new
world of security needs to be built on
things that AI is bad at. That's showing
up in person. That's breaking
cryptography, especially post-quantum
cryptography. That's making very complex
computational predictions about physics
and how light refracts on things or how,
you know, something can change
geometrically. And that's what a lot of
the liveness algorithms are about. But it
all starts with having a really strongly
certified credential. And when you want to
verify with it, then it uses the operating
system level controls to say, hey, do you
want to share your data? It's built on the
same technologies as passkeys actually if
you look under the hood. We want to share
it. QR code comes up. We see on the
wallet. I'll scan it. You won't be able to
see everything. I think there's some like
privacy protections with the screen share,
but you'll be able to see the important
parts. So it tells me only connect to
devices you trust. And when I connect,
what happens, you'll see a lower popover.
This is kind of like the Apple Pay
experience or the Google Pay experience.
It's part of the operating system. And you
get to pick which wallet it comes out of,
right? You've been requested a credential
from somewhere. We're going to agree. And
again, we have that opportunity to consent
what gets sent, right? If we send it, then
what happens is instantaneously a
cryptographic payload is sent along with
the data fields and that can be verified
by a server. So it goes to from the phone
to the laptop, goes from the laptop to the
laptop to the server, and then it gets
verified way easier and more secure than
uploading all those different documents.
You submit and you're good to go. So
getting easy access to financial services
benefits a slew of other things requires
really good UX, but we can't compromise on
individual rights. We can't compromise on
security as we get there, right? So let's
take those existing investments that
companies put their best UX and security
people on and apply it to a framework that
is individual rights driven, right? So
that's the proposal for ensuring backwards
compatibility to a lot of these systems. A
lot of the time you think legacy old
experience, but these are actually some
really great experiences happening, right?
And the last thing I'll show is
interoperability with a completely
different system. This is the same
technology harness. Thank you for the
Veridian team for providing their issuance
portal for this part of the demo. So
different company, not Spruce ID. It's not
like one company built all this stuff.
These are interoperable protocols. And
there's something called the Global Legal
Entity Identifier Foundation that is able
to do identification for organizations to
a high degree of proofing so that we can
know who we're doing business with if a
company wants to get a benefit or
something else, right? So basically, I
want to have another credential on my
phone where I can have that employee badge
or proof that I'm part of an organization.
Let's say I'm going to ask someone else
for a credential. or I want to open a
business banking account. These are useful
to understand what entity I'm associated
with. What if you're part of LEO and you
want to show that you're a real cop and
you're not trying to just coerce someone
to do something, right? So you can issue a
credential for this. There's some numbers
as part of it. I'll put my name. We'll
just say employee and we'll issue the
credential. And this is a totally
different technology stack built on KERI
and ACDCs which were protocol and format
invented right here in Utah. You get to
accept it. You get to accept it and a new
credential shows up as an official
organization role. And then when we want
to go request it, we can request a
presentation from that wallet. The wallets
have been linked prior. It's a demo.
Request a presentation. We will see the
request happening and approving it. We'll
see the request is updated, right? And
these are different data formats entirely,
right? But following the same control
principles, right? So that's the end of my
demo and my time. Thank you so much for
your attention. Thank you. Thank you.
Presentation by Representative Cutler on
the role of the state and how to keep the
feds out of our business. I was there'll
be a later discussions.
My boss is here, Marvin Dodge. I hope that
joke didn't get me in trouble.
Oh, you don't last long with a personality
like most.
So this is going to be 10 minutes and then
we're actually going to do breakout into
two breakouts before lunch. I'll give some
instructions after this for that.
Fantastic. Thank you. Thanks for putting
the break. I think the sound will work. I
will see if the sound works. If not, we'll
bring our live demo team back up here to
help. So I brought a couple of friends
with me to help. Let's see what they have
to say. And the sound did not work.
Is your sound up. It's going to be a
little
source thing next to it. You are there. It
was muted though. Okay. So let's see now.
Scoop it. One more try. Welcome to Utah,
folks. Digital identity is fabulous. It's
really great. You're going to want one.
What is the state's
role in digital identity?
What is the state's role in digital
identity? Wait. Wait. Wait. Am I not in
charge of all the digital identity around
here? Wait. Wait. If you see him, tell him
he is in charge. That'll be just fine.
We've all seen lots of evidence of the
challenges with digital identity, the
breaches that are happening around the
world often with governments involved in
these and And let's talk about what the
role of the state is compared to the role
of the federal government or the role of
private industry. And I would suggest to
you that the role of the state, as we have
heard so many times, is not to control or
to create but to endorse. And the reason
it's important for the state to be
involved is a matter of trust. In our
society, some of our largest tech
companies have lost the trust. And the
trust needs to come back to the
individual. And as Phil Windley presented,
put the individual back in control. So
let's try this again on what the state's
role is. Look, this is important. The role
of the state is to endorse, verify,
authenticate, protect, and guarantee an
individual's digital identity. This is
even more important. Personally, I really
like control. But the role of the state is
not to own, create, control, gatekeep, or
surveil an individual's digital identity.
In the age of AI, even a legislator can
create terrible videos that could fool
somebody who's not paying attention. I
think we understand the points there.
Historically, the state has had a
significant role in identity. A
significant role in identity. Often we
think of, oh, well, you know, the feds
have a passport, the feds provide a social
security number. But it, this goes back to
the presentation before. The root is
typically, the root of the identity is
typically a state endorsed credential. We
often start with a birth certificate that
in most cases is issued by a state. And
the state handles most of the vital
records. They're often used used by others
in private industry or by the feds. But
the vital records is primarily a state
responsibility.
This was mentioned earlier, but I think
this is really important in the crux of
our argument for a state endorsed digital
identity. In the tech world where many of
us live, there is often a call for
expediency and for efficiency. It's more
efficient to use this. It's more efficient
to use this. Or it's easier to adopt VHS
than beta. It's easier to adopt or some
people believe they like the Android
interface or the iPhone or iOS interface.
If we start with efficiency as our value,
then we will get a completely different
set of products than if we value value
protection, we value protection, security,
and privacy. I think if there's anything
we've learned over the past few years,
when we think about social media, we think
about online fraud, is that we have to be
more purposeful in designing our identity
systems and in the systems that are going
to be used by millions and millions of
people. Because if we make a mistake, that
mistake scales again and again. So our
argument is to think carefully about your
values. What are your values as a state?
What are your values as an individual? Do
we put our rights protecting our children
at the top of our list? Many people would
argue that in designing social media,
child protection was not the top value.
And over the years, we've had to pay a
price for that as things have changed. And
that because that wasn't the most
important value in designing these
systems. Our argument is that we should
protect the vulnerable. You've all read
the articles of people, vulnerable adults,
vulnerable children getting scammed by
people. We heard a heartbreaking story
today of what can happen when a bad actor
takes advantage of a bad actor takes
advantage of somebody. We must look at our
values and put our most important personal
values, our most important moral values at
the top of the list and not let
efficiency, interoperability, or profit
take over the design of our identity
systems.
Those of you in the in the world of
designing systems understand that we have
to think big and we have to consider a lot
of different elements in our governance
framework. We've got to consider how are
we going to audit these systems? What are
the open protocols? Because historically,
we have to agree on a protocol and a
standard to get mass adoption. We have to
think about how will this be enforced?
enforced. We saw an example just a minute.
Okay, if the enforcement and the verifier
is so ubiquitous that it can be put on a
mobile app, that'll reduce the cost to
install readers in all of our places.
Should we have a right to paper? That's
going to be a debate that I think many of
us will experience. Our friends in the UK
have said everybody gets a digital
identity. We have some people who don't
want a digital identity. How do how do we
help them move forward when 95% or 99% of
the world is moving to digital
transactions? Can we build transparency
into the system so we can identify fraud?
Will we prevent all fraud? You of all
people know preventing
all fraud is impossible, but can we make
the systems transparent so that we can
identify that fraud earlier and quicker so
we can take steps to reduce that fraud as
we go forward. Okay. Last I'll leave you
with this thought is that comparing the
state controlled identity which we've been
talking about and certainly we have some
examples of that in other countries
compared to a user controlled or a liberty
-based model and we discussed many of
those key elements. Selective disclosure.
One issue we haven't talked a lot about
but is really important as we think big is
the guardianship. We've seen the
importance of guardianship in social
media. Should a parent be able to control
what apps a youth has access to? With
vulnerable adults, how do we design
systems to take into account that there
are going to be adults in our lives that
we have guardianships over or youth and
we've got to have that as a key mechanism
to have a guardianship capability. So
those are the key things that I wanted to
present to you.
It's been mentioned by my good friend
Senator Colomore that if we leave this up
to the federal government we're going to
be stuck in in in in in our we're not
moving forward. If we leave it to our
friends in industry, their hierarchy of
values is different. They have fiduciary
responsibility to make money and in some
cases they will view making money as more
important or interoperability is more
important than protecting the vulnerable
and protecting individual rights. It is
our responsibility to exert
our constitutional and moral principles of
liberty, self-determination and individual
autonomy. Thank you for coming and for
participating in this. And I think we're
moving to the breakouts. Chris?
We had a couple questions come up about
will this all be available? We are going
to make slides and this is all being
recorded and will be available online. We
are now going to break out into two
different breakouts. We will be having
lunch upstairs. We will be having lunch
upstairs. So we're actually going to just
move up there now for the breakouts. So if
you exit through these doors, you can take
the stairs or the elevators. We have some
UVU interns out there that will help guide
you. So if you go to room upstairs, room
405 is going to be having a breakout
discussion on the proper role of the state
versus the federal government. So those
who love big government head up there and
advocate for your for your what you want.
And then we're also going to have an
amazing discussion led by Will Seigos of
the SEDI impact on destination economies
and how it's going to help economies grow.
So that's going to be in room 408. So 405
for the government policy discussion 408
for economic and then we'll take it from
there. Those are both at the same time
right now. You have to pick one or the
other. No, lunch is after. I'll take it
from there.
I'll take it from there. I'll take it from
there. I'll take it from there. I'll take
it from there. I'll take it from there.
I'll take it from there. I'll take it from
there. I'll take it from there. I'll take
it from there. I'll take it from there.
I'll take it from there. I'll take it from
there. I'll take it from there. I'll take
it from there. I'll take it from there.
I'll take it from there. I'll take it from
there. I'll take it from there. Thank you.