Hello, my name is Samuel Smith. I'm uh
uh with the Kerry Foundation. I'm also
the originator of the Kerry suite of
protocols which are gaining adoption in
various sectors. Um, I wanted to have a
discussion today about what I'm calling
the last best hope for individual
control digital ID in an AI world. And
it was prompted by the recent release by
the Five Eyes surveillance
uh conglomerate between th those
countries about the threat the cyber
cyber security threat uh that uh
foundational geni models pose and
contrasting that with what Kerry
provides and Kerry stands for key event
receipt infrastructure. It doesn't you
know it's a technical term but basically
it's a digital identity system that that
retains individual control over their
identity which has some important
properties. So I want to talk about that
in more detail.
Um this is an excerpt from the uh report
the link is there from the NSA. Um it's
saying that frontier AI models are
anticipated to exceed current industry
expectations.
Um this is a very technically worded
you know warning basically
uh in months not years um these AI
models will overwhelm
um any say any cyber security
capabilities of existing systems and so
they're basically telling everyone in
this article it's a short article um you
need to um change your stance. You need
to, you know, change how you do things
because we can't guarantee that your
current security systems will survive
what's happening. And what what is
happening is is that certain foundation
models, Mythos for example is one were
developed to try to provide better cyber
security, but in the process of training
them to be better at at detecting
exploits, they also became good at um
exploiting exploits. Um and so that
means that
um other less,
shall we say, um
virtuous parties are building comparable
models. And on those uh once those are
available to cyber attackers, then
pretty much the current way that we do
digital identity, which is what digital
security is based on, um will be broken
everywhere. And that's a problem. Um and
so we need to start doing something
about it. What that means is is that we
actually have two paths forward.
Um the there the two paths are AI based
digital identity and carry based digital
identity. When I say carry I mean the
carry suite of protocols. There's a
bunch of protocols bunch of different
things that are associated with carry.
When I say AI based digital identity,
I'm talking about what the um the five
eyes report recommended is that people
start using AI based uh c counter
measures, defensive measures. In other
words, it's a it's like a
um spy versus spy sort of thing where
where we where both sides have AIS and
the AIS are working really hard to
either defend against cyber attack or to
you know, you know, engage in cyber
attacks. And so they're saying uh
everybody needs to start using AI to
defend themselves because the AI
attackers will be able to defeat your
current identity security systems and
that's a that's a that's a potential
problem. Now Carrie as as we'll talk
about a little bit was designed to be
highly resilient in this sort of
scenario. Um so what does an AI based
digital identity look like? Well, it's a
digital persona that is derived from
continuous tracking and statistic
correlation of one's behavior and
biometrics expression. Basically, the AI
creates
a picture uh you know digital picture of
your behavior based on tracking and
correlating your behavior and then an
attacker has to impersonate
um something that correlates better to
your behavior than than your own
behavior. And so as long as your AI is
doing better job of correlating your
behavior and and collecting those
signals um you know called fraud signals
or anti-fraud signals then the AI can
say no it's you not and not an
impersonator right whereas the attacker
is saying no I can create an AI that can
impersonate you can deep fake you can
can make it look like it's you right and
so what happens is that everything that
you're protecting digital identity AI
learns how to do to better identify you,
the attacker will learn how will you
will will will eventually learn how to
better impersonate you. And so it's just
a continuous cycle. And the only way
that you win is if your protection ID AI
has as much information as it possibly
can have about your behavior so that it
can do a better job of creating a
digital persona that matches you. So if
that isn't scary from a privacy tracking
surveillance perspective, um you don't
know what scary is because that is
pretty scary from a um but that but
that's that's what that looks like.
Whereas carry is based on uh a
cryptocurrency derived fault tolerant
survivable AI and it's survivable to AI
cyber attack. We call it perpetual ID.
It isn't based on on me on the the the
weak things that current
uh internet-based identity are based on
which are largely shared secrets. It's
not based on the weaknesses that are in
the DNS certificate authority system and
TLS and OOTH and OIDC and all of these
systems that have that we've developed
over the last 30 years that are now
vulnerable to AI cyber attacks. It's
it's a it's a groundup new design that
is uh designed from the beginning to be
fault tolerant to survive attack uh to
be able to detect compromise and recover
from it. So so it it is it is designed
to be resilient to these these sorts of
uh attacks.
So so what happens is that if you go
with AI based identity you can get
protection but inevitably it's going to
be totally centralized with zero
privacy. Whereas if you go the carry
route, it's fully decentralized with
best possible privacy. And that doesn't
mean that you have the privacy that
maybe you thought you could have. It
means it has the best privacy you
possibly can have given we're living in
this new AI environment where AI are
consuming all of the data on the
internet and there have available to
them, you know, data to correlate pretty
much anything about anything you do. um
so we can talk about it in more detail
about what best possible privacy looks
like. So so what we want to do is is in
this discussion is answer some highle
questions about what this means. Um so
these questions have topics and then
there's a question and then I'm going to
go into more detail on that. Um but but
let's go back and remember we're talking
about AI based digital identity which
NSA and the major security organizations
from the five eyes countries have said
everyone needs to start adopting or the
alternative is a carry based digital
identity. you know, Carrie's not as well
known, so people don't know about it.
Although it's got some significant
adoption vectors, including one is
called state endorsed digital identity.
The the other one's called open
verifiable calling, which is getting rid
of um uh spam in calling. Um and in the
healthcare sector, there's there's
there's work on on on using carry for uh
patient ID. Um, all of those are major
significant adoption vectors that um
that could put Carrie in a position to
be the last best hope for individual
identity because if we go down the AI
route, we may get security. It's an arms
race. It'll always be an arms race. Um,
but we won't have we won't have any
semblance of of user control or privacy.
So, let's talk about that.
Um the five I's statement calls for AI
assisted defense. So the question is how
do we ensure AI remains subordinate to
humans law policy and cryptographically
verifiable identity infrastructure
without rather than becoming a de facto
authority.
Well
the way that we ensure that is that we
need to have cryptographically
verifiable identity in the first place.
If we don't have that, then we can never
ensure that it doesn't become a de facto
authority because we can't tell what
it's doing. It's not transparent. It's
not observable. It's basically an AI and
that AI is going to make decisions about
about who you are. And you know, and the
goal is to protect you from fraud. But
uh but AIS themselves don't have any
inherent structure that allows them to
separate out what is sensitive
information and sensitive authority, you
know, and and sensitive things that it
should do or not do versus anything that
it's within its um its feature space or
weight space. uh based on you know the
the prompts that it's received and the
objectives that it's received and the
temperature by which it's deciding which
with patch to follow paths to follow um
and I can go into more detail but OASP
re recently released in March 100page
uh cyber security report on the new AI
threat and it is stark and uh because
the the the AI threat poses a threat
that hasn't ever existed for and there
aren't any
uh uh solutions for it. They say that in
the report. All you can do is to try to
mitigate it to some degree.
So, so how we ensure it first is we have
to start with we have to have
cryptographic verifiable identity
infrastructure. Um so that that is the
authority and and individually
controlled. So what are the hardest mech
legal technical governance mechanisms
that are needed to ensure
um that every significant AI action
remains attributable or accountable to
humans and organizations? Well, that
means that we have to build a regulatory
and a legal
um bull work for our individual rights.
The original Constitution of the United
States, you know, has a a couple of
amendments and the fourth and fifth
amendments, but those were written in an
age when there wasn't a digital realm
when when when pretty much everything
was on paper. Information was
disseminated on paper. We now have a
digital realm where information is is
disseminated electronically. And the way
you protect yourself in the digital
realm and the way you protect your
identity, your information, your
presence is is com is is different
enough that we can't rely solely on
those two protections. We need to have
additional protections for that. And one
of those protections is called a duty of
data loyalty. It's the it's probably the
best legal framework that's been
developed over the last few years.
There's some legal scholars um that have
been working on it, written several
papers uh papers on it and the state of
Utah recently adopted it in the
legislation
um that that requires that people who
process data about you must use that
data in a way that is in your best
interest. And that that that's the
start. And then you have to layer on top
of that um a mechanism for people to be
in control of their identity to be able
to then express their preferences. And
it's not simply consent. It's actual,
you know, um engaging in uh in in what
is in their best interest and attaching
to um the use of that data what is
called chain link confidentiality where
the where the terms and the the follow
the data as it goes through the system
so that so that you have an ability to
enforce it so that it also includes
citizen enforcement or citizen recourse.
So there's several there's layers of
mechanisms that we need to put into
place and we're starting to do that in
some places. The state of Utah is is
being a leader in it and there's a there
is a um coalition of other states that
are looking at creating legislation the
same way that it gives us an opportunity
to be able to do that. But but absent
that um uh it's going to be very
difficult to stem the tide of what's
happening with AI and and and because of
the urgency it makes it all the more
problematic. Um
um
so um so the NSA's reports calls for
stronger identity and access controls.
Right. Well um there there's a problem
there.
the the problem is what what what counts
as stronger, right? I mean, um the the
current controls and people have been,
you know, using them for years and and
the and people keep strengthening them
and and they keep adding to them, but
the AI can attack them in such in in
such a broad way now that that they need
to be strengthened,
you know, in a way not ever done before.
It's like I I guess you could say it's
like going from uh from uh armor made
out of out of leather to armor made out
of steel, right? Like to go from from
weak to strong, but you don't have the
ability to build steel armor yet. You
haven't invented steel. So, what do you
do? Um,
so Carrie was designed from the ground
up to not require um an AI to defend
against an AI. It was designed to use
cryptography in the best possible way
that you can use cryptography which
requires key management
and it requires key management done in a
special way. And if you do key
management in that way, then you can
then you can build a system that is that
that is resilient to these sorts of
attack because it doesn't have the
weaknesses which are built into the
current controls because of the the
state of technology 30 years ago when
these systems were designed and then
they've been bolted on and added on and
modified but the core architecture
hasn't changed in in 30 years whereas
Kerry is a new architecture.
Um so when an when an when so this
question is which weaknesses in current
identity systems become most dangerous
when attackers can operate at AI speed
and scale. Um well most vulnerabilities
typically employ
um
a a combination of vulnerabilities. So
you might have an algorithmic
um an infrastructure,
a software and an operating system and a
and a usage vulnerability that together
uh enable an attack. A recursive
privilege escalation attack often takes
advantages of multiple vulnerabilities
to be able to, you know, both move
vertically and horizontally in in in an
or in an access control organizational
space um by exploiting different
different degrees of vulnerabilities.
And so it it doesn't get to where it
wants to go all at once. it just
gradually works there because it finds
what's broken at each point and then
searches for the next exploit, right?
And with AI, they can search faster.
They can combine exploits faster um
because they can search the whole space
and they go, "Oh, wait." You know, in
fact, there was a recent paper, I think
last week, where they were able to
exploit um the memory security model in
Apple's M5 architecture
um through a combination of human and
machine AI um analysis that the humans
could have never done on their own
because they just didn't have the
ability to analyze all of the possible
different things they could think about.
thei did didn't necessarily know how to
how to finish the exploit but with the
human guidance you know in combination
so so so the so so so AI speed and scale
is not just the AI itself it's fact the
attackers are are human the you know
most of these attacks are guided by uh
humans either criminals or nation states
that that that want want to come after
critical or valuable infrastructure and
the AI just is a force multiplier for
for all of those types of attacks, not
just, but is for sure a force
multiplier. And that means that
um even hard to find unknown exploits
that are latent that are in your system
are going to be exploited quickly, which
means that your system has to be
designed differently. It has to be
designed to be fault tolerant to be able
to survive even if it's exploited. And
so you have and so it has so that's
that's a different approach to security.
So let's talk about that a little bit
more. Cyber resilience after breach
because that's the the perfect segue.
The statement assumes breaches are
inevitable.
Um and the question is in a carry-based
architecture what remains trustworthy
after servers databases cloud providers
certificate authorities are compromised?
Well, in a carry-based architecture,
what remains trustworthy is that you
have built a a fault tolerant mechanism
that enables you to recover to detect
and recover from from compromise.
And so what happens is is that um you
you you may not be able to anticipate
all of the um ways that an attacker can
attack you. But if you have mechanisms
that allow you to detect compromise
and then a way to recover from
compromise in a timely fashion, then the
attacker doesn't have time to exploit
that compromise. And like in a recursive
privilege escalation attack, it's
usually it's a sequence of exploits that
take time. Now the time doesn't have to
be very long. It might be it might be
hours or days, you know. Um now now
prior to AI, you know, well well the
current the average time for a breach to
get detected currently and that and I
guess that's no less what you know and
and having an AI as a protector might
reduce that time because it's better
able to detect breaches, right? That's
that's the idea. Um is 6 months and then
90 days after that to contain the
breach. So it's nine months of time that
an attacker has to uh to exploit the the
vulnerability that they've discovered.
So so so carry um is designed so that
the the detection time is on the order
of seconds. It's network propagation
time. Um so so that breaches that are
exploitable
must exhibit detectability. So the whole
system's designed around dete
detectability, right? and and and
everything exhibits as duplicity. So
it's a duplicity evidence system. So for
an attacker to benefit, they have to do
something that exhibits as duplicity,
which then enables
um the controller of the identity to
recover from that um in a timely
fashion. Which means it doesn't mean
that there aren't successful attacks.
means that the the the blast radius of
the attack is minimized um in such that
in many cases the ROI to the attack or
the return on investment is negative. I
mean it costs more it costs more to to
to execute the attack than they get from
it because the attack is quickly um uh
uh contained and and and recovered from.
So these systems that we currently use,
servers, database, cloud providers,
certificate authorities, they're all
based on an antiquated, outdated notion
of security and key management. And
those are really harsh terms. And I know
a lot of people in the industry don't
like it when I say things like that, but
they are. It's 30 years old. And you can
walk back and you walk back the choices
and they were good choices 30 years ago
or even 20 years ago or even 10 years
ago. Not so much 10 years ago, but 20
years ago for sure. Um but at least in
the last 10 years we've had better
technology for key management and carry
is based on understanding that if you if
you have better technology for key
management then you do you do different
things most all of these systems that
that use um DNS TLS OOTH OIDC based
systems all use shared secrets
and shared secrets are inherently weak
and and inherently contribute ute to uh
recursive privilege escalation attacks.
And so it's really just uh figuring out
different ways to to exploit those
shared secrets. Carrie doesn't use
shared secrets. It doesn't have any, you
know, and so so the protection
mechanisms are based are are are
fundamentally different, right? If if
you don't share something, then somebody
can't capture it and collect it, right?
It requires a different type of attack.
And even if they're successful in that
attack, um if you have a recovery
mechanism,
then then then you can recover from it.
And so and so you don't spend your time
trying to build a tank that's impervious
to any sort of bomb. You spend your time
um building, you know, uh a squadron of
tanks that some of them can be
destroyed, but the squadron survives and
repairs itself and is able to continue
to operate. And that's what fall
tolerant means. Um, so I use that
analogy. You know, you can build a tank
with armor thick enough that withstand
any shell, but then it stops being a
tank which is mobile, right? By
definition, tank must be mobile. So, so
it goes from a tank to a to a bunker,
right? And and that's not and and so so
so you have to make some trades. Um, and
and the right in the right trade in in
an AI world is a fault tolerant system,
not a uh a system that that you have to
throw away and start over with every few
days or months because because you know
you you can't tell whether or not you've
been attacked or breached because you
have no uh you have no uh mechanism for
detecting
u compromise.
Um
so
yeah so so actually uh this question I I
sort of jumped the gun on it but how
does carry suite shift security from
protecting infrastructure protecting
secrets to reveal verifable truths and
provenance. So the idea in cryptography
is that um in in asymmetric cryptography
is that you have private keys and public
keys and and private keys are truly
private in that they're never shared. Um
the problem is is that that people who
want to um have an digital identity have
to manage those private keys. And so
that was always viewed as too difficult
a problem to manage. And so we needed to
have identity providers that manage
private keys on our behalf, right? And
then and then the the key management was
hidden from the system. So so you have
identity providers and re relying
parties and and then you use usernames
and passwords or now you know pass keys.
there's stronger things than usernames
and passwords, but you're still relying
on an identity provider for for the
ultimate security of the system. Um, and
and that's and and and that ends up
looking like um shared secrets um bearer
tokens that that the identity provider
distributes around to people to to
entities to be able to engage in things
with over over um secure channels,
right? So, so and the secure channels
are protected with shared secrets. TLS,
you know, uses a a diffy helman key
exchange shar shared secret to do to
exchange an encryption key which is then
weakly authenticated by by by uh uh
encrypting something and then the other
side decrypts it and then sends it back
to you. Um so, but it but it's subject
to key compromised impersonation attacks
and so and so anytime you start doing
things to avoid the hard problems of key
management, you end up weakening
security. Carrie says, "No, we're going
to build key management the right way.
We're going to make it um fall tolerant
and we're and then we're going to uh
enable people to use it in a way that um
that requires um too much effort
uh for for for for the attack to be
successful." and Carrie uh uses
threshold structures multi multi-
signature um witness pools watcher pools
and delegated uh aids that that are
hierarchical so that you can build as
secure a system as you want so that you
can tune the security to the value that
an attacker has to go for. So if it's
going after something really valuable,
then you layer on additional threshold
structures. Um, and relative to the cost
uh of the resources to run a a defensive
AI to protect your system, the
infrastructure for carry is trivally
trivally in trivally, you know, costly
in in in comparison. So that's that's re
that's that's really the the the thing
that we're looking at.
So let's talk about privacy without
surveillance. Can strong strong
security, accountability, and resilience
be achieved without continuous
monitoring and surveillance? Right.
Well, it can. Um
now because what what what Carrie does
is it says we're going to use
cryptography the way it was meant to be
used.
um
and without explaining the carry
protocol which which would take it too
much time. Um it doesn't have those the
weaknesses that our current shared
secretbased um uh systems do which are
vulnerable to exploit by AIS. Um uh AIs
can't brute force
um a public key to get to a private key.
Now if I have a quantum computer that's
a different story but we now have
postquantum you know public private key
generation algorithms. Um and if your
system's cryptographically agile you
switch to them which Carrie already is.
So so so that's a different problem. Um
so what they have to do is what's called
a side channel attack. They have to find
a way to exploit through side channels.
Whereas a shared secret multiple parties
have a copy of that secret.
So the the number the the types of side
channel attacks that work are much
greater. Um so if I've got you know a
carry private key that's truly private,
it's never shared. It never has to be
shared. And even if that private key is
compromised, I can recover from it
through uh car's pre-rotation mechanism.
Then an attacker doesn't gain much by
compromising my private keys. they have
to compromise much more and and that
much more can be designed to be low
friction for the user but high cost to
the attacker in such a way that you
invert the the the resource expenditure.
So it's too expensive to succeed in an
attack against the carry infrastructure
than what you gain for it because of the
the the inherent uh distributed nature
and decentralized nature of its design.
Um
and and I'll go back to this word uh
balance privacy and how does Carrie
balance privacy and accountability? Um
security
um requires secure attribution. You need
to know who's doing what.
Um but but you also
um want to be able to control what
context
people know about who's doing what. And
that's the and Carrie does that. Carrie
gives you the ability to have
identifiers that you use in specific
contexts that are not correlatable to
identifiers you use in other contexts.
But in each context, you have u
perfectly secure attribution to all the
parties in the context. And what that
means is that is that you get rid of the
main main source of fraud which is
impersonation taxes which which def
fakes all of those things because every
participant must be accountable in that
context and so they can't they can't
they can't pretend to be somebody else
because you can challenge them and they
have to prove that link. So if it's an
AI that's an agent working on behalf of
somebody, you can you can challenge
all the way back to that person. If
you're using Carrie and and and that
person is delegating authority to an
agentic AI, um then you then you can
always establish the chain of authority,
right? So so so accountability comes
from from chains of accountability or or
chains of authority or chains of
provenence or uh chains of custody. um
and and and carry inherently is designed
to support th those sorts of structures.
Whereas most security systems are flat.
They they don't have this hierarchy that
enables you to establish these
delegations that are strongly
cryptographically verifiably chained
together.
Um
uh privacy without surveillance. What is
the minimum amount of data disclosure
needed to achieve accountability without
creating surveillance society?
Um that's an interesting question. Um
basically
each context, each transaction, each
application the minimum is different
because um for high stakes transactions
where there's high value
um usually the amount of trust required
amongst the parties is higher. That
means they need to be able to better
predict
um the outcome and the behavior of the
participants to that interaction.
Um for low stakes interactions, the
amount is much less. So you need a
system that that gives you enough for
the highest transactions
um but still allows you to tune it for
the lowest stakes transactions and
Carrie does that. Um but but how do you
pro how do you how do you not create a
surveillance society? Well, you well
everybody in that transaction has to
have balanced
um obligations,
right? The how do you need it to achieve
accountability without creating
surveillance? Well, if the surveillors
are accountable,
then the people being surveiled will
have recourse against the surveillance.
And it's a this is a change in
philosophy. It's been for the last 15
years that I've been working in this
space. It's been that we were hoping
that there were technological means
where you could hide. Well, basically
you could engage in transactions and
hide from surveillance. And that's not
true. With AI, there's no hiding. Um if
the data is on the internet, it's going
to be correlated. Even the smallest
signal is correlatable given given
enough coverage w with and and AIs have
enough coverage right people are
building you know consume you know AI
data centers that are going to consume a
significant fraction of the the world's
global electrical production and what do
they do they correlate they're
correlation machines and they consume
all pos all the data that you can give
them and and correlate everything so
that every every point of information
becomes a a a correlatable signal that
results in in something uh that is
actionable. So so you're not going to
stop the correlation. What you can stop
is the exploitation of the correlation
and that means putting accountability on
the exploiters. Um and that and that and
and that requires uh that requires a a
slightly different uh well a profoundly
different um legal and regulatory and
approach. But from a identity point of
view, it it requires understanding that
that that hiding isn't how you how you
do it. Um you can partition context so
that you can um uh keep keep the
interaction space from leaking out too
fast, but it will leak. No matter what
you do, it will leak. But what you want
to be able to do is make your ability to
enforce um the mi the exploitation or
misuse of that data stronger. And that
and so contextually
to to contextually specific identifiers
can be used to remove um plausible
deniability by the other parties uh to
those transactions. Um so so there's
some specific things we can do.
Um, so we're we're left with a stark
choice.
If Frontier AI reaches superhuman
offensive cyber capability, do our
choices become increasingly stark? They
they do. In fact, a lot of the
discussions I've been having over the
last few years are often in the
decentralized identity space, and
they're usually discussions about, well,
you know, we want to weaken security so
we can get privacy. We're willing to
make trade-offs along those lines. And I
I've always said you can't weaken
security. If you weaken security, if you
give up security for privacy, then you
get neither. And now now that's become
obvious. It's sort of like now if you
want security,
you know, at all,
um then then then it's really hard. And
if you don't have security, then you
have nothing. Because if you can be
impersonated
at will by an AI,
then you have no identity. And
therefore, you have nothing that's
private, right? Because I can't I can't
assume that anything that I do can be
kept private if an AI can impersonate me
and prove to the rest of the world that
it was me that did it. So, so, so
basically, what does that mean? See, see
people think about privacy as well, I
can do things that nobody else can do
and nobody knows about. But, but if if
if someone can attribute to me behavior
that I didn't do and I can't disprove it
and I then suffer the consequences of
it, what what does that mean in terms of
me having any sort of private life? It
means I don't means my life is governed
and determined by outside forces. my
locus of control is zero and and and and
so privacy is meaningless when you have
a when your locus of control is zero.
What does it mean? It doesn't mean
anything. You're you're essentially a
surf or a slave or a or you know a
minion of of the the forces that control
your your your identity. So so it starts
with control. You you have to have
control before you can have privacy.
Uh and and so so so the stark choice is
you need to have security before you can
have privacy and you can either have
security that has zero privacy which is
which is an AI based identity system
because it requires total continuous
monitoring and surveillance and be able
to do a better job at correlating your
behavior to create your digital persona
than the cyber attackers are doing to
impersonate your persona. or you use
carry which is based on a
cryptographically verifiable identity
that's fault tolerant uses key
management providence and
accountability. So it doesn't solve the
privacy problem the same way that you
might think but it does solve it in the
only way possible in in today's
environment.
Um
why is there no stable middle ground? I
think I just answered that. Um if AI
cyber based attack mechanisms can defeat
conventional security based on shared
secrets not carry then there is no
privacy. It's it's total surveillance in
order for you to have any possibility of
having any sort of value in your life.
Otherwise you're you're you can't you
you can't do anything on on the
internet. You have to go off-rid.
Totally off-rid. Like off-rid in a way
that would be for most people um a a
horrible life.
Um
um this is an interesting question. As
AI capabilities increase, why does
continuous tracking or surveillance
based trust become less sustainable than
cryptographically verifiable trust? The
reason it becomes less sustainable is
that it's a never- ending arms race.
The
information
that's electronic once it once it leaks
out, it never goes away.
And it enables correlation to be all
that much better. the correlation
algorithms, the tracking algorithms,
target tracking. Um, uh, you can think
of as there's a feature space and if I'm
tracking something, it's moving through
that feature space. Now, in the physical
world, that feature space might be, you
know, uh, latitude, longitude, uh,
altitude and and time, right? Um, and
then you got velocity, acceleration, all
of all of all of those things, right?
But in but in in identity world, you
know, the feature space has to do with
things like when you logged in to where
did you log in, what did you do, what
did you say, you know, what time was it,
um what browser did you use, what device
did you use, what protocol did you use,
all of those are are features that can
be used to create a digital fingerprint
um that that then can be tracked as you
move through that space. And so it forms
a trajectory of your behavior. And the
more information you have, the more
highfidelity that trajectory is. People
call it a digital twin. So they're
creating a digital twin. And they want
that digital twin to be as close to you
as possible so that somebody can't
create a digital twin that is not yours.
And the AI and your AI that's working on
your behalf can tell the difference.
Right? Well, that means that
increasingly as uh AIs gain access to
more and more information, as more and
more of our society and more and more of
what we do becomes AI enabled, then the
information available to both track you
and impersonate you increases. So, so
what happens is the pervasive will
always go to maximal, right? there
there's no there's no other approach and
maximal means um high resource right I
mean we're already talking about cons
most of the world's electricity being
consumed by by AIS well it's only going
to get going to get more as time goes on
it doesn't it doesn't get less it gets
more um whereas cryptographically
verifiable trust is based on a
completely different set of constraints
that have to do with what's called
computational infeasibility
and and and exposure. And if you don't
expose something to so that it can be
collected, if it's a true private
private piece of information and you can
prove something um publicly without
disclosing the private thing, that's
what a digital signature does. There's
various types of proofs and you can
prove that um indefinitely or
perpetually. So you have perpetually
verifiable proofs. Then you have the
foundation for a security system that
that that
maintains the security without getting
more expensive over time. In fact, it
gets less expensive over time because
most of the cost is really reducing uh
user interface friction. Um and we're in
the early days of reducing user
interface friction. So, so that that
becomes a perfectly scalable system
relative to the alternative
keeping digit humans digitally free as
AI becomes the dominant interface to the
digital world. How must carry be applied
to AI itself so that people remain
digitally free rather than becoming
exploitable, surveiled, tracked,
manipulated or controlled? Well, we want
AI to work on our behalf. We want the
best of both worlds. We want AI that
does what we tell it to do when we tell
it to do it to the extent we tell it to
do it. And for that we need to be able
to have strong delegation
um and have enforcement mechanisms
where we can publish to other AIs that
says our AI is only supposed to do this.
These are the rules. You can verify what
it's supposed to do. when it doesn't
then um then there's a can then then
then then you cannot trust my AI right
and and so there are there are people
talking about um you know uh reputation
systems for AIS but those reputation
systems have to be managed in a way that
humans control and we can do that with w
with with carry- with uh if you have
identity systems that allow secure
attribution that are not based on
correlation tracking mechanism but are
based on cryptographic mechanisms. Then
you can build delegation mechanisms and
authorization mechanisms that are
fundamentally different in structure.
They they break this um flat weight
space constraint that AI has right now
or that makes it impossible to secure AI
because uh everything's in the same
weight space to where you can actually
partition or segment the weight space
into things that are delegable and
things that aren't. Um,
should AI be trusted to protect human
freemen or should AI itself be
constrained by cryptographically
variable trust architecture that keeps
ultimate authority with people? Well,
there are a lot of people who are
talking about the fact that AI can't be
trusted and you know doom and gloom for
society once an AI becomes smart enough.
Um, I think that you know I spent 20
years doing research in AI systems. In
fact, I did that for the early part of
my career before I started working on
digital identity. And yeah, we we we can
build we can build transparent AIs
um that only do things that we allow
them to do if if if we architect them
differently. That doesn't mean that we
have to throw away uh uh generative AI.
we just have to we have to uh partition
the the the uh space in which it
operates so that it's one thing to have
a generative AI that understands uh
natural language. It's another thing to
have a generative AI that you allow to
co to
uh to do things on your behalf that's an
agent. So we can have a gentic AI that
is controlled but uses you know
interfaces and and that means that the
the interface layer h has to have um
safety jackets and when I used to do
work with autonomous vehicle systems
most of the code we wrote were safety
jackets to keep the autonomous vehicle
alive and well and and and safe and to
keep it from doing bad things. Um but we
sort of forgotten about that um w with
and people are people are worried about
that. I mean a lot of people are trying
to build those but they're building it
with systems that they don't they
they're using the same AI for to secure
the the the the safety jackets and you
can't do that. The safety jackets has to
be foundationally different in nature
from a computational point of view. And
and if you do that, then then you have a
chance.
What would a world look like where every
AI agent operates under
cryptographically verified authority by
delegation and thus accountability?
Well, it'd be the best of both worlds.
It it we we would be able to have AI
help us be a force multiplier for us
without worried about the AI hurting us.
Um, you know, now now that's, you know,
there's always going to be, you know,
edge cases where where people will make
mistakes and AIs will be able to exploit
things, but it it won't it won't be this
Armageddon kind of situation that we're
facing right now. Uh, the race against
time. If frontier air AI is advancing on
time scale, months rather than years,
how quickly can society realistically
deploy either of these features at
global scale? Well, the the stark
reality is the only thing that you're
going to be able to deploy at global
scale today is AI because AI is already
deployed at a global scale, right? But
it doesn't that doesn't mean that you
can't switch to carry as it becomes
available to you, right? you can always
make the choice to say, you know what,
I've been using this uh digital persona
AI, but I want to switch to using uh uh
cryptographically verifiable human human
individual controlled uh identity
system. And so um there, as I mentioned
early in the talk, there are adoption
vectors. People are spending resources,
but nowhere near the amount of resources
going into into AI systems in the AI
identity system. if we had a fraction of
that spend going into Carrie, Carrie
would already be available. Um, but but
we're looking at rolling out Carrie for
the state endorsed digital identity
initiative, you know, in in in the next
12 months. So, we're really close and
like I said, they're already using
Carrie for in the in early adoption in
the telecom sector um in and the healthc
care sector. Um so so so the the the you
know the seeds been planted.
We we've got shoots growing out of
ground but those shoots can grow
exponentially fast. All they need is
sunlight, water and and uh and soil and
resources. So we just need resources and
and the adoption can go m much faster.
Once adopted then it becomes a bull work
against uh future encroachment. So, we
get off the uh we get off the uh the
arms race. We stop we stop being in a
resource arms race. We do a one-time
spend to convert to carry and then we
don't have to keep spending and spending
and spending and spending to protect
ourselves.
Um which approach can be deployed more
quickly, more safely, more hum humanly
at planetary scale? Well, that's a
that's a trick question. Um
uh certainly more safely and more
humanly carry more quickly uh not today
but five years from now uh possibly
because because
you don't have to like every five years
you know double the the number of
servers that you have running in um AI
data centers you don't have to fill
space with AI data data centers and able
to keep up with the arms race. So yeah,
so on a on a 5year time frame, if quick
is 5 years, then carry carry definitely
is is the only only viable choice. Um
what are the biggest technical economic
political and adoption barriers to
deploying carry set carry fasten become
a viable alternative before surveillance
space systems become entrenched? Um well
one is just people don't know about it.
um so they don't know to that that it's
that actually is a viable choice. The
other is is that um society is filled
with lots of people who are unaware of
this threat and so they still think that
old systems are the way to go and so
they're they're um you know uh sort of
like the you know sort of like the
oldfashioned arguments used to you know
it's like they're moving the they're
moving the deck chairs on the on on the
Titanic, right? The Titanic's going
down. It's going to go down in an hour,
right? Um
uh as soon as soon as the hole breaches
and it cracks in half, it's gone, right?
But you you you have this sense that oh
well, it's still floating, so we've got
time, right? We we got we've got time,
you know, and and there's no rush. And
the fact of the matter is you don't have
time, which means that you should stop
worrying about anything other than these
two alternatives. And if you stop
worrying about all the al alternatives
but these two, then it becomes pretty
clear where where where for most people
that are um that care about this stuff
where where their effort should go that
they should be helping because nothing
else is nothing else is good enough
besides carry. There are lots of carry
light or partial carry or you know they
do some of carry but not all of carry
stuff out there. And the problem is is
that those systems aren't good enough
because they leave out important things
you need to protect against the AI
threat. So so they're half measures,
right? And half measures aren't good
enough, right? No more half measures. We
there's a we use that motto, you know,
if if you care about security, can't do
half measures. you're either you either
sufficiently secure or or you're wiped
out. Um, so so that's the alternative.
And I have this uh picture that I got
from uh Chris Bramwell who's working on
on on this SETI for the state of Utah.
Um, uh, STEI, the last best hope against
AI. So it shows SI as a as a warrior,
you know, knight to fight the the the
the AI scourge of identity. Not not that
not that AI
is inherently evil. It's just that the
the only solution that an AI based
identity gives us is a centralized,
you know, identity that requires maximal
surveillance. is it's basically you need
to be continuously surveiled so that it
can build a highfidelity uh persona of
you that is better than than the
attacker's AI who is also continuously
surveilling you trying to build a a
higher sufficiently high fidelity that
it can that that it can steal your
identity and and um and exploit you. And
that's a stark choice. Neither of those
are good, right? Neither of those are
are where we want to end up. We want to
get off that train. And so Carrie is is
is a is a path to get off that train. So
I hope this has been helpful. I hope I
you know, if you if you're worried um
then you're if you're only worried, then
you're you're not taking this seriously
enough. You should you should be uh you
should you should be um
uh uh uh worried like you've never been
before about uh the future of digital
identity. Uh g given how fast the the
frontier models uh are growing in their
ability to exploit current um digital
identity systems which which all
security systems are foundationally
based on digital identity systems. So,
so the you use digital identity security
overlay for everything else that you're
doing. And so if those are breakable,
then
then we're looking at uh an an impending
catastrophe. Um uh and so and and what's
going to end up happening is people are
just going to adopt um the easy path
which is uh uh adopt uh uh AI based um
uh digital identity and and and
that and that would be a bad choice for
us. May maybe in the short run it's the
only choice available to us because
Carrie isn't universally available. It's
still in its still, you know,
it's still a chute in the ground. Not
not a not a, you know, whole field of
plants. Um, but it could be a whole
field of plants in the next in the next
couple of years. Um, not not in the next
couple of months, not unless, you know,
a bunch of resources get thrown at it,
which I don't think is going to happen.