Hello, my name is Samuel Smith. I'm
with the KERI Foundation. I'm also
the originator of the KERI suite of
protocols which are gaining adoption in
various sectors. I wanted to have a
discussion today about what I'm calling
the last best hope for individual
control digital ID in an AI world. And
it was prompted by the recent release by
the Five Eyes surveillance
conglomerate between those
countries about the cyber
cyber security threat that
foundational genAI models pose and
contrasting that with what KERI
provides and KERI stands for Key Event
Receipt Infrastructure.
It's a technical term but basically
it's a digital identity system that
retains individual control over their
identity which has some important
properties. So I want to talk about that
in more detail.
this is an excerpt from the report,
the link is there, from the NSA. It's
saying that frontier AI models are
anticipated to exceed current industry
expectations.
This is a very technically-worded
warning basically
in months not years these AI
models will overwhelm
any cyber security
capabilities of existing systems and so
they're basically telling everyone in
this article (it's a short article) you
need to change your stance. You need
to, change how you do things
because we can't guarantee that your
current security systems will survive
what's happening. And what is
happening is that certain foundation
models, Mythos for example is one were
developed to try to provide better cyber
security, but in the process of training
them to be better at detecting
exploits, they also became good at
exploiting exploits. And so that
means that
other less,
shall we say,
virtuous parties are building comparable
models. And once those are
available to cyber attackers, then
pretty much the current way that we do
digital identity, which is what digital
security is based on, will be broken
everywhere. And that's a problem. And
so we need to start doing something
about it. What that means is, is that we
actually have two paths forward.
The two paths are 1: AI based
digital identity and 2: KERI based digital
identity. When I say KERI I mean the
KERI suite of protocols. There's a
bunch of protocols bunch of different
things that are associated with KERI.
When I say AI based digital identity,
I'm talking about what the Five
Eyes Report recommended is that people
start using AI-based counter
measures, defensive measures. In other
words, it's like a
spy versus spy sort of thing
where both sides have AIs and
the AIs are working really hard to
either defend against cyber attack or to
engage in cyber
attacks. And so they're saying
everybody needs to start using AI to
defend themselves because the AI
attackers will be able to defeat your
current identity security systems and
that's a potential
problem. Now KERI, as we'll talk
about a little bit, was designed to be
highly resilient in this sort of
scenario. So what does an AI-based
digital identity look like? Well, it's a
digital persona that is derived from
continuous tracking and statistic
correlation of one's behavior and
biometrics expression. Basically, the AI
creates
a digital picture of
your behavior based on tracking and
correlating your behavior and then an
attacker has to impersonate
something that correlates better to
your behavior than your own
behavior. And so as long as your AI is
doing better job of correlating your
behavior and collecting those
signals called fraud signals
or anti-fraud signals then the AI can
say no it's you, and not an
impersonator, whereas the attacker
is saying no I can create an AI that can
impersonate you, can deep fake you, can
can make it look like it's you, and
so what happens is that everything that
you're protecting digital identity AI
learns how to do to better identify you,
the attacker will
eventually learn how to
better impersonate you. And so it's just
a continuous cycle. And the only way
that you win is if your protection AI
has as much information as it possibly
can have about your behavior so that it
can do a better job of creating a
digital persona that matches you. So if
that isn't scary from a privacy tracking
surveillance perspective, you don't
know what scary is because that is
pretty scary.
But that's what that looks like.
Whereas KERI is based on a
cryptographically-derived fault-tolerant
survivable AI and it's survivable to AI
cyber attack. We call it perpetual ID.
It isn't based on the
weak things that current
internet-based identity are based on
which are largely shared secrets. It's
not based on the weaknesses that are in
the DNS certificate authority system and
TLS and OAuth and OIDC and all of these
systems that we have developed
over the last 30 years that are now
vulnerable to AI cyber attacks.
It's a ground up new design that
is designed from the beginning to be
fault tolerant to survive attack to
be able to detect compromise and recover
from it. So it is designed
to be resilient to these these sorts of
attacks.
So what happens is that if you go
with AI-based identity you can get
protection but inevitably it's going to
be totally centralized with zero
privacy. Whereas if you go the KERI
route, it's fully decentralized with
best possible privacy. And that doesn't
mean that you have the privacy that
maybe you thought you could have. It
means it has the best privacy you
possibly can have given we're living in
this new AI environment where AIs are
consuming all of the data on the
internet and there have available to
them, data to correlate pretty
much anything about anything you do.
So we can talk about it in more detail
about what best possible privacy looks
like. So what we want to do is in
this discussion is answer some high-level
questions about what this means.
So these questions have topics and then
there's a question and then I'm going to
go into more detail on that. But
let's go back and remember we're talking
about AI-based digital identity which
NSA and the major security organizations
from the Five Eyes countries have said (implicitly, red)
“everyone needs to start adopting” or the
alternative is a KERI based digital
identity. KERI's not as well
known, so people don't know about it.
Although it's got some significant
adoption vectors, including one is called
State Endorsed Digital Identity (SEDI).
The other one's called Open Verifiable
Calling (OVC), which is getting rid
of spam in calling, and in the
healthcare sector, there's
work on using KERI for
patient ID. All of those are major
significant adoption vectors that
that could put KERI in a position to
be the last best hope for individual
identity because if we go down the AI
route, we may get security. It's an arms
race. It'll always be an arms race.
But we won't have any
semblance of user control or privacy.
So, let's talk about that.
The Five Eyes statement calls for AI
assisted defense. So the question is how
do we ensure AI remains subordinate to
humans, law, policy, and cryptographically
verifiable identity infrastructure
rather than becoming a de facto
authority.
Well the way that we ensure that is that we
need to have cryptographically
verifiable identity in the first place.
If we don't have that, then we can never
ensure that it doesn't become a de facto
authority because we can't tell what
it's doing. It's not transparent. It's
not observable. It's basically an AI and
that AI is going to make decisions about
who you are. And the
goal is to protect you from fraud,
but AIs themselves don't have any
inherent structure that allows them to
separate out what is sensitive
information and sensitive authority,
and sensitive things that it
should do or not do versus anything that
it's within its feature space or
weight space, based on the
the prompts that it's received and the
objectives that it's received and the
temperature by which it's deciding which
path to follow
and I can go into more detail but OWASP
recently released in March a 100-page
cyber security report on the new AI
threat and it is stark and because
the AI threat poses a threat
that hasn't ever existed before and there
aren't any
solutions for it. They say that in
the report. All you can do is to try to
mitigate it to some degree.
So, how we ensure it? First is:
we have to have
cryptographic verifiable identity
infrastructure. So that that is the
authority and individually
controlled. So what are the hardest
legal technical governance mechanisms
that are needed to ensure
that every significant AI action
remains attributable or accountable to
humans and organizations? Well, that
means that we have to build a regulatory
and a legal
bullwork for our individual rights.
The original Constitution of the United
States has a a couple of
amendments and the fourth and fifth
amendments, but those were written in an
age when there wasn't a digital realm
when pretty much everything
was on paper. Information was
disseminated on paper. We now have a
digital realm where information is
disseminated electronically. And the way
you protect yourself in the digital
realm and the way you protect your
identity, your information, your
presence is different
enough that we can't rely solely on
those two protections. We need to have
additional protections for that. And one
of those protections is called a “duty of
data loyalty”. It's probably the
best legal framework that's been
developed over the last few years.
There's some legal scholars that have
been working on it, written several
papers on it and the state of
Utah recently adopted it in the
legislation.
That requires that people who
process data about you must use that
data in a way that is in your best
interest. And that's the
start. And then you have to layer on top
of that a mechanism for people to be
in control of their identity to be able
to then express their preferences. And
it's not simply consent. It's actual
engaging in what
is in their best interest and attaching
to the use of that data what is
called chain-link confidentiality where
the where the terms and the follow
the data as it goes through the system
so that so that you have an ability to
enforce it so that it also includes
citizen enforcement or citizen recourse.
So there's several there's layers of
mechanisms that we need to put into
place and we're starting to do that in
some places. The state of Utah is
being a leader in it and there's a there
is a coalition of other states that
are looking at creating legislation the
same way that it gives us an opportunity
to be able to do that. But absent
that it's going to be very
difficult to stem the tide of what's
happening with AI and because of
the urgency it makes it all the more
problematic.
So the NSA's reports calls for
stronger identity and access controls.
Right. Well there's a problem
there.
the problem is what counts
as stronger, right? I mean, the
current controls and people have been
using them for years and
the and people keep strengthening them
and they keep adding to them, but
the AI can attack them in such
a broad way now that they need
to be strengthened
in a way not ever done before.
It's like I guess you could say it's
like going from armor made
out of leather to armor made out
of steel, right? Like to go from
weak to strong, but you don't have the
ability to build steel armor yet. You
haven't invented steel. So, what do you
do?
So KERI was designed from the ground
up to not require an AI to defend
against an AI. It was designed to use
cryptography in the best possible way
that you can use cryptography
which requires key management
and it requires key management done in a
special way. And if you do key
management in that way,
then you can build a system
that is resilient to these sorts of attacks
because it doesn't have the
weaknesses which are built into the
current controls because of the
state of technology 30 years ago when
these systems were designed and then
they've been bolted on and added on and
modified but the core architecture
hasn't changed in 30 years whereas
KERI is a new architecture.
so this question
is which weaknesses in current
identity systems become most dangerous
when attackers can operate at AI speed
and scale. Well, most vulnerabilities
typically employ
a a combination of vulnerabilities. So
you might have an algorithmic
an infrastructure,
a software and an operating system
and a usage vulnerability that together
enable an attack. A recursive
privilege escalation attack often takes
advantages of multiple vulnerabilities
to be able to both move
vertically and horizontally in an
or in an access control organizational
space by exploiting different
different degrees of vulnerabilities.
And so it doesn't get to where it
wants to go all at once. It just
gradually works there because it finds
what's broken at each point and then
searches for the next exploit, right?
And with AI, they can search faster.
They can combine exploits faster
because they can search the whole space
and they go "Oh, wait..."
In fact, there was a recent paper, I think
last week, where they were able to
exploit the memory security model in
Apple's M5 architecture
through a combination of human and
machine AI analysis that the humans
could've never done on their own
because they just didn't have the
ability to analyze all of the possible
different things they could think about.
they didn't necessarily know how to
how to finish the exploit but with the
human guidance in combination
so AI speed and scale
is not just the AI itself it's fact the
attackers are human, the
most of these attacks are guided by
humans, either criminals or nation states,
that want to come after
critical or valuable infrastructure and
the AI just is a force multiplier for
for all of those types of attacks,
not júst, but is for sure a force
multiplier. And that means that
even hard to find unknown exploits
that are latent, that are in your system
are going to be exploited quickly, which
means that your system has to be
designed differently. It has to be
designed to be fault tolerant to be able
to survive even if it's exploited. And
so that is
a different approach to security.
So let's talk about that a little bit
more. Cyber resilience after breach
because that's the perfect segway.
The statement assumes breaches are
inevitable.
and the question is in a KERI-based
architecture what remains trustworthy
after servers databases cloud providers
certificate authorities are compromised?
Well, in a KERI-based architecture,
what remains trustworthy is that you
have built a a fault-tolerant mechanism
that enables you to recover to detect
and recover from compromise.
And so what happens is that you
you may not be able to anticipate
all of the ways that an attacker can
attack you. But if you have mechanisms
that allow you to detect compromise
and then a way to recover from
compromise in a timely fashion, then the
attacker doesn't have time to exploit
that compromise. And like in a Recursive
Privilege Escalation Attack,
usually it's a sequence of exploits that
take time. Now the time doesn't have to
be very long. It might be
hours or days, now
prior to AI, well the
current the average time for a breach to
get detected currently and I
guess that's no less what you know
and having an AI as a protector might
reduce that time because it's better
able to detect breaches, right? That's
that's the idea. is 6 months and then
90 days after that to contain the
breach. So it's nine months of time that
an attacker has to to exploit the
vulnerability that they've discovered.
So KERI is designed so that
the detection time is on the order
of seconds. It's network propagation
time. So that breaches that are
exploitable
must exhibit detectability. So the whole
system's designed around
detectability, right?
Everything exhibits as duplicity.
It's a duplicity evidence system. So for
an attacker to benefit, they have to do
something that exhibits as duplicity,
which then enables
the controller of the identity to
recover from that in a timely
fashion. Which doesn't mean
that there aren't successful attacks.
It means that the blast radius of
the attack is minimized.
In many cases the ROI to the attack or
the return on investment is negative. I
mean it costs more
to execute the attack than they get from it
because the attack is quickly
contained and recovered from.
So these systems that we currently use,
servers, database, cloud providers,
certificate authorities, they're all
based on an antiquated, outdated notion
of security and key management. And
those are really harsh terms. And I know
a lot of people in the industry don't
like it when I say things like that, but
they are. It's 30 years old. And you can
walk back the choices
and they were good choices 30 years ago
or even 20 years ago or even 10 years
ago. Not so much 10 years ago, but 20
years ago for sure. But at least in
the last 10 years we've had better
technology for key management and KERI
is based on understanding that if
you have better technology for key
management then you do different
things most all of these systems that
that use DNS, TLS, OAuth, OIDC-based
systems all use shared secrets
and shared secrets are inherently weak
and inherently contribute to
recursive privilege escalation attacks.
And so it's really just figuring out
different ways to to exploit those
shared secrets. KERI doesn't use
shared secrets. It doesn't have any
and so the protection
mechanisms are
fundamentally different, right?
If you don't share something, then somebody
can't capture it and collect it, right?
It requires a different type of attack.
And even if they're successful in that
attack, if you have a recovery
mechanism,
then you can recover from it.
And so you don't spend your time
trying to build a tank that's impervious
to any sort of bomb. You spend your time
building a squadron of tanks
so that some of them can be
destroyed, but the squadron survives and
repairs itself and is able to continue
to operate. And that's what fault
tolerant means. So I use that
analogy. You know, you can build a tank
with armor thick enough that withstand
any shell, but then it stops being a
tank which is mobile, right? By
definition, tank must be mobile.
So it goes from a tank to a to a bunker,
right?
You have to make some trades. And
and the right trade in
an AI world is a fault-tolerant system,
not a a system that you have to
throw away and start over with every few
days or months because
you can't tell whether or not you've
been attacked or breached because
you have no mechanism for
detecting
compromise.
So actually this question,
I sort of jumped again on it, but how
does KERI suite shift security from
protecting infrastructure protecting
secrets to reveal verifable truths and
provenance. So the idea in cryptography,
in asymmetric cryptography,
is that you have private keys and public
keys; and private keys are truly
private in that they're never shared.
The problem is that people who
want to have a digital identity have
to manage those private keys. And so
that was always viewed as too difficult
a problem to manage. And so we needed to
have identity providers that manage
private keys on our behalf, right? And
then the key management was
hidden from the system. So you have
identity providers and relying
parties and then you use usernames
and passwords or now Pass Keys
There's stronger things than usernames
and passwords, but you're still relying
on an identity provider for the
ultimate security of the system. And
and that ends up
looking like shared secrets, bearer
tokens, that the identity provider
distributes around to people to
entities to be able to engage in things
over secure channels,
right?  The secure channels
are protected with shared secrets. TLS,
you know, uses a a Diffy-Helman key
exchange shared secret to
exchange an encryption key which is then
weakly authenticated by
encrypting something and then the other
side decrypts it and then sends it back
to you. But it's subject
to key-compromise impersonation attacks
and so anytime you start doing
things to avoid the hard problems of key
management, you end up weakening
security. KERI says "No, we're going
to build key management the right way."
"We're going to make it fall tolerant."
"And then we're going to
enable people to use it in a way
that requires too much effort
for the attack to be
successful." And KERI uses
threshold structures multi-
signature, witness pools, watcher pools
and delegated AIDs that are
hierarchical, so that you can build as
secure a system as you want; so that you
can tune the security to the value that
an attacker has to go for. So if it's
going after something really valuable,
then you layer on additional threshold
structures. And relative to the cost
of the resources to run a defensive
AI to protect your system, the
infrastructure for KERI is
trivally costly;
in comparison. So that's,
that's really the thing
that we're looking at.
Let's talk about privacy without
surveillance. Can strong
security, accountability, and resilience
be achieved without continuous
monitoring and surveillance? Right.
Well, it can.
now because what KERI does
It says we're going to use
cryptography the way it was meant to be
used.
Without explaining the KERI
protocol which would take
too much time. It doesn't have the
weaknesses that our current shared-
secret based systems do, which are
vulnerable to exploit by AIs. AIs
can't brute force
a public key to get to a private key.
Now if I have a quantcomputer that's
a different story but we now have
post-quantum public-private key
generation algorithms. and if your
system's cryptographically agile you
switch to them which KERI already is.
So that's a different problem.
so what they have to do is what's called
a side channel attack. They have to find
a way to exploit through side channels.
Whereas a shared secret multiple parties
have a copy of that secret.
So the types of side-
channel attacks that work are much
greater. If I've got a
KERI private key that's truly private,
it's never shared. It never has to be
shared. And even if that private key is
compromised, I can recover from it
through KERI's pre-rotation mechanism.
Then an attacker doesn't gain much by
compromising my private keys. They have
to compromise much more and that
much more can be designed to be low
friction for the user but high cost to
the attacker in such a way that you
invert the resource expenditure.
So it's too expensive to succeed in an
attack against the KERI infrastructure
than what you gain for it because of the
the inherent distributed nature
and decentralized nature of its design.
and I'll go back to this word
balance privacy and how does KERI
balance privacy and accountability?
security
requires secure attribution. You need
to know who's doing what.
but you also
want to be able to control what
context
people know about who's doing what. And
KERI does that. KERI
gives you the ability to have
identifiers that you use in specific
contexts that are not correlatable to
identifiers you use in other contexts.
But in each context, you have
perfectly secure attribution to all the
parties in the context. And what that
means is that you get rid of the
main source of fraud which is
impersonation attacks which deep
fakes all of those things because every
participant must be accountable in that
context. They can't
pretend to be somebody else
because you can challenge them and they
have to prove that link. So if it's an
AI that's an agent working on behalf of
somebody, you can challenge
all the way back to that person. If
you're using KERI and that
person is delegating authority to an
agentic AI, then you can
always establish the chain of authority,
right? So accountability comes
from chains of accountability or
chains of authority or chains of
provenence or chains of custody.
and KERI inherently is designed
to support those sorts of structures.
Whereas most security systems are flat.
They don't have this hierarchy that
enables you to establish these
delegations that are strongly
cryptographically-verifiably chained
together.
privacy without surveillance. What is
the minimum amount of data disclosure
needed to achieve accountability without
creating surveillance society?
That's an interesting question.
Basically,
each context, each transaction, each
application the minimum is different,
because for high stakes transactions
where there's high value
usually the amount of trust required
amongst the parties is higher. That
means they need to be able to better
predict
the outcome and the behavior of the
participants to that interaction.
For low-stakes interactions, the
amount is much less. So you need a
system that gives you enough for
the highest transactions
but still allows you to tune it for
the lowest-stakes transactions and
KERI does that. But how do you
pro how do you not create a
surveillance society? Well,
everybody in that transaction has to
have balanced
obligations,
right? How do you need it to achieve
accountability without creating
surveillance? Well, if the surveillors
are accountable,
then the people being surveilled will
have recourse against the surveillance.
And this a change in
philosophy. It's been for the last 15
years that I've been working in this
space. We were hoping
that there were technological means
where you could hide. Well, basically
you could engage in transactions and
hide from surveillance. And that's not
true. With AI, there's no hiding.
If the data is on the internet, it's going
to be correlated. Even the smallest
signal is correlatable given
enough coverage. AIs have
enough coverage, right? People are
building AI data centers
that are going to consume a
significant fraction of the world's
global electrical production and what do
they do? They correlate, they're
correlation machines and they consume
all the possible data that you can give
them and correlate everything so
that every point of information
becomes a correlatable signal that
results in something that is
actionable. So you're not going to
stop the correlation. What you can stop
is the exploitation of the correlation
and that means putting accountability on
the exploiters.
That requires a
slightly different ,well, a profoundly
different legal and regulatory
approach. But from a identity point of
view, it requires understanding that
that hiding isn't how you
do it. You can partition context so
that you can keep the
interaction space from leaking out too
fast, but it will leak. No matter what
you do, it will leak. But what you want
to be able to do is make your ability to
enforce the exploitation or
misuse of that data stronger. And that
and so contextually,
Contextually-specific identifiers
can be used to remove plausible
deniability by the other parties to
those transactions. So there's
some specific things we can do.
We're left with a stark
choice.
If frontier AI reaches superhuman
offensive cyber capability, do our
choices become increasingly stark? They
they do. In fact, a lot of the
discussions I've been having over the
last few years are often in the
decentralized identity space, and
they're usually discussions about, well,
we want to weaken security, so
we can get privacy. We're willing to
make trade-offs along those lines. And I
I've always said you can't weaken
security. If you weaken security, if you
give up security for privacy, then you
get neither. And now that's become
obvious. It's sort of like now if you
want security at all,
it's really hard. And
if you don't have security, then you
have nothing. Because if you can be
impersonated
at will by an AI,
then you have no identity. And
therefore, you have nothing that's
private, right? Because I can't
assume that anything that I do can be
kept private if an AI can impersonate me
and prove to the rest of the world that
it was me that did it.
Basically, what does that mean? See,
people think about privacy as well, I
can do things that nobody else can do
and nobody knows about. But if
someone can attribute to me, behavior
that I didn't do and I can't disprove it
and I then suffer the consequences of
it, what what does that mean in terms of
me having any sort of private life? It
means I don't, it means my life is governed
and determined by outside forces. My
locus of control is zero and
so privacy is meaningless when
when your locus of control is zero.
What does it mean? It doesn't mean
anything. You're you're essentially a
surf or a slave or a
minion of the forces that control
your identity. So it starts
with control. You have to have
control before you can have privacy.
And so the stark choice is
you need to have security before you can
have privacy and you can either have
security that has zero privacy which is
which is an AI-based identity system
because it requires total continuous
monitoring and surveillance and be able
to do a better job at correlating your
behavior to create your digital persona
than the cyber attackers are doing to
impersonate your persona. Or you use
KERI which is based on a
cryptographically-verifiable identity
that's fault tolerant, uses key
management provenance and
accountability. So it doesn't solve the
privacy problem the same way that you
might think but it does solve it in the
only way possible in today's
environment.
why is there no stable middle ground? I
think I just answered that. If AI-
cyber-based attack mechanisms can defeat
conventional security based on shared
secrets not KERI then there is no
privacy. It's it's total surveillance in
order for you to have any possibility of
having any sort of value in your life.
Otherwise you can't
do anything on the
internet. You have to go off-grid.
Totally off-grid. Like off-grid in a way
that would be for most people a
horrible life.
This is an interesting question. As
AI capabilities increase, why does
continuous tracking or surveillance
based trust become less sustainable than
cryptographically-verifiable trust? The
reason it becomes less sustainable is
that it's a never-ending arms race.
The information that's electronic once it leaks
out, it never goes away.
And it enables correlation to be all
that much better. The correlation
algorithms, the tracking algorithms,
target tracking. You can think
of as there's a feature space and if I'm
tracking something, it's moving through
that feature space. Now, in the physical
world, that feature space might be,
latitude, longitude,
altitude and time, right? And
then you got velocity, acceleration, all of those things, right?
But in identity world,
the feature space has to do with
things like "when you logged in, to where
did you log in, what did you do, what
did you say what time was it,
what browser did you use, what device
did you use, what protocol did you use,'
All of those are are features that can
be used to create a digital fingerprint
that then can be tracked as you
move through that space. And so it forms
a trajectory of your behavior. And the
more information you have, the more
high fidelity that trajectory is. People
call it a digital twin. So they're
creating a digital twin. And they want
that digital twin to be as close to you
as possible so that somebody can't
create a digital twin that is not yours.
And your AI that's working on
your behalf can tell the difference.
Right? Well, that means that
increasingly as AIs gain access to
more and more information, as more and
more of our society and more and more of
what we do becomes AI enabled, then the
information available to both track you
and impersonate you increases. So,
what happens is the pervasiveness will
always go to maximal, right?
There's no other approach and
maximal means high resource, I
mean we're already talking about that
most of the world's electricity being
consumed by AIs. Well it's only going
to get more as time goes on
it doesn't get less it gets
more, whereas cryptographically
verifiable trust is based on a
completely different set of constraints
that have to do with what's called
computational infeasibility
and exposure. And if you don't
expose something, so that it can't be
collected, if it's a true private
piece of information and you can
prove something publicly without
disclosing the private thing, that's
what a digital signature does. There's
various types of proofs and you can
prove that indefinitely or
perpetually. So you have perpetually
verifiable proofs. Then you have the
foundation for a security system that
maintains the security without getting
more expensive over time. In fact, it
gets less expensive over time because
most of the cost is really reducing
user interface friction. We're in
the early days of reducing user
interface friction. So that
becomes a perfectly scalable system
relative to the alternative
Keeping humans digitally free as
AI becomes the dominant interface to the
digital world. How must KERI be applied
to AI itself so that people remain
digitally free rather than becoming
exploitable, surveilled, tracked,
manipulated or controlled? Well, we want
AI to work on our behalf. We want the
best of both worlds. We want AI that
does what we tell it to do when we tell
it to do it to the extent we tell it to
do it. And for that we need to be able
to have strong delegation
and have enforcement mechanisms
where we can publish to other AIs that
says our AI is only supposed to do this.
These are the rules. You can verify what
it's supposed to do. When it doesn't
then you cannot trust my AI.
And so there are people
talking about reputation
systems for AIs but those reputation
systems have to be managed in a way that
humans control and we can do that with
KERI. If you have
identity systems that allow secure
attribution that are not based on
correlation tracking mechanism but are
based on cryptographic mechanisms. Then
you can build delegation mechanisms and
authorization mechanisms that are
fundamentally different in structure.
They break this flat weight
space constraint that AI has right now
that makes it impossible to secure AI
because everything's in the same
weight space to where you can actually
partition or segment the weight space
into things that are delegable and
things that aren't.
Should AI be trusted to protect human
freedom or should AI itself be
constrained by cryptographically
variable trust architecture that keeps
ultimate authority with people? Well,
there are a lot of people who are
talking about the fact that AI can't be
trusted and doom and gloom for
society once an AI becomes smart enough.
I think I spent 20
years doing research in AI systems. In
fact, I did that for the early part of
my career before I started working on
digital identity. And yeah, we can
build we can build transparent AIs
that only do things that we allow
them to do if we architect them
differently. That doesn't mean that we
have to throw away generative AI.
We just have to partition
the space in which it
operates so that it's one thing to have
a generative AI that understands
natural language. It's another thing to
have a generative AI that you allow to
to do things on your behalf that's an
agent. So we can have a gentic AI that
is controlled but uses you know
interfaces and that means that the
the interface layer has to have
safety jackets and when I used to do
work with autonomous vehicle systems
most of the code we wrote were safety
jackets to keep the autonomous vehicle
alive and well and safe and to
keep it from doing bad things. but we
sort of forgotten about that.
People are worried about
that. I mean a lot of people are trying
to build those but they're building it
with systems that
they're using the same AI for, to secure
the safety jackets and you
can't do that. The safety jackets has to
be foundationally different in nature
from a computational point of view.
And if you do that, then you have a chance.
What would a world look like where every
AI agent operates under
cryptographically-verified authority by
delegation and thus accountability?
Well, it'd be the best of both worlds.
It it we would be able to have AI
help us be a force multiplier for us
without worried about the AI hurting us.
There's always going to be
edge cases where people will make
mistakes and AIs will be able to exploit
things, but it won't be this
Armageddon kind of situation that we're
facing right now. The race against
time. If frontier AI is advancing on
time scale, months rather than years,
how quickly can society realistically
deploy either of these features at
global scale? Well, the stark
reality is the only thing that you're
going to be able to deploy at global
scale today is AI because AI is already
deployed at a global scale, right? But
it doesn't mean that you
can't switch to KERI as it becomes
available to you, right? You can always
make the choice to say "you know what?,
I've been using this digital persona
AI, but I want to switch to using
cryptographically-verifiable human
individual controlled identity
system." And so there, as I mentioned
early in the talk, there are adoption
vectors. People are spending resources,
but nowhere near the amount of resources
going into AI systems, into AI
identity system. If we had a fraction of
that spend going into KERI, KERI
would already be available. But
we're looking at rolling out KERI for
the State Endorsed Digital Identity (SEDI)
initiative in the next
12 months. So, we're really close and
like I said, they're already using
KERI in the early adoption in
the telecom sector and the healthcare sector.
So the seed has been planted.
We've got shoots growing out of
ground but those shoots can grow
exponentially fast. All they need is
sunlight, water and soil and
resources. So we just need resources and
and the adoption can go much faster.
Once adopted then it becomes a bulwark
against future encroachment. So, we
get off the
arms race. We stop being in a
resource arms race. We do a one-time
spend to convert to KERI and then we
don't have to keep spending
and spending to protect
ourselves.
which approach can be deployed more
quickly, more safely, more humanely
at planetary scale? Well,
that's a trick question.
certainly more safely and more
humanely KERI more quickly not today
but five years from now possibly
because you don't have to every five years
double the number of
servers that you have running in AI
data centers you don't have to fill
space with AI data centers and able
to keep up with the arms race. So yeah,
so on a 5-year time frame, if quick
is 5 years, then KERI definitely
is the only viable choice.
What are the biggest technical economic
political and adoption barriers to
deploying KERI set KERI fasten become
a viable alternative before surveillance
space systems become entrenched? Well,
one is just people don't know about it.
so they don't know to that it's
that actually is a viable choice. The
other is that society is filled
with lots of people who are unaware of
this threat and so they still think that
old systems are the way to go and so
they're sort of having the
old fashioned arguments.
it's like they're moving
moving the deck show on the
Titanic, right? The Titanic's going
down. It's going to go down in an hour,
right?
As soon as the whole breaches
and it cracks in half, it's gone, right?
But you have this sense that "Oh
well, it's still floating, so we've got
time, right? We've got time,
and there's no rush." And the fact
of the matter is you don't have
time, which means that you should stop
worrying about anything other than these
two alternatives. And if you stop
worrying about all the alternatives
but these two, then it becomes pretty
clear where for most people
that care about this stuff
where their effort should go that
they should be helping because nothing
else is good enough
besides KERI. There are lots of "KERI light"
or partial KERI or they
do some of KERI but not all of KERI
stuff out there. And the problem is
that those systems aren't good enough
because they leave out important things
you need to protect against the AI
threat. So they're half measures,
right? And half measures aren't good
enough, right? No more half measures.
We use that motto
If you care about security, you can't do
half measures. `You're either
sufficiently secure or you're wiped
out.` So that's the alternative.
And I have this picture that I got
from Chris Bramwell who's working on
this SEDI for the State of Utah.
SEDI: the last best hope against
AI. So it shows SEDI as a warrior,
The knight to fight the
AI scourge of identity. Not that AI
is inherently evil. It's just that the
the only solution that an AI-based
identity gives us is a centralized,
identity that requires maximal
surveillance. It's basically you need
to be continuously surveilled, so that it
can build a high-fidelity persona of
you that is better than the
attacker's AI who is also continuously
surveilling you trying to build a
sufficiently-high fidelity that
it can steal your
identity and exploit you. And
that's a stark choice. Neither of those
are good, right? Neither of those
are where we want to end up. We want to
get off that train. KERI is
is a path to get off that train.
I hope this has been helpful. I hope
that if you're worried,
then if you're only worried, then
you're not taking this seriously
enough. You should be you
worried like you've never been
before about the future of digital
identity. Given how fast the
frontier models are growing in their
ability to exploit current digital
identity systems which all
security systems are foundationally
based on digital identity systems.
You use digital identity security
overlay for everything else that you're
doing. If those are breakable,
then we're looking at an impending
catastrophe. What's
going to end up happening is people are
just going to adopt the easy path
which is adopt AI-based
digital identity.
That would be a bad choice for
us. Maybe in the short run it's the
only choice available to us because
KERI isn't universally available.
It's still a chute in the ground. Not
not a whole field of
plants. But it could be a whole
field of plants in the next
couple of years. Not in the next
couple of months, not unless
a bunch of resources get thrown at it,
which I don't think is going to happen.
Video: Sam and Caleb Smith
Subtitles: Henk van Cann and Kor Dwarshuis