I will Ed, but I'm going to
having a great time.
Thank you.
Yeah, exactly.
No one else is looking
If I could just photograph every single
person.
Sometimes
the worst
assistance.
She was
I can't believe this.
Just one minute.
If everybody could take their seats.
We're just about to get started.
Okay, we're going to get started with
the afternoon session. So, this
afternoon we're going to be delving in a
little deeper into some of the unique
approaches of state endorsed digital
identity. These are some lessons we've
already learned as we've been evaluating
in depth what does security need to look
like? What does privacy need to look
like? What does it mean to have open
standards? Um so this afternoon we're
first going to hear from Alan Fuller
who's going to talk to us about state
endorsed digital identity being critical
public infrastructure. We're then going
to have Scott Perry who's joining us
from Seattle. Correct. and he's gonna
and Scott is actually he's the uh he's
been working on C2PA which is um major
providance protocol out in the news
right now. He's going to talk about to
us about open standards and protocols.
Timothy Ruff is going to talk to us
about guardianship and then we're going
to have a demo and presentation about
guardianship from Cardano and then the
clear and Utah life group. Uh that's
going to be followed by Steve Macau
discussing why SETI will have zero
tracking and zero surveillance. And then
we're going to finish up with Sim Simon
Wood who's going to be joining us from
Finland talking about how they cut cost
in government services 99% using digital
identity and data governance
modernization. So Alan Fuller,
thank you Chris. It's a pre pleasure to
be here today. I'm so grateful. I've had
really great conversations here and I'm
so glad uh that you're all able to come.
Let me just quickly make one big point
and and um I I want to talk about
digital identity as critical
infrastructure. So um as Phil Windley
talked about earlier, the purpose of a
digital identity is to create a trusted
relationship online. And we used to talk
about with on with uh trust credentials
that was going to be uh like with
identity and access management systems
that it was you needed something you
know and something you have. But that is
becoming not sufficient. And what we
need is something you can prove and
something you can prove is a credential
with cryptographic codes that can prove
that can verify both the holder and the
issuer of the credential. And I just
want to point out that this is actually
new territory for states to be leaning
in to this area where we are adding a
state endorsement to a relationship
where it hasn't really existed before.
Um yes, the state has issued driver's
licenses and other credentials, lots of
them, but the online age changes the
nature of these things.
Okay. So in the digital age where so
much of our lives have moved online from
social media, social banking, commerce,
uh application for government services
where so much of our relationships have
moved online, this identity, digital
identity becomes absolutely critical
infrastructure. There's so many public
sector areas that rely on this and we've
seen in our country since co um hundreds
of billions of dollars in fraud and a
lot of that fraud is tied directly to uh
not having good identity verification.
So, you know, for at the state level,
public public um social services systems
like food stamps or unemployment
insurance or housing assistance or
Medicaid or child health insurance. Uh
many of these rely they all rely on
being able to identify someone
successfully. Um we have a lot of
discussion in our state about voter
registration and signature gathering and
petitions for citizen uh initiatives.
Can we do those digitally without having
a true digital identity? In the last
legislative session, one of our leading
senators asked me, "What'll it take to
be able to do online elections? And will
this help us do it?" And I told them, I
know for darn sure you can't do an an
online election without a digital
credential that is reliable and
trustworthy for identity um professional
licenses and education credential and
also our corrections and public safety
interactions. Across the private sector,
we have a a plethora of of use cases as
well that rely on secure online
infrastructure.
uh whether it's verifying proof of age
online or in person, whether it's uh
accessing our health records and
benefits and also our financial transa
transactions. We have the know your
customer requirements in that area and
then we have many different online
commercial and travel related needs. But
we have a big problem and uh so as part
of my organization we have the state
cyber security center and what we see is
we're constantly under attack. Our state
systems in Utah have about a billion and
a half scans per day of our system. And
we have uh numerous efforts by uh by
malicious actors trying to create fraud,
trying to create uh ransomware attacks.
And so what we see is uh our
infrastructure especially our digital
infrastructure of all kinds will be
under attack. And the point of attack,
the attack vector most often used is
identity.
And so because digital identity is
critical infrastructure, incomplete and
half measures with regard to the
security of these systems uh are not
acceptable. We we have to have
reciprocity between states, but that
also means that all states need to have
strong security around their digital
identity systems. We have to build SETI
with the highest level of security that
is available and we know that nothing is
perfect. So we need an ability if
compromise occurs or I should say when
compromise occurs we must have a way to
recover. So when we think about SETI and
we think about keys uh cryptographic
keys that are the backing that
credential what I'm talking about for a
technical person in the technical people
in the room is we need a way to rotate
those keys. One of the concerns I have
about the current uh MDL technology is
that we don't have a great ability to
recover if those if those are
compromised you know short of cancelling
and reissuing credentials. So the
ability to revoke is important. the
ability to um
recover if an if it's compromised is
essential. Thank you so much. Glad
you're here.
We could do this quickly like a pit
stop, right?
All righty.
They said wait 30 seconds.
Something kicked in.
There we go. Yay. All right. So, my name
is Scott Perry. I'm here to talk about
open standards and open protocols. And
so
when you're looking at a SETI project,
okay, we're just getting started,
but there's been effort to deal with
decentralized identity for the last 20
years, starting with Phil Windley
co-chairing the internet identity
workshop 20 years ago. And then for me,
it's been 10 years after I got a call
from Timothy Ruff saying, "I need help
around trying to deal with internet
trust." And I realized as an auditor
that was auditing certification
authorities, I realized that the
traditional model wasn't going to work
to add internet to add the kind of trust
that we're trying to do with the SETI
project.
So just a quick little bit about me. I'm
the auditor in the room. I was auditing
for the la for my career last 20 years
I've been auditing cryptography as as as
a profession auditing it's a small group
of folks that audit certification
authorities I was the auditor for a
certification authority based in Utah
it's great to be back here um uh I was
working with digert for quite a long
time and uh I've also been leading some
open source and open uh standards
projects that are listed here. But I I
want to focus on the acronym suit that
I'm going to talk about because it's
important for folks to understand there
has been a lot of work. There was a
question around is it going to work
today? I'd say two years ago things
hadn't been completely baked in, but I
think we're ready. the open-source
community is absolutely ready for SETI
and I'm excited uh for them to
demonstrate their value in all of the
work that they've been doing for over 10
years. And so when we start about I'm
going to give you just a summary of some
of the organizations that I've been
touched with that have been developing
some unique products that can be
leveraged with into the SETI project and
it starts with the Linux Foundation. So,
I don't know if you know, but the Linux
Foundation is the largest repository of
open- source code in the world. They
operate 100% of all the supercomputers
and 62.7
of servers run the Linux uh kernel. And
so, they decided, you know, to get
involved in decentralized trust. There
was a number of projects that was
driving some of this type of thinking.
And so they uh established a subset of
their organization uh last year and they
invited uh and consolidated a couple of
open- source uh and open standards
projects. Uh one that uh is called the
trust over IP and I'd invite all of you
to spend time going to the trust over
IP. I am the co-chair of the steering
committee. We have a couple of steering
committee members here in the in the
audience and they've been doing enormous
work to get ready for the SETI project.
We've created a a a stack a technology
and a governance stack. We everyone's
talking about governance. Trust over IP
is the leading organization driving
governance standards and methodologies
and toolkits. And I hope that the
organization here, the SETI projects
uses it because it's been successful in
the C2PA, in Glyfe, in the government of
Bhutan and such. It also is housing
Kerry. You've heard some stories about
Kerry. It's a blueprint of how to
decentralize identity and make security
more autonomous and user controlled.
It's exactly one of the the main uh
principles within the SETI project. We
have a trust st spanning protocol which
acts underneath the internet protocol to
to uh add to the ability to authenticate
senders and payloads of transactions
because we need that level of trust in
our transaction protocols and also it is
leading around trust registries which
are public repositories of those that
have passed certain governance
frameworks.
The open the open wallet foundation was
was founded in August of 2023. It hosts
components that can be used to create
secure, flexible and portable wallets.
It's a big where are we going to keep uh
these the SETI credentials? We need a
secure place because they have private
cryptographic keys. Also we've talked
about the you know the W3C started in
1994 produces two key standards that we
can leverage within the SAD STEI project
the decentralized identifiers the DIDS
projects as well as defining the the
components of verifiable credentials
which we expect to use in the
decentralized identity foundation
started in 2017. We have a number of
projects that are working that can add
value. They are the leading place to to
deal with all of the decentralized
identity methods that are out in the
marketplace and they are working to
consolidate that. They're creating uh
standards around the communication using
DIDCOM as well as the credentation
exchange of credentials as well as
hosting um an organization called the
creators assertion working group which I
co-chair which deals with individual and
organizational attribution to any
digital object based on the content
credential created by the CTPA. So I
would look up look that up as well. uh
also the open ID which has been around
since 2007 and has modified their
standards to deal with with verifiable
credentials with open ID connect and
open ID verifiable credentials.
ISO as we have mentioned here has been
instrumental in creating foundational
security uh standards both with quality
and ISO 2701 for for foundational
security management systems as well as
they have identity management uh
standard ISO 24760
and finally also the mobile driver's
license the ISO 1818013
Three,
we talked a little bit about what the
role of the federal government would be.
Well, NIST is is providing a lot of
value there associated with dealing with
postquantum cryptography. They're also
dealing with uh you know the the this
the certification of hardware security
modules which protect your private key
and are the leading standard for digital
identity guidelines both for proofing of
identity authentication and federation.
So what's the case for open standards?
How do you use it? Okay, at the end of
the day it enhances interoperability
and compatibility. Okay.
It prevents the vendor lock in so that
all the tech vendors are using open
standards and they can use it. So you're
not locked into a individual technology
company uh uh you know and and can't get
out of that.
It creates the innovation and
collaboration. You're not limited to an
individual's company R&D. You're you're
leveraging world R&D. And that's what
the state the organizations that I work
for they are creating that research and
development that we could leverage
it in it and increases flexibility and
Joe Jackson mentioned about future
proofing. They're baking in uh you know
advances of these standards to deal with
new technologies as they come along and
they're free. state loves free, right?
And and the best way to leverage it is
steal this technology and steal these
standards because it's there for the
taking and they work. So I'm going to
just walk through I'm not going to go
into details of some of the products
that we've created in the open standards
world but these are the some some of the
ones as a governance um you know
professional have leveraged on and you
know we've realized there was a trust
you know triangle with the issuer holder
and verifier trust over IP added a
governance model and and we have found
that that's the missing that's the
secret sauce into making it long lasting
and and and workable.
This I'm not going to go into the
detail, but this is the trust over IP uh
trust stack and you can see that there's
been a lot of work that's gone into it
and Chris Raml said to me, if you do one
thing, let people know how complicated
it is and we've done a lot of the
bakedin work. So, governance framework,
it's already built. The framework's you
don't have to worry about it. You just
have to put in your requirements into
the governance framework and then you
could leverage the time and energy to
get this to market. So I'm going to
quickly go through the reasons why you
should adopt open standards.
It's all there and I think we're ready
to go and I think you could take
advantage of a lot of the work that's
been done to make this happen. If you
want to have an idea of a uh white paper
that's free to use on how to use
governance and use trust registries, I
put it out there. It'll be in the
videotape so that you could, you know,
access this at your leisure.
Thank you very much for your time.
Yeah.
I would like to recognize two
individuals
if they are here. Scott Stoornetta, are
you here? Been walking around. Is he in
the room?
Samuel Smith.
He took off.
I was hoping to I want to acknowledge
two people whom I think are uh fathers
of modern uh digital trust and I'll just
say that uh Scott Stoetta
um was cited by Satoshi Nakamoto's
Bitcoin paper. He's uh the original
conceiver of blockchain which is a
really important innovation in digital
trust. We wouldn't have cryptocurrency
without that innovation. And literally
the creator of blockchain quoted Scott
Stoornetta who's been here today. He's
out in the hall or somewhere. And then
Sam had to leave. Sam is the creator of
the carry protocol key event receipt
infrastructure that has inspired the
SETI identity model including the very
exciting thing I get to talk about which
is guardianship and delegation. A really
big breakthrough in digital trust to
solve a very thorny problem. Now I'm
going to break from how I usually
present things and I am going to um
I'm going to really almost read the
slides which I hate to do that but I
know this is being videoed and I know
these presentations are going to be
asked for and I want anyone who gets
this presentation at a later time to be
able to understand every single point
and so um so you're going to see me you
know uh basically reading some of this
but we're going to go quickly really
important concept. First of all, a
couple of definitions. Guardianship
gives someone legal authority and
responsibility to make decisions for
another like a child or a disabled
person. So, real key concepts underlying
there, legal authority
and responsibility.
Two different really important concepts
that make up guardianship.
Uh, delegation. Oh, I want to wait for
my example to come up. It's a little bit
of a lag here. Temporarily transfer
specific duties or powers, but not full
legal responsibility. Key concepts are
temporarily and specific duties or
powers and not full legal
responsibility. That's the difference
between guardianship and delegation. So,
let's give an example. If a parent
delegates school pickup to a neighbor,
the parent still holds the ultimate
responsibility for the child's welfare.
Okay, that's just a task that has been
delegated, but not ultimate
responsibility or legal uh authority.
Guardianship legally transfers that
responsibility. The guardian and not the
parent is now the one accountable for
decisions and care. So those are the two
conceptual differences. Now, um I'm
going to share with you 10 tools that we
use in combination to make guardianship
and delegation work as well as all of
the rest of the SETI uh protocol. Um I
sh I chose logo uh Legos here instead of
a toolbox.
The difference is when you put Legos
together, you might make a pirate ship,
you might make a pirate, you might make
spaceship, you might make a dinosaur.
You put them together in different
combinations to do the thing you're
trying to do. a toolbox. You get out of
the toolbox and you you do something to
use the tools and then you're done. So
with SETI, it's very much the Legos even
though they are tools. The first tool is
verifiable containers. Now for those of
you familiar with verifiable
credentials, we're talking about the
same concept. But a verifiable
credential is misnamed.
It is a container that holds data and
makes it portable. It might or might not
be a credential. It could have anything
inside the container. It's the container
that's verifiable technically. So, but
it makes data portable and verifiable.
The next tool is secure attribution to
verify who digitally signed a thing. So,
if you get a container that has some
data in it, who put that container
together?
Who did it?
Uh, and and being able the secure part
is really important. Verify who did it.
The third tool, non-repudiability. You
can't later say that you didn't. Once
it's been signed,
it is nonrepudiable. You can't later say
someone else did that. So when you have
um encryption with TLS or HTTPS, you see
the encryption that happens on the
internet, there is reputability. You
don't know who is on the other side of
it's not bound to a human person or an
individual.
It's just um there's a there's a weak
form of authentication that goes with
encryption, but it's not like a digital
signature that you can actually bind to
an individual and say who did the thing.
Uh chained signatures which give you
verifiable provenence. So you can
actually see a chain of authority rather
than just a single level.
So if someone signed something like a
manager, well, who was their boss?
Where' they get their authority from?
Who was their boss? Who did they work
for? And is that really the company? How
do we know that was really the company?
And on you can see a full chain and it's
unlimited. A full chain of providence on
there is another really important tool.
And then weighted multic critical for
business and and a whole lot of other
cases we're going to talk about here in
a moment. But weighted multic means that
you can have one of two signatures. You
can have one of one just one person
signs it and they have the full weight.
You could have one of two, two of three,
five of seven, 11 of 92, whatever you
make up. Okay? So, it's weighted because
you can have one signature have more
weight than another. And in a situation
with divorced parents and things like
that and and where the court might be
intervening, really important in guard
uh guardianship to have weighted
multi-IG. We'll talk a little bit about
that. uh consent,
the ability to use your identity to make
a non-repudable reputable agreement and
say I I agree to a thing. Delegation of
authority, which we're going to talk
about in a little greater detail,
revocability of that uh um delegation
and critically a really important
breakthrough with SETI privacy
respecting delegation. I was just
talking to a representative from another
state who said that the reason that they
were adopting a very you know popular
technology for identity is because their
technical people thought that there was
no way to get around a phone home for
revocation. That is not true. There is a
way to get around a phone home and have
privacy respecting revocation. really
important breakthrough in digital trust
in one of the tools in SETI graduated
disclosure which can be selective uh
contractual basically you can disclose
as little as you want to disclose when
you're doing something and there's
actually a way to only disclose that
thing once terms for disclosure have
been agreed to and consented to and that
can happen behind the scenes with
Agentic AI and these agreements could be
made and you actually don't disclose a
thing until the terms have been agreed
and it's mutual it's like it's like a
real time ND DA done digitally really
exciting capability uh and detection and
recovery from compromise. As a matter of
fact, SEI brings a a four-step concept
I'm very excited about from a security
standpoint. SETI expects compromise,
then it can detect compromise, then it
can contain compromise and recover.
These are mind-bendingly awesome in
digital trust. Expect, detect, contain,
recover.
Uh, secure attribution. Really
important. In Utah law, an electronic
signature can be as legally valid as
handwritten with some assumptions.
There's got to be an intent to sign.
There's got to be attribution, which is
where SETI comes in and really helps uh
consent to electronic transaction, which
interestingly uh there's going to be a
dilemma, a legal one. Can you use
digital means to agree to use digital
means?
I that's going to be a fun one. Uh and
then no legal exclusion. Sometimes
there's a legal exclusion that says you
cannot use digital. You must have paper.
Saidi can use its own tools to prove
each of these. Doesn't mean that we
legally want it to. There's going to be
some policy debates, but it does mean
that SETI can use the tools to do these
things. So guardianship, examples of
guardianship, parent of a child, the
natural guardian, guardian of a disabled
adult, guardian for an orphan, uh, which
is courtappointed, or temporary
guardianship like when parents are
traveling.
Guardianship is the missing piece of
government digital identity. You don't
see it anywhere. You don't see it talked
about. I think it is the the the cherry
on the Sunday when you're doing a
digital identity system. If you're
government, if you're not government,
you don't care as much. But when you are
government, you absolutely
um are the dog wagged by the tail of
dependent populations.
So these are the u children, infants,
elderly, disabled, homeless, right?
There's advocates for all of those and
and they're loud and they're powerful
and they should be. And so to be able to
have
uh guardianship and digital guardianship
that actually brings those dependent
populations into the digital realm,
really important stuff. And if there's
one takeaway from any representatives of
other states that are looking at SETI
SETI, there's some privacy and autonomy
reasons for looking at SETI, there's
some security reasons for looking at
SETI, but I think the number one reason
why a state would look at SETI is
because of digital guardianship because
it includes everybody, all the different
dependent populations you want to
include. No government system has
figured this out. Few of them are even
talking about it. Uh, only 25% of US
16-year-olds get a driver's license.
Only 50% of 20-year-olds have driver
license, driver's licenses.
But yet, 100% of 15y olds need identity.
Said he solves a big technical
challenge, decentralized digital
guardianship. That's peer-to-peer with
no phone home and no dependence on any
vendor network or blockchain.
That's a really important thing. You
know what's easy to do technically to
prove a guardian relationship. If you
phone home to a server and the server
says, "Oh yeah, that's the parent of the
child. We're good." And you're phoning
home to the server. That's easy
technically to do. You know, it's
extremely hard. that requires the
breakthroughs enabled by Sam Smith, who
I mentioned earlier, is to be able to
verify that guardian relationship in a
decentralized manner where you're not
phoning home
offline
using Bluetooth peer-to-peer.
Major breakthrough in digital trust.
Now, you know, I gave these guys some
kudos at the beginning. Um, SETI can
mimic any form of guardianship. A
guardian can prove that the guardian a
ward can prove who their guardian is and
verifiers can follow guardian
requirements for ward authorization. So
what I mean by that is Johnny requests
to spend 35 bucks on Fortnite and his
mother is prompted for approval.
It's a simple example
of how a verifier can follow guardian
requirements for award authorization.
Guardianship however gets very tricky.
A single guardian is very simple. It's
onetoone. A single parent actually is
the simplest use case. A single parent
just they're the only one who makes the
decision, right? It gets trickier when
there's two parents. When they're
married, it's still trickier than a
single single because you can say the
parents either one of them can say
Johnny can do it. You can say both of
them have to approve before Johnny can
do it. you can say um up to a certain
dollar amount either parent can do it
but if it exceeds another dollar pound
dollar amount then both parents need to
be able to do it and that's what I call
graduated. So you can you can have
conditions in there and things like that
for that approval. Uh it gets even
trickier with divorced parents where you
have a twotoone relationship with Johnny
potentially a 3:1 relationship if the
court is involved which they might be
for some things that Johnny might want
to do. Uh and there's waiting. So you
can give more weight to more uh to the
court. You can give more weight to one
parent. You can give weight to a
grandparent. You do whatever you want.
It's called weighted m of n multi-ig.
And so you can divide that that
authority however you choose. Um and
adult ch children of a disabled parent.
So I've got a mother who's 89 and she's
starting to forget some things and she's
got a lot of living adult children. And
there's some of these adult children who
should probably not have a say in what
happens with mom. It's an opinion, but
at some point that might have to be
adjudicated. And someone might have to
say, well, when it when push comes to
sub, the kids are not agreeing. How is
that adjudicated? And and however that
is if the conclusion is that a certain
subset of children have authority and
maybe one has more than the others that
can be modeled with MAN weighted
multi-yig which is part of car part of
seti. Um how about homeless people
unable to carry credentials?
Well what are you doing there to bring
that homeless person in the digital
realm if they're unable to carry
credentials? How does it work in real
life? We try to mimic what happens in
real life and that is there's a
government agency that actually holds
some credentials or has the ability to
do something on behalf of that homeless
person. Very tricky situations.
Um, and I'm going a little bit slower
than I want, so I'm going to go a lot
faster. Delegation. A parent signs a
permission slip that authorizes another
adult child to pick up their child. Or a
manager delegates a task
or an individual delegates to an AI
agent. We talk about AI and agentic AI
that is a form of delegation. Delegation
is absolutely everywhere. A legislature
can delegate to committees and agencies
who then delegate to departments and
outside companies who delegate multiple
levels of employees who provide a
service to a citizen.
So delegation is absolutely everywhere.
All organizations private uh or public
or are hierarchies of delegation. said
he enables an individual to directly
delegate authority to another without
involving anyone else.
The individual with the authority can go
directly to the delegate and and give
them that authority. With SETI, anyone
anywhere can verify the claimed
authority without phoning home. We
talked about that earlier,
decentralization.
Saidi can mimic any form of delegation.
A delegator can prove what and to whom
they've delegated. A delegate can prove
what's delegated and from whom. And by
the way, the word delegate a little bit
awkward because in some cases a noun, in
some cases a verb. Okay, so I'm using
the form delegate here. And number two,
a delegate noun can prove what's
delegated verb and from home. Okay,
delegation can expire or be revoked. A
delegate can delegate again with proof
of authority to do so. Delegations are
non-reputable and they which means they
can't be denied later. Delegations can
form hierarchies or chains. They're
auditable, traceable. They cannot be
forged. They're resilient to key
rotation. And rules and restrictions can
be made verifiable, machine readable,
and enforceable. Sounds like a dream
list. It is. Now you know why we're
excited. A gentic future. And by the
way, I have to laugh at this picture of
grandma being helped by a robot. And no,
that wasn't made by AI. Uh, and no, I
didn't take that photo. Uh but Microsoft
CEO said this and and I'm paraphrasing
because this quote is too long but the
the paraphrase of the Microsoft CEO AI
agents will replace all software as a
service SAS
CEO of Microsoft
and the reason he says that is because
of frankly what I I think is um
illustrated by grandma. It's a user
experience. Most agentic tasks are
simple and don't require delegation, but
some important ones do and they require
some delegation, some authority on
behalf of the agent. And I think one of
the uh greatest use cases, I keep
hitting the wrong button and gets rid of
them. Um I think one of the greatest use
cases for Agentic AI is user experience
for elderly people.
I know my mom could talk to an agent and
ask her to do something. She struggles
to open her phone and start an app to
play Scrabble with her daughter in
Pennsylvania. But I know she could talk
to an agent and say, "Please open the
Scrabble game,
or please do something." I think the
future of of AI for elderly people is
really, really bright. And I want that
agent's authority to do something on
behalf of my mom carefully constrained.
SETI is ideal for delegating to agentic
AI. So in conclusion, SETI brings
guardianship and delegation into
verifiable digital form harmonizing law
and technology. Saidi includes everyone
through digital guardianship. Parents,
caregivers, and courts can securely
represent those who cannot who cannot uh
self-manage their identity. Through SETI
delegation, individuals can safely
empower others or AI agents with limited
revocable authority. said he actualizes
both human and legal rights and
principles and is designed for the
coming agentic AI era. Thank you.
Good afternoon.
Good afternoon. My name is Thomas
Mayfield. Um I am joined here today by
my colleagues Fergle Okconor on stage
and Jeremy Fster in the audience. Uh we
are here representing the Cardano
Foundation, a Swiss-based nonforprofit
and we've traveled from quite far and
wide. Jeremy has traveled from Taiwan.
Fergle has traveled from Ireland and
myself has traveled from the United
Kingdom. And we have done so because
what is happening here in the state of
Utah is a paradigm shift in digital
identity. And what we would like to
demonstrate for you today is the art of
the possible, the potential for what
some of these things we have heard of
today such as guardianship could look
like for your citizens and how the state
could leverage these technologies.
Before we start the demo, I would just
like to say a few words.
We live in a world where our trust in
government, technology, and our fellow
citizens is eroding every day. I would
testify that every person in this room
and those watching online believe the
protection of children is our most
important societal responsibility.
It is evident that the internet is a
powerful but dangerous place. A place
where we do not know unequivocally who
we are interacting with online. Is it an
adult or a child? Is it a human or a
machine? It is a genuine person or a
predator.
There are numerous statistics available
and I would like to highlight a few
given the time constraints we have
today.
In 2024, Childlight, the global child
safety institute, reported more than 300
million children fall victim to online
sexual exploitation and abuse each and
every year.
Similar to the tragic story we heard
this morning, there are more than 1300
reports made involving violent online
groups that encourage children to harm
themselves
and others.
Online games have become hunting grounds
for predators. Some of the largest being
Roblox, Minecraft, and Fortnite.
Roblox, self-reported cases of suspected
child sexual exploitation to the
National Center for Missing and
Exploited Children, increased
dramatically between 2019 and 2024
from 675
to 24,000 cases.
In the first six months of this year
alone, Roblox has reported more than it
reported all of last year.
In 2019, a study of more than 2,000
child Minecraft players found that
nearly 10% had been asked by another
player to meet in real life. That's
almost 200 children, and that was six
years ago. This number has grown
exponentially.
There have been numerous attempts to
remedy these risks to children. However,
they do not address the core problems.
How we access the internet, digital
content, and the interactions children
are exposed to. Today you will witness
for the first time in the world two
technologies key event receipt
infrastructure commonly referred to as
Kerry and authentic chained data
containers ACDC's being leveraged in a
manner that no other technology can
achieve today
providing open-source state endorsed
digital identity wallet and supporting
services designed to return control back
in the hands of parents and guardians.
empowering them to ensure a safe and
verifiable digital future for their
children and their children's children.
What we'd like to do now is walk you
through a demonstration leveraging these
technologies.
What Fergle is going to be demonstrating
on the lefth hand side is a
representation of the state of Utah
vital records platform. What he will be
doing here is issuing a birth
certificate. Now this may be a manual
process conducted by an administrator.
It could be a checkbox in an existing
system that's integrated. It could be
fully automated. But the point here is
that there are certain aspects of SETI
that must be introduced by the
government and others that fall into the
power of the parents. Fergle is forming
a peer-to-peer channel with the
government leveraging the mobile wallet
of the child Oliver. In today's
demonstration,
the parent Mary also has established a
peer-to-peer communication and she will
be requesting the government issue a
birth certificate to her child as well
as a guardianship credential. These are
all AC/DC technology.
So what has happened now is a
guardianship credential has been issued
to the parent and a birth certificate
has been issued to Oliver. What you can
see online here is the credential
contains any amount of information
including a direct link potentially to a
file system or server. It can be fully
customized based on policy and that is
the most important aspect. This is not
tech providers
dictating what the state can use. This
is technology that is built based on
policy and law.
Now that the birth certificate has been
issued and the guardianship credential
has now been issued to Mary the mother
and this could be a multi- signature
relationship for both parents for
example all capable with Carrie and
AC/DC technology. Now Mary will leverage
the family portal. This is all open-
source software you are seeing here
today.
This could be running in your home
system like a home media center or it
could be provided by a third party. The
key difference here is these are not
like the centralized systems. The keys
controlling the data reside in the SETI
wallet in the hand of the parent. They
never leave that platform. They never go
into this system you are seeing.
Everything must be signed and approved
at the edge or from the wallet. So now
Mary has logged into this system. You'll
notice there were no usernames, no
passwords. This is known as passwordless
authentication.
And now Mary is presenting her SETI
credentials to the family portal. This
will allow the portal to determine what
features should be available to her. In
there you will see a number of things
appearing in the family tree. This is
this chaining characteristic that was
just mentioned behind AC/DC credentials.
In the SETI wallet is not only a
credential dictating the guardian
relationship for Oliver, but also the
guardian relationship to Liam,
Liam's father. So this would be a power
of attorney issued by a court for
example. The idea is to demonstrate that
all of this information can be contained
within a chain of credentials that are
cryptographically built upon one another
similar to that scenario with the Lego
blocks just presented on screen. So now
the parents are empowered to issue
credentials to delegate authority to
their children completely removed from
the state. The state has provided the
credential to prove guardianship, but
now the parent has control. Now Mary
will issue a credential to Oliver. And
you'll see there are three scenarios
we've explored here. Social media,
streaming platforms, and gaming
consoles. We will demonstrate a social
media credential and the ability to
customize the attributes. What you can
see here initially is a conversational
age rating. This is the ability for the
parent to decide the age in which they
want their children to interact with.
Second, you will see a time constraint.
They can set parameters around when
these credentials can be used, when
these platforms can be accessed. And
finally, there is a content rating that
can be set by the parent. You'll see a
checkbox at the bottom that says enable
safe interactions. What this is telling
the system wherever this credential is
presented that this user can only
interact with other SEI endorsed users.
What we're going to do now is issue this
credential. But before I do so, this is
just an example. The policy will dictate
the parameters of this credential,
not the tech providers. So when that is
established exactly what will go into
this credential, what are those options?
Then that will be implemented. They are
fully flexible. What you will see now is
Mary will receive a request because
although it looks like this system is
creating and issuing the credential, it
isn't. It is merely a Lego block to
build, but Mary must sign with the keys
that are stored in her steady wallet,
her identity which is contained within
in order to execute this action. And now
what you will see is the child will
receive a prompt in their phone saying
their mother would like to issue them a
credential and they must also approve
this credential in order to hold it and
receive it. So what you see here is not
only holding and issuing but also the
ability to do decentralized verification
which is the next step.
So now that Oliver has received a social
media access credential, he can now
register for a new paradigm shift in
social media that we are calling social
book today. You'll notice again there is
no usernames and passwords. Oliver will
log in online with his delegated
authority from his mother in an AC/DC
credential into the social book
platform. Oliver will scan this QR code
you see on screen to establish a
peer-to-peer connection with social
book. He will input his email, but
you'll notice Oliver will not be telling
the system how old he is. The state
endorsed digital identity which
empowered the mother to create a
guardian to the mother to create a
social media access credential will
inform the platform cryptographically
how old Oliver is.
Oliver will now register for the
platform and will then log into the
platform using no usernames and
passwords.
Once Oliver has logged into the
platform, we will now start to explore
how those criteria and restrictions that
were set by his parent can be visualized
in a system. What we have done here is
we have tagged the data in this post um
with a metadata label indic indicating
the content level of which this image
was. And because the parent has set that
restriction to teen, he can no longer
view that image. If he wanted to view
it, he could request it. But let's move
on now to the chat to demonstrate how
chat now is leveraging that age
restriction. What you will see on screen
here is existing conversations that are
already underway. And you will notice
below there are a number of SETI tokens
that indicate that these are users that
have leveraged a SETI based credential
to access and register for the system.
And you'll see other users that have red
tags there. These fall outside of the
constraints of the age that was set by
the mother. In a scenario where Oliver
would like to talk to Justin, he must
receive approval from his parents. In
this scenario, Mary in order to do so.
This is creating a shield online that
parents can control for their children
cryptographically.
What we will now do is we will move on
to another example of how social media
can be leveraged.
We've had a couple of conversations with
um social media platforms um as well as
uh game development houses um and we
we're trying to establish uh proof of
concept leveraging decentralized
identity
and the very common feedback we received
was decentralized identity is too
complex to integrate into gaming. Games
must have centralized servers. The
identity systems must be centralized in
the platform to ensure the game and user
experience is maintained. So although
the concept and the idea behind a
centralized identity is powerful and
they understood the value it could
bring, their statement was you simply
cannot integrate this comprehensive
technology.
So I set this task upon my team to do
exactly that. So what we have done is we
have cloned roadblocks. We are calling
it carry blocks.
We did this in less than two weeks just
to give you an understanding of the time
frame here. We are not game developers
by any means. And what you will see is
Oliver is now going to register and log
into this platform in the exact same way
le leveraging a credential that was
issued to him by his mother in order to
play this game online. And all of those
constraints and restrictions that are
embedded inside the credential will also
pertain to his usage of this game
platform. So Oliver will join the system
and we he will begin gameplay. And there
are a number of elements here I would
like to touch upon.
The level of predatory engagement that
is happening in in-game chat is a
significant concern.
What you have now demonstrated today on
screen is the ability to have age
verification built into a game. This is
a complete carry and AC/DCbased chat
integration into Kerry blocks. All of
these communications are digitally
signed and the age of the individuals
that can communicate with Oliver must
fall within those constraints that were
set in the credential.
Another huge element to in-game
um concerns is purchases.
Many times parents will input their
credit card information
to purchase something that time and what
has happened is children have racked up
credit card bills because that
information is in the game. The children
can click on things and purchase them
and mom and dad only find out once the
bill arrives. In the exact same way that
Oliver had to request permission to
speak to someone who was outside of the
age constraints, mom and dad also have
to approve the purchase.
Again, this is a completely new paradigm
shift in in-game purchases and parental
controls for individuals leveraging
online systems. The next one to two
minutes of what you're about to see is
the potential future for the users that
are leveraging Roblox. There are 20 to
40 million users a day leveraging this
system.
There is a huge opportunity here from a
commercial perspective, but there is a
huge risk that can be solved with this
technology.
Go ahead.
Let's see if the sound works.
Okay. Sound's not working, but that's
okay.
Go ahead. Do it one more time.
Okay.
Secure, portable, and self sovereign.
Using this identity, you can create your
own rules and trusted circles with
cryptographic proof. Set age limits for
your private space, define your play
hours, or grant access only to friends
you have personally approved. In Cary
Blocks, you don't just build worlds. You
build the rules that govern them,
creating a provably safe and
personalized gaming experience.
Developed by Vidian and integrated with
notblocks.online
project, Kerryblocks redefineses how we
play in a connected world.
So I leave you here with a thought to
the parents and the guardians in the
audience and viewing online today.
If you could choose
from this safe, secure, friendly gaming
experience for your children
or you can take a gamble and leverage
the systems that are available today.
What choice would you make?
Thank you very much for your time.
Hello. Hello. Hello. My name is Michael
Proper and I work with an organization
called the digital world which has been
involved with Kerry which you may have
heard lots of acronyms for a long time
for about six years and we've actually
been implementing real world deployments
of this technology and in an operating
environment that uh majority of you
might already be familiar with. Um we
already understand decentralization
right?
How is it actually governed? What parts
of the world is it governed within?
That's the core of what we actually
looked for long ago when we actually
were based here in Utah and went around
and tried to find environments where
what's the jurisdictions, what's the
policies, what's the technologies, how
do we actually use it, how does it work
and trying to put these answers
together. And what we found was there's
a lot of different environments that
actually willing to adopt it. a lot of
countries, especially sovereign ones
that are used to governing themselves,
and we found a lot of acceptance within
the Pacific. We went to 28 different
countries, and out of the 28 different
countries, a lot of small countries are
very, very adapt to do it, but they're
usually outside of the United States.
Tbalu, Vanuatu, Fiji, Samoa, Raritanga,
Altereroa, these are places that being
decentralized is actually second nature.
they they're self- sovereign and
independent of it. When we look at it,
we we look at the decentralization
around carry and how we can actually use
it as humans in a very simple way. How
we actually take something and start our
own identities as individuals usually
with keys. These are good example of
keys. And then it links with us
individually in a private way that then
has derived keys that basically then
manage our world, our life, our identity
from usernames and passwords to
applications to credentials to wallets
to health and many other things. So
we've worked a lot about building the
implementation of carry into real world
environments and actually helping to
bring the next step of what we look at
as centralized systems namely like with
real ID or other environments to where
the individual has the opportunity to
actually own their own identity and
their own data. the opposite of what's
happened. For instance, if you're
familiar with HIPPA, Health Information
Portability and Privacy Act, it was
supposed to be implemented like this
where your different records actually go
to you as the individual, but it was
actually done the opposite way.
So, we've seen technology get
implemented the opposite way. And it
just so happens that same technology,
HIPPA, came from a gentleman right here
in Utah named Richard Dick. Wonderful
gentleman. Uh, make a long story short,
Carrie switches this onto its head. So
the individual actually has the ability
to own their own identity and SETI is a
standard that can actually do that for
humanity in a very important way. What
I'm going to do is show you not only on
a clear phone which we actually built
clear phones that are based around the
individual. So they actually are carry
based devices. Right out of the gate you
get your 12 words but it's not just
about a particular device. You can do
this with Apple. You can do this with
Android in real time. Uh I'm going to
talk a little bit about what's called
Utah Life. It's an experience where not
only does a guardianship for a child or
a grandparent, for instance, if a
grandparent basically is compromised,
how can they actually So, it's a 10
billion dollar industry where a
grandparent can have a grandchild call
them and say, "Hey, I made a mistake and
I've run into somebody and I need some
money." And then an attorney gets on and
says, "We're actually going to need you
to send us over here." It's a10 billion
dollar industry a year in fraud, which
is in addition to what we saw earlier,
which that happened 10 years ago. It's
like what's happened since this uh
Cindy's son had actually tooken her
life. These are some of the things that
actually can can do it in real time. And
so when a grandparent actually imagine a
future where a grandparent doesn't need
to use username and passwords. They just
grab their phone, push on an apps, log
in, and they can actually see all of
their assets, all of their ability to
pay things, all of the things that they
own, all the contacts, and it's actually
managed by someone that's given
guardianship rights from an organization
like a state to be able to help manage
that grandparent. Maybe it's accounts.
Maybe it's paying bills. Maybe it's
paying different vendors. Maybe it's
different assets and how to pass them
from one generation to another. Maybe
it's currencies. Maybe it's the ability
to actually manage contacts, not just
for your child, but also for
grandparents. There's a lot of confusion
when people get into that environment.
And then the ability to actually take
these types of things and actually drop
from one environment to another to
actually make it easy for them to pay.
So if you wanted to pay a utility bill
or you wanted to pay a grandchild, it's
all integrated and simple. So that's a
good example of a grandparent type
guardianship reality with a simple app
that you can pull down, log in today,
and actually start using these types of
things. It also works with children. So
the ability for children to be able to
be managed from what apps are they using
to what sites are they going to, uh
there's a lot of functionality and
opportunities there. So, I just want to
say thank you for those specifically Sam
Smith, Phil Windley. These are people
that have dedicated their lives to
solving this problem. Tim, I mean, this
is this is real. This is and this is a
nucleus here in Utah that we can
actually make a real difference, but
ultimately it's actually all of you that
have said, "This is a problem that I
want to learn about and a problem that I
want to be able to be a part of the
solution in the future." So, thank you
for coming and thank you for actually
understanding what's happening here in
Utah. But it's really the world. It's a
problem that society has a
responsibility in our generation. Like
when all of us were born, we didn't have
the cell phones. We didn't have the
internet. And when we pass on, we've got
to pass on a better legacy than what's
currently there. So, thank you for Chris
and all the hard work that he does to
put this together and those at the state
that truly are aligning with this effort
because I know it's not easy to put
these parts and pieces together. When we
went and searched the world, we could
not find a body like this. We went to
the government in DC. We went here. We
went it. It's just amazing to see the
heart, the alignment to support someone
like Cindy
who 10 years ago lost a son that's real
in this university. That young man went
to this university 10 years ago
and here we are. So, thank you for being
here and understanding some of these
concepts.
Thank you.
All right. My name is Steve Macau and I
am a commissioner on the Utah Privacy
Commission. I'm also chief architect of
Anonyomy Labs and um I'd like to talk to
you about surveillance and tracking
today and what SETI do does to uh get in
the way of that.
Um years ago I worked for the US
Department of Energy as basically a
computer hacker and one of my
assignments was to work on compromising
cell phones. Um, another part of my
assignment was what they call
open-source intelligence.
And this is the collection and an
analysis of data gathered from open
sources, think internet, and in order to
produce actionable intelligence. And in
that capacity, I was able to uh be given
target sites and um pull together enough
information from the internet that
resulted in classified reports.
So the first I wanted to look and see
when the first open-source intelligence
was uh taking place and this is January
of 1862.
A publication called Harper's Weekly was
uh publishing articles um about force
movements during the US Civil War. And
as you can see here,
um the the text talks about um a
general's expeditions and where the
troops were going, what assets he had,
and um while the specific targets were
secret, they also were able to surmise
where they were going. They went so far
as to draw pictures of the target
locations and and the forces um
attacking the other forces.
in modern times. Let's talk about
surveillance for modern times. So, how
do email marketers know when to call
you? So, sometimes, and this happened to
me personally, I was reading an email
and within five minutes of reading the
email, I received a call from the sender
of the email and I engaged them in
conversation to find out how they were
doing this. Um,
here's an example, one of many examples
of what we call tracking beacons. So,
what they'll do, an email is simply like
a web page. It's an HTMLbased
uh, email these days. And they'll put a
one by one pixel transparent image on
there. And for those of you who know
HTML,
um, there's a little tag called image
that's supposed to load an actual image.
And instead of loading an image, what it
does is it contacts the internet and
pings a web service. And that web
service can do a variety of things. And
you can add a variety of information.
Username, email address, GPS location,
whatever you can get your handle,
whatever you can get a hold of and your
email client allows, you can then send
that off.
So that's a modern um example of open-
source intelligence. And this leads us
into what we call surveillance
capitalism, which is a concept in
political economics, which denotes the
widespread collection and
commodification of personal data by
corporations. It's not limited to
corporations. Governments can do this
too. And there can be collaboration
between the two. Couple of interesting
points about surveillance capitalism is
that it operates without meaningful
mechanisms of consent. It just happens
to you.
Uh and you can lose your
self-determination through the
manipulation of um advertising and other
practices that might happen as a result
of this. Duke University with West Point
University with the with the um with the
army. They did a study back in uh 2023
about data brokers and the sale of data
on US military personnel. So data
brokers using these kinds of methods
were able to collect sufficient
information that it became of interest
to uh foreign entities. And so as part
of the study, they were able to approach
the data brokers originating from either
US domains or Asia domains
and purchase information on US service
members and veterans. And when they
ordered in bulk, it was about 12 to 32
cents per record that you could uh get
on US uh military members. Think of all
the things we do on social media and how
that might be used as we heard this
morning for blackmail in order to invoke
espionage.
Um this is a real problem yet it's also
the way the web kind of operates uh
these days. Uh their recommendations
were uh federal privacy legislation and
also to restrict the collection of data
on current and former military
personnel.
So how SETI helps protect our identity.
So one of the things if you uh look back
to SB260
it says in and a couple of lines in here
uh the state endorsed digital identity
enables an individual to selectively
disclose indivi elements of an
individual's identity. So, taking the
driver's license as an example, when you
go to a government entity, say the
Department of Motor Vehicles, you don't
really have an expectation of privacy.
You're going there to give your
information in order to get a driver's
license credential. So, we don't really
have an expectation of privacy in that
regard just by the nature of that
interaction. However, when we go to the
bank, you don't need to give your height
and your weight and your donor status
and all that kind of stuff. And so that
you can selectively disclose what the
bank requires.
Then if you go shopping on Amazon or
somewhere, other than payment
information, they need your name and
they need your address to ship whatever
it is you're buying. They don't need
your driver's license number. And so um
over the summer, Apple has allowed MDLs
to be used for website loginins. And
that's may create some very side effects
about the transfer of information.
Another aspect of SB260 is asserting
with zero correlation. So part of the
one of the lines in that bill says uh
verify that the individual's age
satisfies an age requirement without
revealing the individual's age or date
of birth. So, for example,
if I were to go to the Department of
Alcoholic Beverage Services, which is
where you buy liquor here in Utah, the
the assertion you need to make is I'm 21
or older. That's what's required in the
law. You don't have to get your give
your name, your address, or any other
information. There should be a way to
give only the information that is
required, and that's what SEI's after.
So, when I go to a concert at the Delta
Center and I want to use that neat fancy
um uh digital ticket, I need to be able
to assert that I purchased a ticket,
that I'm authorized to get in having
paid my my money and so forth without
having to give all the other information
that may sometimes come with digital
credentials. I want this to be a process
of least disclosure, not full
disclosure.
Now, when I go to uh uh the hardware
store as a veteran myself, I'm offered a
10% discount. And I get that by scanning
everything on my driver's license. That
includes obviously that I am a veteran,
which is on my status. It includes
whether I'm a donor, my height, my
weight, my address, all these things
that are unnecessary for that
transaction.
So said it gives you a choice.
Um here's a quote from the US Supreme
Court from back in 1995.
It says anonymity is a shield from the
tyranny of the majority. It thus
exemplifies the purpose behind the bill
of rights in the first amendment in
particular to protect unpopular
individuals from retaliation at the hand
of an intolerant society. Now whether
you're on the left or the right, this
should resonate with you maybe for
different reasons, but this is a is a
really important principle because if we
don't enable you to disclose only the
information that's required in an
untrackable sense in some situations,
what we will end up with is what Scott
McNeely from Sun Microsystems said back
in 1999.
You have zero privacy anyway. Get over
it. And so SETI is giving you the choice
of what you disclose and when you
disclose it and they put that choice in
the hands of the holder.
So that's what I would hope that you
would take away with and you would go
back to your respective companies,
departments and states and pose this to
um your constituents because we want a
private um identity system that keeps
individuals safe. So thank you very
much.
Hi Chris. Am I coming through?
Yeah, absolutely. Great stuff.
Excellent.
Thank you. Okay. Good afternoon all. Uh
apologies for being your remote speaker
of the day. Uh unfortunately I couldn't
uh get across from the UK to to join for
this. Um but I'd like to spend the next
10 minutes uh looking at something
slightly different uh in terms of the
the presentations that have happened so
far. Um we've heard an awful lot today
um about what what said he can um
protect from the fraud, making sure
everything is assured, making sure we
have the assertions, making sure um
child age verification and adult age
verification can be put in place. I'd
like to spend a few minutes looking at
the flip side of that and looking at
economic benefit as a result of a state
endorsed digital identity and what can
be achieved there. Uh and and bring
forwards a proof point to show that this
has happened and the sort of values that
can be expected from that. Uh so Simon
Wood um I've been involved in identity
systems for a long time now most
recently uh group of Ubiscure. Ubiscure
is a UK company but deploys a lot in the
Nordics. uh obscure has deployed a
number of platforms uh in Finland and
Sweden and the uh the case studies taken
from there. One of the things I'd just
like to touch on before getting into
that is a differentiator that McKenzie
makes on digital identity versus
advanced identity. Everything that has
been spoken about today I would say
falls in that advanced identity category
as defined by McKenzie. Um uh in the UK
we're obviously reeling at the moment
from the uh brick card announcements and
so on. uh and the McKenzie report is is
often rolled out as one of the values
for having uh an identity. It's referred
to as digital identity in in in the
general sense. Um but if you read that
report in detail, you'll see that to
benefit from the advanced capabilities
and the uh returns and the GDP increases
that are positioned there specifically
for the US and for the UK, it needs to
be advanced identity which brings in
additional attributes, additional
information and additional features as
well. You've already seen a number of
demonstrations of those today in a SETI
context and that's what we're looking at
here. We're looking at those advanced
capabilities beyond just authentication
and authorization which is uh McKenzie's
classical definition of digital
identity. I want to run you through uh a
very quick scenario. You've seen a
couple of diagrams like this already
today uh where we have a uh a chain of
of delegation. Um Vict Dish's example
here uh we'll look at setting up a new
company uh in in Utah. So the uh the CEO
of that company to be uh contacts Utah
division of corporations um goes online
and uses their steady identity to
register that company. uh the USR
division of corporations automatically
passes that across to the state tax
commission because there will be taxes
to pay and collect from that
organization and the uh tax commission
will send uh a request back to the CEO
using let let's assume that there's a
secure mailbox capability from a SEI
implementation so you can securely
contact uh people who have that identity
and request that tax registration the
CEO will obviously go to that website
register uh to submit the taxes
uh but then the CEO themselves will not
be uh undertaking that work. They will
delegate that capability to the CFO of
the organization. So that delegation
will be done through the website. The
CEO will invite the CFO to that system
uh using their uh city identity as well.
And so a delegation chain is built.
You've seen examples of this of such a
delegation chain already in a couple of
the demos that have been uh delivered
today. But if we consider that uh tax is
reasonably complex, you might have three
different types. So sales tax, uh
corporation tax, employment tax, uh
maybe the employment tax is outsourced
to an organization. So that organization
can be invited in and delegated to the
administrator in that organization can
pick that up and then onwards delegate
to an internal accountant. So we've got
a chain of delegations running through
individuals and organizations using uh
an identity that's that's highly assured
and available to them. This delegation
chain builds and allows all of the tax
to take place and not once has the uh a
tax commission being involved in that
they've just provided that service to
allow it to happen. Now this seems like
a great scenario. If that were true,
what would deliver us? Well, that does
speak this that happens already in
Finland. Uh there is a platform uh
delivered in 2008,
right?
I believe so.
Are they not coming through?
That will help. And it
how's that?
So just to just to reiterate that that
previous slide so you can see what was
there. Uh it's it's a it's a delegation
chain across individuals and through an
organization there towards the bottom as
we have uh around here. Uh, Chris, I
assume that's coming through now.
Is that okay?
I think that's okay. Uh, so this this
platform was delivered or it is
delivered in Finland. It's called the
Catso platform uh delivered in 2008. Uh
it's it is a state operated platform as
opposed to stated endorsed. Back in 2008
there was not this distinction and this
understanding of privacy and how
important that that is as we acknowledge
today. Um state operated platform
integrates with the business registry um
uh to generate that link to the tax
office. Uh in 2018 the Finnish
government published stats on the
savings as a result of uh having that
platform. uh and when they published
that at that time there were 450,000 uh
users registered on there 420,000
organizations and 104 different online
government services using that platform.
One of those services was the tax office
and it worked exactly as I just
described uh in that delegation chain
that's there. Um, in terms of the stats
that were collected on that, uh, a
significant reduction in physical
service points because everything was
online and everything was driven by the
organization that was registering. Uh,
they could massively reduce the the
physical points of presence. That
allowed them to make a 20% year-on-year
tax admin staff reduction, repurpose
them to more profitable areas, and the
cost of servicing the tax transactions
uh when they went from the old um
physical base to an online basis dropped
from €35 per tax transaction to €30. Um
that's a 99% reduction in cost per
transaction measured by the Finnish
government. That's the value that they
achieved uh deploying a an highly
assured identity that has delegation
capabilities that has the ability to
work uh across individuals and
organizations
within that. You've heard me talking
about organizations. Organizations are
an important part of the identity chain.
Incorporating an organization identity
enables the the really advanced identity
use cases and that's where we see a lot
of the economic benefit coming from. Now
it would be wrong to assume that
organizations are just legal entities.
Uh we get a lot of utility and benefit
from lower assurance levels of
organizations. Uh just like individual
identities, there can be low assurance
and high assurance and we see economic
savings at higher assurance levels.
You've heard multiple times today that
SB260 already considers organization
identity in the form of uh family units
and and family structures. That is an
organization. uh there's no reason not
to have the ability ultimately to extend
that to bring in private sector legal
entities as well to take advantage of
that massive uplift in utility and
economic potential that comes from
there.
So
to conclude uh from there uh we've seen
already that um SEI uh has phenomenal p
uh potential for protection for
implementing privacy um and for making
sure that um uh state citizens uh the
public get the protection and the uh the
facilities that they need. But once
that's up and running uh then extending
that to organization identity will bring
significant uh benefit as well. We've
heard again a number of times that uh we
shouldn't let private sector define this
and and I I fully agree it needs to be
run at the the policy level generating
the privacy that's needed ensuring
that's first and then bringing utility
and benefit u to public sector
organizations afterwards. Um but
incorporating those public sector
organizations and allowing them to
leverage that information and be
involved in there and integrate their
platforms and their systems to that will
bring significant benefit and what has
already happened in the Nordics and in
the Baltics gives very strong proof
points to show what can be done and the
level of savings and level of return
that can be achieved there. I've run
through this very quickly. Um I realize
this is remote and a little bit more
more complicated. Um but uh the I
believe the the slides and this
recording will be out later. So, uh, you
can always, uh, contact me afterwards or
Chris can put you in contact and, uh,
provide more information if that's
useful. Thank you very much.
Is that good now? All right. Does
everybody know what digital identity is?
Yeah. Is there anybody in here who I
just say, "What is digital identity?"
And you're like, "I have no idea." That
must have been a really long day.
All right. Um,
oh, am I Oh,
it it was today. I was obviously here
all day.
Actually, it looked like I missed some
meetings today. So, um, I assure you I
work really hard. I really do. All
right, this is actually I think going to
be the most exciting part of the day.
This is the final discussion. Um I am
going to ask and we didn't plan on some
chairs. Um could we get a couple chairs
just uh for some of this? We're actually
going to discuss how are we going to
move forward. We have enough brain power
in this room. We have enough
policymaking authority. We have the
ability to create legislation. Uh we had
uh Senator Cullymore here earlier, our
Senate majority leader. I've already
heard there's going to be discussions
happening with some other states Senate
Majority Leaders. We have counterparts
in states. We have companies we work
with. So now the discussion for this
last hour before we leave is how do we
move forward? You never want to have a
summit like this without some outcome
and some deliverables. We have a lot of
momentum built and in order to keep this
going, you don't stop. That's what
usually slows government down is then
you go back and you review. So the
question is how do we keep the momentum
going? Um I think three three will be
good. So we're gonna ask Representative
Cutler to come up and then is Alan
Fuller in here? Allan if you'll come up.
So this is we're going to have uh we'll
just have one mic for us to share but
then the rest of the mics we'll have
some interns around and we want to
discuss um what are we doing next? what
are our next action items from our side?
But then how do we engage with states to
to go ahead and and get this consortium
going? And then I see the clock here
says 14 minutes, but I think we're just
at at the end, right? So we have until
four timers,
right?
Okay.
So let's actually uh do we have a mic
here or is it over here?
Yeah, there's
check.
Um, I think it'd be beneficial if we
explain some of what our our next steps
are actually going to be. Allan, do you
want to take the first?
Let me let me just get started by saying
that Senate Bill 260 gave the Department
of Government Operations of which um
Chris and I and Marvin Dodge was here
are a part or all are all part of and it
uh tasks us with uh coming back to the
legislature with a specific proposal and
the input we received here and the input
we've received through a request for
information that we put out. Many of you
responded to that RFI. Thank you for
that. We over the next couple of months
are going to be putting together a
proposal to go back to the legislature
uh for our for our SETI program going
forward. And you know, we live in the
real world. We have to if we're going to
create a system uh that's going to have
provide identity for millions of people
in the state, it has to be something
that works really well, is performant,
is secure, is private. And so all of the
principles we've talked about today need
to eventually come together in a a real
life system that actually works. Maybe I
can turn over to you represent color.
Sure.
One one of the thoughts that I have is
if is
in order to we can I mentioned this
before we can pass the policy but we
need our industry partners and we need a
large enough coalition that that we have
a critical mass. So, what you can do to
help is encourage our industry partners
that you by telling them, look, I'm
interested in this or let's work
together to get something done. Uh, in
communicating that you're interested in
being part of a critical mass to move
this forward, even if even if we don't
necessarily agree on all the finer
points, I think is really important. and
the uh I thought the gentleman um Steve
from the the blockchain co-inventor
that that that was real wisdom that
working together even if it's not
perfect we can make a tremendous impact.
So, but we can't do this without our
industry partners pushing very very hard
and getting products that we can put in
an alpha phase or a beta uh phase and
and start testing and finding the flaws
and finding the successes.
Two um practical things that I think we
can expand um here in Utah for the last
couple months we've actually held a
private sector stakeholder group. Every
Friday we meet, whether we're exhausted
or not, to engage with the private
sector. I do think we should expand that
to invite all private sector in other
states. If you are are ready to
participate and you want to engage, you
want to help be part of building the
solution, we can expand that and get
that set up so you can come and
coordinate. And this doesn't have to
just be a Utah stakeholder group. This
is part of the SETI consortium. How do
we make sure everybody's engaged and
participating? Um, we want a diverse set
of ideas, you know, so long as you love
constitutional rights and
but uh but but I think you know it we
all have a role to play here and for the
private market there's always going to
be money to play. You can bring real
value added services. We don't want
government to be doing beyond the bare
minimum of providing a foundation to
protect individuals. So this is amazing
for you. this is going to be really
disruptive in a good way to move that
money from incumbent players to to
others that can help create a more
competitive marketplace. So, that's one
thing we'll do right away. We'll open
that up. Um, I'll start on the
communication for that and and get
invites out set next week. I think we
had the National Chamber of Commerce
Foundation here today as well. So, I'm
assuming you might be able to help us
with that as well. How do we get this
out to all the the businesses that are
part of that? The other thing is now
that we're through the summit, we need
to go back and start defining some of
those baseline requirements. What is
what are the requirements we're going to
compare technology to and everybody
should play a part in that. Obviously,
the RFI is closed. We have uh was a,000
or 1300 pages to read. We have 1,200
pages to read and um I know we don't
have all the info we need. So, we're
going to need everyone to participate to
say what additional requirements are we
missing. And then comes the hard work of
the technology needs to prove itself.
How do you meet the requirements? And
then also I think to what you said ear
earlier the hierarchy of values that's
going to be the hardest part. I know a
lot of people in this room are concerned
that we are going to compromise on the
wrong things in the name of
interoperability interoperability and
efficiency. So as we define the
requirements we're going to have to
create this hierarchy of values which I
have seen nowhere. I think that slide
was the first time I've seen that
presented in that way to to have
technology value at the highest level of
that constitutional rights. So that's
going to be a hard part in the
requirements building list. But that's
the type of stuff that's going to build
trust with the public when they see what
we are prioritizing. And I think it's
going to be great. I think it's actually
going to be great for government. Trust
is at an all-time low. So this is a
really good way to be very transparent
um to an extreme and let them know that
we really want to protect them.
One of the things I think that we should
talk a lot about is uh something that
Ryan brought up earlier in his
presentation about the kind of practical
side of of rolling something like this
out and and gaining adoption. We need to
uh find a launch uh customer that not
maybe customer is not the right word,
but a launch tenant that can help us uh
that that will pick this up and run with
it. maybe in Utah like a Zans's bank or
a uh something like that that will help
launch the whole process and and also uh
create the system in such a way that it
incentivizes use uh rather than
disincentivizing use in order to get
adoption. One of the big problems that
we have with our current MDL program in
Utah is that by charging the verifiers
for the verification software, it's a
disincentive for them to verify and that
makes it so you got a you got an MDL
that that people can walk around with on
their phone, but there's not very many
places it can be used. So then you have
uh not very much adoption. And we want
to set this up systematically so that it
will have adoption and incentives to to
use from the beginning.
Kristen Allen, if if if people have
ideas for use cases, where do they go?
And and I think I'm thinking back to our
experience with verifiable digital
credentials. We didn't start with the
most critical key. We started with
something easy that that no one was um
it wasn't controversial. So I I think
maybe there's some lessons learned here
that how do we start this and get some
use cases where we can learn from before
scaling it and and what's what what are
your thoughts on that process?
Well, I was thinking they should call
their legislator. Yeah. We could
that is absolutely terrible idea.
Go
ahead. Um,
all the RFI responses are protected, but
I think I can se semiquote what was in
them. Uh, one of the best ones that I
read was, uh, it was actually from an
entity that's not looking to compete.
They were just giving advice of how they
could best serve their customers with
this. And they said, and this is
actually a saying, I was in health uh,
human services for seven years before
this role. Um, they said in that RFI
response, help us meet the clients where
they are, meet people where the use
cases are. Um, and so they said, you
know, TSA probably was not the best
example. That's not something that, you
know, everybody is going to need, but
there's lots of people who have their
kids going to school every year. They
need to uh to enroll and need to have a
birth certificate or immunization
records. There are use cases where we
don't have to try to replicate what's
already being done with MDL and is
working and they're getting traction on
that side. what are other use cases that
we can tackle to tackle other more
complex issues that that um are a
different subset of individuals, but
it's meeting people where they are and
they're going to use it. And
government's great. I love the saying,
government can actually do almost
whatever it wants because it's the only
entity that can have a legal monopoly.
So, the only thing stopping us from
getting the credentials out to where
they're needed in a secure way and
getting these use cases is I think
that's the legislature.
Speaking of the legislature,
you need money.
Yeah, if we need money, we know who to
talk to. Um, you know, this is not just
about us talking. We really want to uh
this is audience participation. I really
wanted to maybe start by asking the
audience some questions, especially can
I start with the the legislators in the
room. What uh what do you feel like
you've seen today or what uh questions
do you have uh coming out of the
conversations today? Would anybody like
to please
and and introduce yourself too.
Okay. Knowledge is power and you know
getting more of us in the room or you
know legislative trainings etc. Because
it's hard to vote for something if
you're insecure uh or ignorant of an
issue. you're less apt to vote for
something or or even make any kind of
progress if you are unsure of what
you're voting for, which is a good
thing. You don't want your legislators
voting on things that they're they don't
know about. So, I think, you know,
increase, you know, I I see a handful of
us here today. Maybe it's because, you
know, my colleagues just know all the
things. Um, but I've certainly learned a
lot today. Appreciate especially those
uh presenters who really broke it down
into simplistic terms for me. And you
know, I'm a lot more comfort. I was I
was never against not completely against
it, but um I definitely feel more
comfortable after things I've learned
today. So I would just say uh especially
with our lawmakers,
we need them. We need us in a room so
that everyone can understand and then
make the decision based on that. And I
think that you know the more people
learn, the more comfortable they'll be
with the direction that we're heading.
Thank you.
Anyone
else questions out there
or Yeah, let's open up to everyone other
thoughts and
thank you.
Um, were were you the one that was that
works with Anatomy Labs? Is it who was
not Anonym Labs? Oh, he's over there.
Steve Macau.
Um, so I use I use my pseudo and that's
Yep. Excellent. Um, I was curious. So
you're asking how we can implement this
technology into that. I mean, is this
something that's being implemented into
my pseudo?
We do a wide variety of credentials and
so uh we implement and support a wide
variety of c credentials and soi is
definitely on our road map.
What?
Okay. Well, that's awesome. Um, and I
just think that this is excellent
technology. Um, my limited understanding
so far, but I think from some of the
policies that we've seen get passed, uh,
the app store identification, I'm
forgetting SP, whichever one that was,
um, and just a variety of bills that
Utah has passed has been, you know, for
the children is kind of like the pol the
the messaging push behind it, but it's
devastating to internet privacy and
anonymity. Like, we've talked about some
of these here in my opinion. And I think
that SETI is one of the um technologies
that can bridge that gap and that can
really help us in my understanding right
now. It seems like this is some vital
technology. So I just I'm championing
you know everyone here working on this.
It's great. So thank you. Question over
here.
So maybe not so much a question is just
you know you talked about what use cases
and and things that you can do to to to
make it move forward. So Eric
Jorgensson, I'm the motor vehicle
director out of Arizona. uh fantastic
conversation and discussion this week.
Thank you very much for or today for for
putting it on. Uh I I think a couple
things that I would just want to say
that I I I think would be key was one is
um you know we already have a great uh
head start on this with MDL. Right? So I
somebody early on said hey let's not
worry about the technology aspect of it.
This is really about the the
underpinning policies. And I will tell
you, I've been involved with MDL for the
past uh 10 10 years almost. Um over 10
years now. Um and um I haven't heard a
single thing today that like butts heads
with that technology. And the good news
is when we talk about adoption, 60% of
the US population is covered by a state
that issues a MDL today. So we already
have it. And in Arizona, by the way, we
have over 1 million 1.2 two million MDLs
issued.
Uh we have a population of 56
million driver's licenses out there. Um
biggest use case is not TSA,
it's the motor vehicle division, it's
state services. We use it now. We used
it in a preart 7 ISO compliant way to do
it, but we had it out there. We we
consume our own MDL And that became one
of the biggest use cases. H massive
driver for adoption for us. So something
to think about and something that is in
in your control as you look at it is why
not use it yourselves. That's that's uh
a place where you can control both sides
of the equation and make sure not only
is the provisioning done in a privacy
preserving secure way but the
consumption too and set kind of that
example for everybody else on how to
consume it too. So just a thought.
That's terrific. And also let's
acknowledge Chris Carris. Chris, if you
could raise your hand. He's our the
director of our um our driver's license
division here in the state of Utah and
has done a terrific job leading our MDL
program. We're grateful for him. And I
think Jimmy Higgs is here as well
somewhere. I don't see him at the
moment. Uh who will be the um the next
driver's license division lead after
after Chris retires. Um we are um I I I
believe that
pro my expectation and hope and and uh
this was mentioned to me today too from
someone else that likely the states who
are already doing MDL will be the first
adopters of moving to more broad study
because they kind of get it and have
already invested in creating a
credential like that. Let's see. I think
I saw a hand up here. I think it was was
it Sarah or
question?
Okay. Well, go here and then back. Oh,
yeah. Ameilia, please.
Yeah. Um, I know that I've obviously
been working on this with you guys for
years.
Introduce yourself, Ameilia.
My name is Ameilia Powers Gardner. I'm a
county commissioner in Utah County, and
I've been working on decentralized ID
and self- sovereign identity since 2019,
um, pre-COVID. Um, and you know, as I
look for as a county commissioner in the
fastest growing county in the state,
we're 43.6% of the state's growth. um as
I'm starting to look at capital projects
and building brick and mortar to the
tune of tens of millions of dollars
because of for a growing population. The
sooner we can get these services in, you
know, instituted in a way that we can
start utilizing them to deliver services
to our citizens in a secure private way
that prevents me from having to spend
millions of dollars. And so my question
comes in like I know we've got the
groundwork but I mean you know me I'm
like rock I I want to run first. I want
to run first and then I want to walk and
then I want to crawl. And we do need
backwards compatibility. But when are we
going to have the ability for an
organization like mine that has already
done some of this work? Like when are
you going to give us the ability to
start adopting this on a broad scale?
like when do I start getting the schema
and the requirements so that I can start
implementing this for my citizens so
that I can deliver services to my
citizens without having to spend tens of
millions of dollars building
brick-andmortar buildings.
Was that chastising us, Amelia?
I'm not joking. Now we
Yeah.
Yeah. So, uh, there's a lot actually
going on in Utah. For those that are
from other states, and just, you know,
we work with Amelia all the time, so
we've had this discussion. Um, for every
state, you actually have a unique
opportunity right now. Every state
nationwide is pretty much non-compliant
with their records management and data
governance laws. And and Amelia shaking
her head, but this this is the
opportunity. So when I say that, what I
mean is you all have antiquated laws
from the 70s and 80s that require
certain things like disposal of data
according to retention schedules. Most
systems have not been uh created to
dispose of data. Most states haven't
established the purpose and use of data.
Most states haven't been giving notice
uh privacy notices. And that sounds
really bad, but the great thing about it
means there needs to be a modernization
anyway over the next decade. And so
you're in the ne unique spot of because
you know there's non-compliance. Um and
I'll actually I'll share out after one
of my team uh can take a note. We we had
interns over the summer actually uh uh
research all 50 states laws to determine
where they are uh legislation wise. So
you can see where is your state with
privacy with records management with
data governance. You'll know you're
non-compliant. But now that you know
what's coming with digital identity, you
know you need data governance. And now
what Ameilia mentioned is the schemas.
this concept of what are the the rules,
what's the schema, what's the formats of
the data that needs to be collected.
When when Emil is asking what's the
schema, it's hey, when somebody uh
applies for a building permit, what is
the exact data the county should be
collecting? What needs to be on the form
so they can automatically ingest it,
automate that process with AI or machine
learning and then move toward the
efficiency that government can get. So
what I'm saying is now is actually the
first perfect time to learn where you
are. You and it takes about a decade to
transform. Utah's about 3 years in on
this journey and that's why we've been
modernizing our laws. We've been getting
comprehensive privacy law but the
schemas will come sooner. We actually
have on our team we're doing
modernization of then the data
governance structures the rules around
the data how long can you keep it what's
the legal basis what's the purpose
purposes and uses we're starting to
define what are the immutable records
which records are immutable public
permanent records which make sense to go
on a blockchain these are the things you
need in a schema to then implement
technology correctly if you jump right
to the technology without having these
things you end up having to backtrack so
I don't know if that's the answer but
it's it's coming soon and the schema as
I think will be very soon. We have some
almost almost ready.
Maybe Sarah
um I just want to echo thanks again for
having this event. It has been really
really powerful learning a ton and
getting to make sort of leaps and bounds
forward. So thank you. I think there's
an an opportunity to create a more sort
of like formal digital space um where
those things that you were just talking
about Chris if you could post them
playbooks I think this opportunity of
how can we learn from you also share
what we are doing in Colorado and other
states so that we can um learn together.
I was reflecting on the statement about
um MDL and opportunities around MDL. We
recently discovered that the standard
MDL contract with the big tech wallet
companies Apple, Google, Samsung in our
case have a clause in them that says
they are sole and exclusive provisioner
and revoker of MDL and like that's
something I want to share with you all
that like one particular thing because
it does conflict with the SETI idea and
so how do we join forces together and
say like hey Apple Google uh let's not
have that as the standard clause. cause
all of us are sort of against that idea.
Um so I think that there is an ask maybe
and and how can we contribute it's not
just an ask of you can we host it can we
do something so that we can do that
knowledge sharing and really accelerate
our co-rowth
we will be emailing out after the summit
uh one obviously we had the white paper
of what is SETI we have some resources
that we've created of model legislation
model resolutions model executive orders
for us to do a formal consortium this
should be something you want your
elected officials, governor or
legislature to authorize. Um we've had
the disc discussion with our governor
and let them know we wanted to do a
consortium which is why we've invited
you all today. If one more state for and
we've had a couple reach out and say
actually we're very interested if you
can get the formal approval we'll start
si.gov and and it's not si.utah.gov
si.gov. We need at least two states with
formal approval and that's where we
start building that multi-state formal
consortium and we can start then uh
advocating for ourselves and for our
citizens and put these resources there
and we can build it together.
More hands over here.
Yeah, that works. Okay. Um so first of
all, thank you. This is actually turned
out very well. uh as an event and I
think there's been a lot of really great
interest. Um I always talk about this as
an idea when we talk about off Broadway
use cases as Representative Coler
mentioned, but I think the idea of vital
records um is something that is not so
much any having anything really
implemented yet. And uh I always like to
say death records because everyone needs
one one day. uh death and taxes are the
two things that they say are inevitable
and there's a guardianship mechanism and
a burial permit mechanism and a plot of
land kind of have everything at once. Um
I do am the treasurer of a cemetery so I
would love some funds.
We're we're actually going to have
George Mchuan make a comment about how
are we engaging vital records. The
amazing thing actually about government
is once we start saying we want to do
something it opens doors with all these
organizations.
I wasn't anticipating getting on stage.
So one of the things we've done is we've
reached out to Napsus and I just gave a
discussion to their security and privacy
group last week. We are actually talking
about the schema that they have for a
national standard for a certified birth
certificate and their digital schema. So
we have committed that that if they want
us to come out to their December event,
we will bring a SETI compatible version
of that. So they're close on their
standard. We just need to wrap it in the
appropriate cryptography to make sure
that it meets the study threshold. And I
think we'll be there. And the the real
goal will be is in June of next year
when they have their annual event that
we'll really move that forward with them
and kind of codify all that.
one of the this session as we go in to
uh make recommendations for the SETI
program and we also need to recommend
what would the next legislation look
like. Part of that does need to be
prioritization of credentials and that's
been a very common ask. How do we get
these other value added credentials, not
just mobile driver's license or driving
credential, but it was well birth
certificate, your immunization records,
your death certificate and um and so I
would anticipate that would be part of
the discussion we have this session is
not only do we need to get it out there,
but then we need to work with the
groups. So we had I think we had part of
the group group here from Health and
Human Services today where vital records
is, but I I think that is a lowhanging
fruit use case to get out there. We'd
actually love to know what are you going
to use that data for if people have it?
What's the private sector able to to
provide value for if you have those
records though? And Scott, I think you
had a question, right?
I Oh, sorry.
Three things. One, excellent day. Really
outstanding. Two, um, incrementalism is
important, but there's a cart and a
horse kind of aspect to this. And so,
who how do you get to trust? And I think
that's one thing that we really need to
ask ourselves in terms of who is trusted
to each of us. And if that's our
teacher, our professor, our doctor,
our lawyer, our banker, I mean where
that comes in, I think really might help
you define use cases and how to go after
those early and first. And third, if you
want an example of one state that I if
you went to Hawaii anytime during the
pandemic, Hawaii did an really excellent
job of making sure that they could
reopen their economy, which is tourism,
by making sure that they had the smart
health card for people to come in and
show prove you had to prove you were
vaccinated in order to visit at that
time. and they did a really a great job
of it. People were motivated, of course,
to fill this out and and an ID for it.
But it's just one example that you might
want to loop in Hawaii on.
So,
listening to all the constituents here,
the challenge I think that we have here
is a scope problem. There's lots of
things that can be done, but the way to
get something done is iterative and it
needs to start with the core of what
you're looking for. So, you've done two
things. You've said we're going to have
a state endorsed
identity. Okay? And you have a law. So,
you have two things to build upon. I
think you start there. What is the state
going to do? Whether you have you know
paper to present to the state to endorse
but it has to be focused on the first
and foremost thing which is how do we
issue a state endorsed digital identity
and and start there and then use cases
will come once you have that established
if you don't have that established
what's the SETI project so that needs to
be the absolute core and it needs to
start with a risk assessment because
there's a million risks we talked about
today. But there are only certain risks
that can be mitigated by a project like
this and that will drive the scope of
how you can mitigate the risk to the re
to the degree that the state can accept
and you take the law and all the
requirements that you have in the law
and put it in the governance framework
and set of requirements and at least you
are have you have momentum. You need to
start with momentum and leadership and
others will come and use cases will come
but it has to be right down the road for
what you've what you've done. Don't lose
so don't lose focus on that. You have
law to drive a state endorsed digital
identity. Make that happen. You have the
you have the means to do it and and you
have the expertise in the room here to
start for sure.
So, Matthew Hston here from Brigham
Young University and uh I think
transcripts and educational data is a
very complex use case and been working
on this since 2016 with SSI space and um
we've made a long way. So, it's really
amazing. But I wanted to emphasize
something that I think about with um
decentralized identity I think is
important is that just because we have a
credential and a set credential doesn't
mean we have a ubiquitous identifier. So
we don't want to have a unique
identifier that correlates us wherever
we go. We have the possibility of using
that identifier where we want to, but we
can create an ephemeral identifier with
our credential and make a connection
with another entity to present our
information. That's really important
that when we think of our use cases,
we're not thinking of I can be
correlated wherever and that's a great
user experience. And that may be true,
but I may not want that as an
individual. And the technology needs to
support the privacy policy of me being
able to choose to create an identifier
to present my interfa.
Um, so I want to emphasize that. Another
thing I wanted to emphasize is
credentials need to be intentional. They
don't have to be where everything is
stored in one credential. Right? I can
have a very micro credential for a
specific attended purpose. And the
technology stack um allows me to take
multiple credentials and draw selective
disclosure information from each of them
and aggregate it into a presentation for
the verifier. So that means as an issuer
of a credential, I don't have to solve
all my use cases where I think my
credential is going to be used. I just
have to focus on my data and and give
that to the individual and let the
verifier define their own data contract
that really empowers them from a data
model right perspective of verifier
defines their contract and we can
fulfill it from a number of credentials.
We can give an example of that with our
the first credential and this is what
Representative Cutler was referring to
as our offhighway vehicle training
certificate which we put out a
verifiable digital credential for this
uh training certificate to drive your
four-wheeler on the roads. Yeah. Thank
you. And and uh we have um but it
doesn't say who you are. So you still it
doesn't provide your identity. You have
to have both an identity and this
credential to say you know who you are
and that you've taken the course. Let's
see where are we with our microphones
maybe here. Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, Phil Long from the US Chamber of
Commerce Foundation and T3 Innovation
Network. I just want to bring us back to
the actually the first presentation that
was given this morning by Ryan first who
are Ryan. Yeah. um that reminded us that
we really need to look at the the um
examples of failures of the things that
we're looking at as potential priorities
to try to learn from them because we we
tend to dismiss that was done by them.
It was done at a different time perhaps
a year ago. It may not be relevant but
there are things and lessons in there
that will be extremely valuable if you
look for them. So that's one thing and
the second to reinforce several of the
comments here which is to pick the two
or three to start with that are win-wins
for all of the stakeholders involved
because everybody's going to have
resistance to it at some point in this
early stage. So the where you can come
up with one where there's beneficial
time savings for a government office to
get something done that time savings
benefits the individual who's making a
request and the benefit of the
credential actually has direct value to
that person for what they're trying to
do. Those combinations are absolutely
critical and I applaud you for doing all
of this.
Thank you. Do we still have Jeremy Grant
here? I'm gonna steal a line that he
said. We can't build identity or uh what
what did he call it? It says we can't
build ident or we're a bunch of identity
weenies building identity for other
identity weenies. And and so we can't be
identity nerds trying to build this
really small use case of like, yeah,
it'd be great to use a verifiable
credential to I don't know, Timothy,
what's a really weird use case? You can
probably think of one off your head.
What? Okay. You got a you got a use
case?
Which one?
Oh, yeah. What about the beekeeper's
license?
Okay. Okay. Beekeepers license. That's a
pretty small use case. And I I does
government go and actually check
beekeeper licenses.
So, but we yeah, we have to build
identity for people that it's going to
have value and we have to meet them
where they are. Who how how are they
going to get value? How is government
going to get some value? you and I think
that's also where I said we have the
ability because we are a monopoly to
solve the catch22 of well let's create
that instance where both can get value
and we're already spending money on it
so it's let's move those resources to
actually realize the savings that can
come from that
so who has ideas of how we can work
together with other government entities
is
hello. Hello. My name is Mariano Marino
Green. I'm from Mexico City. I'm very
glad to be here with you guys. Uh even
though that I'm born Mexican-American
and I'm more Mexican than American. I
live most of my life there in Mexico. So
I have learned a lot with you guys how
we can implement. We have been working
with clear companies try to like develop
the the Mexican environment there and
but we came to the conclusion that it
has to be a grassroot movement. has to
be with the communities you know the
communities has to endorse their own not
only the entity you know like yes the
entity has to be uh more broad you know
but
it's something that this movement has to
be more more locally you know I have
been talking with some of these persons
here and a a lot of those persons came
to the same conclusion you know and
that's that's the way that I think
personally the human being has to like
has to move towards to that because if
not that will happen with centralization
and control power we all know that so
this idea of stay indoors I will say it
more like community indoors that's my
grain of salt
like that community endorsed one of the
um I had the opportunity I think it was
uh is representative Chevier still here
she invited me to speak at uh one of her
events for stand for health freedom a
couple weeks ago and we had a a really
interesting discussion of you mentioned
community of how to decentralize the
proofing process out into the community.
A lot of cities and towns and school
districts or even our post offices are
in the community. Do you need to go
centrally to a DMV to do proofing or can
we have lots of entities doing it? Move
it out to the community so there's more
trust because these are their neighbors
that work out there. If you can
standardize the identity verification
and proofing process, there's some real
low lowhanging fruit and we can we can
eliminate some of those inefficiencies
or barriers for people that that can't
get it currently. And if you could just
go to your local city recorder or your
local treasurer or your local postal
office, why don't you have all the
options? And and that's I think a great
way to get that grassroots going of
those communities that want it. We know
Utah County and and some small cities
have been saying we want it. if we could
build it, bring it out to them.
Pat Brooks with the state of Missouri
uh judiciary. Um I'm not sure how many
people here are familiar with the
standard called NEM.
Anyone familiar with NE? Okay, NE is the
national information exchange model and
that started as what was the predecessor
of that was called GJXDM and that was a
global justice
data exchange model and what you're
talking about doing here is following
the same path that that program
followed. You have a grassroots
follow along with the gentleman just
before that people had a need to do
something and the standards were
established and not so much in
legislation but in adoption from a
technology perspective to say this is
how we can get the work done. Going back
to the comments of publishing schemas,
publishing standards that people can
adopt and the organization that that
that started that was a multi-state
organization and it was in the justice
domain. And what happened to it was it
saw a need to exchange information in
multiple domains and identity is one of
those domains. And so I would encourage
you to make sure that that that if we're
establishing a standard for multiple uh
states to follow that we look at if
there is a something at the national
level that could be more readily adopted
than maybe building something from total
scratch. You have governance that you
have to issue. You have to have u
vitality issues. You have technology
standards. But um I I think this is a
wonderful idea and I think that that it
can be uh well served to see how others
have done something similar and going
forward
over here.
Michael proper. I have um I've seen this
dilemma that we've been building and and
sitting upon for years, well over a
decade actually.
And
the solution's right in front of us.
But will we really see it?
And what I mean by that is we know that
we've all got to come together and adopt
a system. And we know that there's a
political side of it and there's a
technology side of it.
But what if they really existed?
Would you really adopt them? Would you
really use them? Even if it had the
beekeeper scenario built into it
and 86 other certificates, permits,
licenses that already exist and already
use these standards,
would you really use it? Would the state
of Utah really use it?
Would the state of Arizona really really
use it? Would Mexico really use it?
Mexico doesn't know.
It's it's a community thing. It's the
person that would actually be the
ultimate decision maker if they're going
to use it. That's why MDL has such I
think Arizona has a ton of adoption,
17% adoption.
If we could do that with a decentralized
system where the individual actually
will th if we could do the same 20% of
MDL energy into a decentralized system
and people knew about it the awareness
and adoption would go through the roof
because it's around the individual
first.
If we want to be true and honest around
what's going on, Cindy who has a son
that's dead is one very small proof.
It's not just the person's life and
their breath that's gone. It's their
time on earth that's sucked from them
from these corporations.
whether they're sluming around
pornography or they're sluming around
video games that are taking the youth
when we're allowing AI to be able to
replicate and take not just from the
next generation the grandparents our
parents
our children this is our responsibility
in Hawaii it's our kulana it's our it's
our time
and I look at what Chris and Phil and
Sam and Tim. These people have dedicated
dedic decades of their life.
I too 19 years,
$28 million of my own hard-earned money
into this technology
for the state, for the countries, other
countries for no price.
Would you really adopt it? Would you
really look at it?
Because if you do it here and you can do
10% of what we're talking about, other
states will get on board with it. If you
give it back to the individuals and
truly let them own their own identity,
their own data, their own payments,
their own assets, and pass it to the
next generation instead of the state
sucking out hundreds of millions of
dollars of unclaimed assets because
people don't even know where they are.
The technology is here today.
It's not just in some proprietary phone
that's really open. It's not about a
phone. Even though Cindy's parents,
Cindy's son, that's how they that's how
he took his life. That's how they stole
him. As a parent of six kids, I want to
be able to say I did everything that I
could
so that my son that went to this
university and when I sat on the board
of this university when her son killed
himself
was responsible enough to say, you know
what, enough is enough. We got to stop
the games. We got to come together with
the policy. We got to come together with
the technology
and we have to actually act. Charlie
Kirk was killed 500 feet from here, 150
ft from here.
The action behind his choice network was
all what it's about acting. It's about
doing
the technologies here. People have seen
it. People can live it. They can adopt
it. You can download it. Utah Life. Go
to your app store. Download it. Log in.
And it's simple. This isn't
hypothetical. These are real systems
that really function better than
Bitcoin, better than Ethereum, better
than the banking system, better than the
current identity management systems.
And I'm sorry. I want to slow down and I
want to just let the process take its
process. And Chris, I emphatically
support everything that you're doing,
but we don't have time. We don't have
another 10 years for another decade
worth of kids to not only stick bullets
in their heads, but to stick bits in
their heads that takes them away from
the life that they've been given. It
steals their time. It steals their
souls. It steals their hearts.
I'm sorry that this means so much to me,
but I can see the solution.
Thank you, Michael. And our timeline is
that 10 years is data governance. Our
time on this is as fast as we can. Uh
Senator Colmore said this on it was on
KUTV last week and he said we have to
get it right. You know, we don't want to
cause more harm, but the time is as fast
as we can get out there so parents and
individuals have the tool. So that's our
timeline and that's our commitment is
we're trying to get it out as fast as we
can. Obviously we have to follow the
law, but we we understand the importance
and that it's needed now. This is not
something that we want regular
bureaucracy to to just sit on and and I
think that's why we're all here. This is
not normal bureaucracy. This is not a
normal meeting. This is something
different is happening and and this is
going to get done right.
I'm not going to try to follow that. But
my question is for for those in the
private sector partners who are helping
us, what can we do to help move this
faster? Understanding that we have to do
it right, but how can we move faster?
I think yeah, Tim, so you'll hear our
mic.
I've been working in the space for over
a decade now. It's like trying to push a
a really heavy rock uphill really hard.
A lot of failure. A lot of things we
tried in different ways that that didn't
work and very uh optimistic about SETI
and what's happening at the state level.
I think the answer um I've always been a
small government guy
and um the reality is that now that
government is getting into the digital
identity space it's it's several decades
behind private industry and private
industry has has turned the digital
identity space into this incredible
surveillance mechanism.
Um but now government's getting into the
digital identity space and government um
at the end you said has the monopoly uh
on whatever it decides to do. Um
government will dictate how much privacy
or freedom or autonomy we have or don't
have in the digital realm is my
prediction after all I've seen. So to
answer your question about how to
finally solve this, I think Utah has to
be successful in getting other states
and create momentum. I know that Utah
has depprioritized interoperability,
which is really interesting when you
look at Utah's hierarchy of val
hierarchy of values for a lot of um uh
identity initiatives specifically, but
technology in general, the highest
priority is interoperability. And so
what gets sacrificed is uh security and
privacy.
Specifically with the MDL uh standard,
there was a country that said we need to
have phone home and they didn't call it
that. We need to have server retrieval.
And it was baked into the standard
because a country demanded it. Different
culture. It's not our culture. Someone
else's culture demanded it. It got baked
in. Uh a bunch of us squawkked about
this a couple few months ago and they
have now separated it thankfully. But
the point is that was made earlier.
We as Utah need to do what's best for
Utons if even if it means that we're not
interoperable with the rest of the
world. We have to dep prioritize
interoperability and do what's best for
the privacy and security of our
citizens. And so what I think is the
answer to your question is to get Utah
to be more than just Utah that's doing
this. to get some representatives from
other states who are here to actually
move forward and join. It reminds me of
the end of the movie um A Bug's Life
where the the grasshoppers were were
bullying the ants through the whole
movie and finally at the very end the
ants realize they're more powerful if
they lock arms. I I this digital
identity thing is so big and I see
grasshoppers everywhere who are the
bullies in digital identity and I think
the only way we do it is Utah's an ant.
We need to lock lock arms with other
ants and scare the grasshoppers out of
this space.
Uh my name is Jeremy Fster from Cardano
Foundation in Vidian and I'm going to
say that I'm in the technologist camp or
stakeholder group and normally when
speaking to policy makers there uh is a
view from technologists that you're way
off the mark with what you're presenting
as policy. However, that is not the case
at all when coming to SETI. And I think
that the the the uh engagement that you
receive and the interest that you're
receiving uh the reason why it's so high
is because fundamentally the policy
makes sense for the constituents.
We've been able to demonstrate with our
demo that today SETI is not just policy.
It can be codified. It can be
implemented.
And I would ask uh do you see a path
where you can eat your own dog food?
Because when you look to implement SETI,
you need that first user. A very easy
lowhanging fruit could be having a SETI
wallet to have a passwordless login to a
government website.
And if you do something like this, it's
very low risk to actually get things
started and have something uh put into
production that is end to end.
Well, I'm going to make a quick comment
because I actually got some tech I get
texts every weekend just you guys know
from citizens that are like I hate this.
What are you doing? And uh they actually
sent a text and you may have been about
to go here where they were going to say
hey they were like what is this Utah ID
I now need to use to log into a system.
It's a just a single sign on portal
which any it's any single sign on system
is going to have tracking. It's a
centralized Yeah. It's a username
password type system. So there's low
hanging fruit and I I think those
discussions already happening. So we
know constituents have identified the
system. They actually have said they
want SETI on. We have the man here in
charge of it.
So we have a couple of initiatives that
we're working on and and uh we h first
of all we have our um we we have we have
in a beta form our next version citizen
portal which we've branded my Utah and
you'll probably see Governor Cox making
an announcement about this early next
year but the goal and we don't have this
quite here yet I'm looking but we'll
we'll be getting there where we hope to
be able to have people authenticate with
a study credential for that and we don't
quite have the study credential yet to
do that, but we want it. And so that'll
be one of our first and best use cases
to get that going. And we also want to
look at state systems. So we have our
22,000 state employees and we have
identity and access management that we
log them into our state system and we
like to have a a steady credential so
that they can log in as employees and we
would like to move away from passwords
even with our multiffactor. uh we don't
love them. We'd like to you move to a
more secure settype credential for login
and use in identity and access
management systems across the state.
Hopefully that'll be one place we can
start to get rolling.
I'm Mark Allen. I'm with Citizen Portal,
my brother to ancestry.com and we're
we're trying to work towards government
transparency and accountability. And
Chris, you're spot on when you say that
uh most of the state of Utah is not
compliant. I think our stats show about
15% of public meetings are being
recorded gavvel to gavvel. Uh I think
some of the lowhanging fruit that I'd
suggest for authentication and
certification would be within your own
home uh of state government.
Um, I have been branded a vexacious
litigant as of last night by the judge
of Charlie Kirk case because I asked for
a court record.
Let that sink in. I asked for a WebEx
video hearing.
I can't get anybody in the state of Utah
to give me a certified record.
When I'm doing grammar, they say, "Oh,
it's a duplicate request. I want
statecertified
authenticated genuine record that I can
take to the bank and say I'm innocent
but when I ask for that I get branded a
vexacious litigant. So my admission
admonition as a state and county
delegate is also with what we're doing
is clean up your own house first. Not at
your level, but at the clerk level where
they won't give me a certified record
where the keyboard is the weapon of
today. And I'm the first victim probably
in the state of Utah of lawfare.
And uh but if I had everything that you
been talking about today, set a ability
to authenticate, ability to uh track
back into the record to see who was the
ghost that hit the keyboard to backdate
a record by two years. Um
I wouldn't be as smart as I am now, but
I've learned a lot in the last 10 years.
And I'd say Utah, let's get it right
first. Let's start in the judiciary
where the problems are. And then my
personal identifying information I can
control and protect it. But mine's been
scattered to databases around the world
and I don't know how to un undamage uh
what that's been done. We also have a
problem with
all three branches of government in
Utah. Uh they're not watchdoging each
other. There's not enough healthy
friction. I'd like to see a little more
healthy friction between stuff. So and
this is not specific setting related. It
really is civil rights, my personal
protections, and I I don't need to go
deeper down that because I really
appreciate what you're trying to do. If
we would have had implemented what you
did, what you're talking about 10 years
ago, my life would be totally different.
But I've seen how China weaponizes and
surveills. I've been surveiled in Utah,
Provo, Utah.
So,
court certified records definitions are
really important. What's a certified
record? What does a certified record
look like to you? If I go down to the
court and try and get a a digital copy
or something that someone will go, oh,
this is we made a mistake. How do we
undo the mistake? So, that's a personal
use case scenario, but I think our
courts uh they don't on a standard basis
uh do a transcript. You can't get a
certified record unless I pay for it.
$2,500 for me to get a certified record.
So, I would start within the court
judiciary and start certifying records
and start doing court transcripts if it
were me. That's lowhanging fruit that
would benefit most of Utah.
Thank you, Mark. We are all right. We're
gonna have one more question. We're at
time, but Jeremy Baker is a Utah privacy
commissioner. If you don't know,
governance structure in Utah, we have a
whole commission dedicated to privacy.
So, take that back to your state if you
don't have one. Go ahead, Jeremy.
Um, so I'm actually going to take this
from a different perspective, and this
is from my private sector experience
with being uh someone that integrates
security and identity into software
applications.
um and it's related to how do we get the
private sector to adopt this a lot of
private sector companies like even
Roblox or others they end up using
identity providers like AWS Cognto octa
um Azure B2C all of those they've added
in different integrations for identities
so you have like your social media login
that are allowed in there as well as
like the current adoption of pass keys
which has been really slow to roll out
across the entire private sector, even
though they're significantly better idea
than um passwords and usernames. Um but
to get SETI adopted across all of them I
think the framework like the what we've
talked about today having an open
framework where those major identity
providers could bring that integration
in as an authentication service under
their umbrella to have it as an option
to add directly into applications that
are currently working with their
products. I I think that would be a
significant push for adoption. Thank
you, Jeremy. Okay, we're gonna close up
first by raise of hands. Who wants to
help get seti going forward? Okay. Uh
and if it's not up, okay, everyone got
it up. I And that was the worst thing to
do because I am shameless. One of my
tricks in government is I have no
problem asking for your time. So, you
will all be getting calls in your states
to move this forward and we'll be
shameless together to take this
national. Um we are so thankful that
everyone came today. I know this is a
long day and this was a lot of
information, but you now are ready to
actually have the in-depth discussions.
So, we will go back. We'll do some of
the grunt work to get organized. We'll
set up an extensions. We'll make our
materials available. We'll reach out to
the states to get at least one more
formally involved so we can get si.gov
going at si.utah.gov doesn't have the
same, you know, ring to it. We want
si.gov. Um, but we'll get rolling on
that and we're going to meet back here
again in less than six months for the
next SETI summit. And from what we're
already hearing, it's probably going to
be twice as big. And by that point, with
the with the pace we're going, uh, not
only we have more legislation, but
hopefully we have a lot more to share so
other states can take it, steal from our
tax dollars, and take it to your state
so you don't have to pay for it. And
let's get SETI rolling. So, thank you
everyone.
Thanks,