I will never edit it, but I'm going to
keep it. I'm happy to keep it. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you, Chris. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
There we go. Yay. All right. So my name is
Scott Perry. I'm here to talk about open
standards and open protocols. And so when
you're looking at a SEDI project, okay,
we're just getting started, but there's
been effort to deal with decentralized
identity for the last 20 years. Starting
with Phil Windley co-chairing the Internet
Identity Workshop 20 years ago. And then
for me, it's been 10 years after I got a
call from Timothy Ruff saying, I need help
around trying to deal with internet trust.
And I realized as an auditor that was
auditing certification authorities, I
realized that the traditional model wasn't
going to work to add internet, to add the
kind of trust that we're trying to do with
the SEDI project. So just a quick little
bit about me. I'm the auditor in the room.
I was auditing for my career last 20
years. I've been auditing cryptography as
a profession. Auditing small group folks
that audit certification authorities. I
was the auditor for a certification
authority based in Utah. It's great to be
back here. You know, I was working with
DigiCert for quite a long time. And I've
also been leading some open source and
open standards projects that are listed
here. But I want to focus on the acronym
suit that I'm going to talk about because
it's important for folks to understand
there has been a lot of work. There was a
question around is it going to work today?
I'd say two years ago, things hadn't been
completely baked in, but I think we're
ready. The open source community is
absolutely ready for SEDI and I'm excited
for them to demonstrate their value in all
of the work that they've been doing for
over 10 years. And so when we start about
the I'm going to give you just a summary
of some of the organizations that I've
been touched with that have been
developing some unique products that can
be leveraged in into the SEDI project. And
it starts with the Linux Foundation. So I
don't know if you know, but the Linux
Foundation is the largest repository of
repository of open source code in the
world. They operate 100% of all the
supercomputers and 62.7 of servers run the
Linux kernel. And so they decided, you
know, to get involved in decentralized
trust. There was a number of projects that
was driving some of this type of thinking.
And so they established a subset of their
organization last year. And they invited
and consolidated a couple of open source
and open standards projects. One that is
called the Trust over IP. And I'd invite
all of you to spend time going to the
Trust over IP. I am the co-chair of the
steering committee. We have a couple of
steering committee members here in the
audience. And they've been doing enormous
work to get ready for the SEDI project.
We've created a stack, a technology and
governance stack. We everyone's talking
about governance. Trust over IP is the
leading organization driving governance
standards and methodologies and toolkits.
And I hope that the organization here, the
SEDI projects uses it because it's been
successful in the C2PA, in GLEIF, in the
government of Bhutan and such. It also is
housing KERI. You've heard some stories
about KERI. It's a blueprint of how to
decentralize identity and make security
more autonomous and user-controlled. It's
a security more autonomous and user
-controlled. It's exactly one of the main
principles within the SEDI project. We
have a trust spanning protocol which acts
underneath the internet protocol to the
ability to authenticate senders and
payloads of transactions because we need
that level of trust in our transaction
protocols and also it is leading around
trust registries which are public
repositories which are public repositories
which are public repositories of those
that have passed certain governance
frameworks. The Open Wallet Foundation was
founded in August 2023. It hosts
components that can be used to create
secure, flexible, and portable wallets.
Where are we going to keep the SEDI
credentials? We need a secure place
because they have private cryptographic
keys. Also, we've talked about the you
know, the W3C, you know, the W3C started
in 1994 produces two key standards that we
can leverage within the SEDI project. The
decentralized identifiers, the DIDs
projects as well as defining the
components of verifiable credentials which
we expect to use. In the decentralized
identity foundation started in 2017, we
have a number of projects that are working
that can add value. They are the leading
place to deal with the leading place to
deal with all of the decentralized
identity methods that are out in the
marketplace and they are working to
consolidate that. They're creating
standards around the communication using
DIDCOM as well as the presentation
exchange of credentials as well as hosting
an organization called the Creators
Assertion Working Group which I co-chair
which deals with individual and
organizational attribution to any digital
object based on the content credential
created by the C2PA. So I would look up
look that up as well. Also, the OpenID
which has been around since 2007 and has
modified their standards to deal with
verifiable credentials with OpenID Connect
and OpenID Verifiable Credentials. ISO, as
we have mentioned here, has been
instrumental in creating foundational
security standards standards standards
standards both with quality and ISO 27001
for foundational security management
systems as well as they have identity
management standard ISO 24760 and finally
also the mobile driver's license the ISO
1801.
We talked a little bit about what the role
of the federal government would be. Well,
NIST is is providing a lot of value there
associated with dealing with post-quantum
cryptography. They're also dealing with
the certification of hardware security
modules which protect your private key and
are the leading standard for digital
identity guidelines both for proofing of
identity authentication and federation. So
what's the case for open standards? How do
you use it? Okay, at the end of the day,
it enhances interoperability and
compatibility. Okay? It prevents the
vendor lock-in so that all the tech
vendors are using open standards and they
can use it so you're not locked into an
individual technology company and can't
get out of them. It creates the innovation
and collaboration. You're not limited to
an individual's company. R&D you're
leveraging world R&D. You're leveraging
world R&D. And that's what the state of
the organizations that I work for. They
are creating that research and development
that we could leverage. It increases
flexibility and Joe Jackson had mentioned
about future proofing. They're baking in
advances of these standards to deal with
new technologies as they come along and
they're free. State loves free, right? And
the best way to leverage it. And the best
way to leverage it is steal this
technology and steal these standards
because it's there for the taking and they
work. So I'm going to just walk through.
I'm not going to go into details of some
of the products that we've created in the
open standards world, but these are some
of the ones as a governance professional
have leveraged on. And we've realized
there was a trust triangle with the
issuer, holder, and verifier. Verifier.
Trust over IP added a governance model.
And we have found that that's the missing,
that's the secret sauce into making it
long lasting and workable. This I'm not
going to go into the detail, but this is
the trust over IP trust stack. And you can
see that there's been a lot of work that's
gone into it. And Chris Rammel said to me,
if you do one thing, let people know how
complicated it is. And we've done a lot of
the baked in work. So governance
framework. So governance framework. It's
already built the framework, but you don't
have to worry about it. You just have to
put in your requirements into the
governance framework. And then you could
leverage the time and energy to get this
to market. So I'm going to quickly go
through the reasons why you should adopt
open standards.
It's all there. And I think we're ready to
go. And I think you could take advantage
of a lot of the work that's been done to
make this happen. If you want to have an
idea of a white paper that's free to use
on how to use governance and use trust
registries. I put it out there. It'll be
in the videotape so that you could access
this at your leisure. Thank you very much
for your time. Thank you.
I would like to recognize two individuals
if they are here. Scott Stornetta, are you
here? Been walking around. Is he in the
room? Samuel Smith. He took off. I was
hoping to I want to acknowledge two people
whom I think are fathers of modern digital
trust. And I'll just say that Scott
Stornetta was cited by Satoshi Nakamoto's
Bitcoin paper. He's the original conceiver
of blockchain, which is a really important
innovation in digital trust. We wouldn't
have cryptocurrency without that
innovation. And literally the creator of
blockchain quoted Scott Stornetta, who's
been here today. He's out in the hall or
somewhere. And then Sam had to leave. Sam
is the creator of the KERI protocol key
event receipt infrastructure that has
inspired the SEDI identity model,
including the very exciting thing I get to
talk about, which is guardianship and
delegation. A really big breakthrough in
digital trust to solve a very thorny
problem. Now I'm going to break from how I
usually present things and I am going to
I'm
going to really almost read the slides,
which I hate to do that, but I know this
is being videoed and I know these
presentations are going to be asked for
and I want anyone who gets this
presentation at a later time to be able to
understand every single point. And so
you're going to see me, you know,
basically reading some of this, but we're
going to go quickly. Really important
concept. First of all, a couple of
definitions. Guardianship gives someone
legal authority and responsibility to make
decisions for another like a child or a
disabled person. So real key concepts
underlying their legal authority and
responsibility. Two different really
important concepts that make up
guardianship. Delegation. I want to wait
for my example to come up. There's a
little bit of a lag here. Temporarily
transfers specific duties or powers, but
not full legal responsibility. Key
concepts are temporarily and specific
duties or powers and not full legal
responsibility. That's the difference
between guardianship and delegation. So
let's give an example. If a parent
delegates school pickup to a neighbor, the
parent still holds the ultimate
responsibility for the child's welfare.
Okay. Okay. That's just a task that has
been delegated, but not ultimate
responsibility or legal authority.
Guardianship legally transfers that
responsibility. The guardian and not the
parent is now the one accountable for
decisions and care. So those are the two
conceptual differences. Now, I'm going to
share with you 10 tools that we use in
combination to make guardianship and
delegation work as well as all of the rest
of the SEDI protocol. I chose Lego or Lego
here instead of a toolbox. The difference
is when you put Legos together, you might
make a pirate ship. You might make a
pirate, you might make spaceship, you
might make a dinosaur. You put them
together in different combinations to do
the thing you're trying to do. A toolbox,
you get out of the toolbox and you do
something to use the tools and then you're
done. So with SEDI, it's very much the
Legos, even though they are tools. The
first tool is Verifiable containers. Now,
Verifiable containers. Now, for those of
you familiar with Verifiable credentials,
we're talking about the same concept, but
a Verifiable credential is misnamed. It is
a container that holds data and makes it
portable. It might or might not be a
credential. It can have anything inside
the container. It's the container that's
verifiable technically. So it makes data
portable and verifiable. The next tool is
secure attribution to verify who digitally
signed a thing. So if you get a container
that has some data in it, who put that
container together? Who did it? And being
able to secure part is really important.
Verify who did it. The third tool, non
-reputability. You can't later say that
you didn't. Once it's been signed, it is
non-reputable. You can't later say someone
else did that. So when you have encryption
with TLS or HTTPS, you see the encryption
that happens on the internet. There is
repudiability. You don't know who is on
the other side of the other side of the
other side. It's not bound to a human
person or an individual. It's just there's
a weak form of authentication that goes
with encryption, but it's not like a
digital signature that you can actually
bind to an individual and say who did the
thing. Chain signatures which give you
verifiable provenance. So you can actually
see a chain of authority rather than just
a single level. So if someone's signed
something like a manager, like a manager,
well, who was their boss, where'd they get
their authority from? Who was their boss?
Who did they work for? And is that really
the company? How do we know that was
really the company? And on you can see a
full chain and it's unlimited. A full
chain of provenance on there is another
really important tool. And then weighted
multisig critical for business and on a
whole lot of other cases we're going to
talk about here in a moment. But weighted
multisig means that you can have one of
two signatures. You can have one of one,
just one person signs it and they have the
full weight. You can have one of two, two
of three, five of seven, 11 of 92,
whatever you make up. Okay. So it's
weighted because you can have one
signature have more weight than another.
And in a situation with divorced parents
and things like that and where the court
might be intervening, really important in
guardianship to have weighted multisig.
We'll talk a little bit about that.
Consent. The ability to use your identity
to make a non-reputable reputable
agreement and say, I agree to a thing.
Delegation of authority, which we're going
to talk about in a little greater detail.
Revocability of that delegation. And
critically, a really important
breakthrough with SEDI, privacy respecting
delegation. I was just talking to a
representative from another state who said
that the reason that they were adopting a
very popular technology for identity is
because their technical people thought
that there was no way to get around a
phone home for revocation. That is not
true. There is a way to get around a phone
home and have privacy respecting
revocation. Really important breakthrough
in digital trust in one of the tools in
SEDI. Graduated disclosure, which can be
selective, contractual. Basically, you can
disclose as little as you want to disclose
when you're doing something and there's
actually a way to only disclose that thing
once terms for disclosure have been agreed
to and consented to and that can happen
behind the scenes with agentic AI and
these agreements could be made and you
actually don't disclose a thing until the
terms have been agreed and it's mutual.
It's like a real-time NDA done digitally.
Really exciting capability and detection
and recovery from compromise. As a matter
of fact, SEDI brings a four-step concept
I'm very excited about from a security
standpoint. SEDI expects compromise, then
it can detect compromise, then it can
contain compromise, then it can contain
compromise and recover. These are mind
-bendingly awesome in digital trust.
Expect, detect, contain, recover. Secure
attribution, really important in Utah law
and electronic signature can be as legally
valid as handwritten with some
assumptions. There's got to be an intent
to sign. There's got to be attribution
which is where SEDI comes in and really
helps consent to electronic transaction
which interestingly there's going to be a
dilemma. There's going to be a legal one.
Can you use digital means to agree to use
digital means?
That's going to be a fun one. And then no
legal exclusion. Sometimes there's a legal
exclusion that says you cannot use
digital. You must have paper. SEDI can use
its own tools to prove each of these.
Doesn't mean that we legally want it to.
There's going to be some policy debates
but it does mean that SEDI can use the
tools to do these things. So guardianship.
Examples of guardianship. Parent of a
child, the natural guardian, guardian of a
disabled adult, guardian for an orphan,
which is court appointed, or temporary
guardianship like when parents are
traveling. Guardianship is the missing
piece of government digital identity. You
don't see it anywhere. You don't see it
talked about. I think it is the cherry on
the sundae when you're doing a digital
identity system if you're government. If
you're not government, you don't care as
much. But when you are government, you
absolutely are the dog wagged by the tail
of dependent populations. So these are the
children, infants, elderly, disabled,
homeless, right? There's advocates for all
of those and they're loud and they're
powerful and they should be. And so to be
able to have guardianship and digital
guardianship that actually brings those
dependent populations into the digital
realm, really important stuff. And if
there's one takeaway from any
representatives of other states that are
looking at SEDI, there's some privacy and
autonomy reasons for looking at SEDI,
there's some security reasons for looking
at SEDI. But I think the number one reason
why a state would look at SEDI is because
of digital guardianship. Because it
includes everybody. All the different
dependent populations you want to include.
No government system has figured this out.
Few of them are even talking about it.
Only 25% of US 16 year olds get a driver's
license. Only 50% of 20 year olds have
driver's license. But yet 100% of 15 year
olds need identity.
SEDI solves a big technical challenge.
Decentralized digital guardianship that's
peer to peer with no phone home and no
dependence on any vendor network or
blockchain. That's a really important
thing. You know what's easy to do
technically? To prove a guardian
relationship. If you phone home to a
server and the server and the server and
the server and the server and the server
and the server and the server says, oh
yeah, that's the parent of the child,
we're good. And you're phoning home to the
server. That's easy technically to do. You
know it's extremely hard that requires the
breakthroughs enabled by Sam Smith who I
mentioned earlier is to be able to verify
that guardian relationship in a
decentralized manner where you're not
phoning home. Offline using Bluetooth peer
to peer. Major breakthrough in digital
trust. Now you know I gave you these guys
some kudos at the beginning. SEDI can
mimic any form of guardianship. A guardian
can prove that the guardian award can
prove who their guardian is and verifiers
can follow guardian requirements for award
authorization. So what I mean by that is
Johnny requests to spend 35 bucks on
fortnight and his mother is prompted for
approval. It's a simple example of how a
verifier can follow guardian requirements
for award authorization. Guardianship,
however, guardianship, however, gets very
tricky. A single guardian is very simple.
It's one to one. A single parent actually
is the simplest use case. A single parent
just they're the only one who makes the
decision, right? It gets trickier when
there's two parents. When they're married,
it's still trickier than a single single
because you can say the parents either one
of them can say Johnny can do it. You can
say both of them have to approve before
Johnny can do it. You can say up to a
certain dollar amount. Up to a certain
dollar amount. Either parent can do it.
But if it exceeds another dollar amount,
then both parents need to be able to do
it. And that's what I call graduated. So
you can have conditions in there and
things like that for that approval. It
gets even trickier with divorced parents
where you have a two to one relationship
with Johnny, potentially a three to one
relationship if the court is involved,
which they might be for some things that
Johnny might want to do. And there's
waiting so you can give more weight to the
court. You can give more weight to one
parent. You can give weight to a
grandparent. You can do whatever you want.
It's called weighted M of N multisig and
so you can divide that authority however
you choose. And adult children of a
disabled parent. So I've got a mother
who's 89 and she's starting to forget some
things. And she's got a lot of living
adult children. And there's some of these
adult children who should probably not
have a say. And what happens with mom.
It's an opinion. But at some point that
might have to be adjudicated. And someone
might have to say, well, when push comes
to sub, the kids are not agreeing. How is
that adjudicated? And however that is, if
the conclusion is that a certain subset of
children have authority and maybe one has
more than the others, that can be modeled
with M of N weighted multisig, which is
part of KERI, part of SEDI. How about
homeless people unable to carry
credentials? Well, what are you doing
there to bring that homeless person in the
digital realm if they're unable to carry
credentials? How does it work in real
life? We try to mimic what happens in real
life and that is there's a government
agency that actually holds some
credentials or has the ability to do
something on behalf of that homeless
person. Very tricky situations. And I'm
going a little bit slower than I want, so
I'm going to go a lot faster. Delegation.
A parent signs a permission slip that
authorizes another adult child to pick up
their child or a manager delegates a task
or an individual delegates to an AI agent.
We talk about AI and agentic AI. That is a
form of delegation. Delegation is
absolutely everywhere. A legislature can
delegate to committees and agencies who
then delegate to departments and outside
companies who delegate multiple levels of
employees who provide a service to a
citizen. So delegation is absolutely
everywhere. All organizations, private or
public or public or our hierarchies of
delegation. SEDI enables an individual to
directly delegate authority to another
without involving anyone else. The
individual, the authority can go directly
to the delegate and give them that
authority. With SEDI anyone anywhere can
verify the claimed authority without
phoning home. We talked about that earlier
decentralization. SEDI can mimic any form
of delegation. A delegator can prove what
and to whom they've delegated. A delegate
can prove what's delegated and from whom.
And by the way, from whom. And by the way,
from whom, and by the way, the word
delegate a little bit awkward because in
some cases a noun, in some cases a verb.
Okay, so I'm using the form delegate here
in number two. A delegate noun can prove
what's delegated verb and from whom.
Delegation can expire or be revoked. A
delegate can delegate again with proof of
authority to do so. Delegations are non
-reputable and which means they can't be
denied later. Delegations can form
hierarchies or chains. They're auditable,
auditable, traceable, they cannot be
forged. They're resilient to key rotation.
And rules and restrictions can be made
verifiable, machine readable, and
enforceable. Sounds like a dream list. It
is. Now you know why we're excited.
Agentic future, by the way, I have to
laugh at this picture of grandma being
helped by a robot. And no, that wasn't
made by AI. And no, I didn't take that
photo. But Microsoft CEO said this and I'm
paraphrasing because this quote is too
long. But the the paraphrase of the the
paraphrase of the Microsoft CEO, AI agents
will replace all software as a service,
SaaS. CEO of Microsoft. And the reason he
says that is because of frankly what I
think is illustrated by grandma. It's a
user experience. Most agentic tasks are
simple and don't require delegation, but
some important ones do. And they require
some delegation, some authority on behalf
of the agent. And I think one of the
greatest use cases. And I think one of the
greatest use cases for agentic AI is user
experience for elderly people. I know my
mom could talk to an agent and ask her to
do something. She struggles to open her
phone and start an app to play Scrabble
with her daughter in Pennsylvania. But I
know she could talk to an agent and say
please open the Scrabble game or please do
something. I think the future of of AI for
elderly people is really bright. And I
want that agent's authority to do
something on behalf of my mom carefully
constrained.
SEDI is ideal for delegating to agentic
AI. So in conclusion, SEDI brings
guardianship and delegation into
verifiable digital form, harmonizing law
and technology. SEDI includes everyone
through digital guardianship. Parents,
caregivers, and courts, can securely
represent those who cannot self-manage
their identity. Through SEDI delegation,
individuals can safely empower others or
AI agents with limited revocable
authority. SEDI actualizes both human and
legal rights and principles and is
designed for the coming agentic AI era.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
SEDI actualized by the way. Good
afternoon. Good afternoon.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
I Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild increased dramatically between 2019
and 2024 from 675 to 24,000 cases. In the
first six months of this year alone,
Roblox has reported more than it reported
all of last year. In 2019, a study of more
than 2,000 child Minecraft players found
that nearly 10% had been asked by another
player to meet in real life. That's almost
200 children and that was six years ago.
This number has grown exponentially. There
have been numerous attempts to remedy
these risks to children. However, they do
not address the core problems, how we
access the internet, digital content, and
the interactions children are exposed to.
Today, you will witness for the first time
in the world two technologies, key event
receipt infrastructure, commonly referred
to as KERI, and authentic chained data
containers, ACDCs, being leveraged in a
manner that no other technology can
achieve today. Providing open source,
state endorsed, digital identity wallet
and supporting services designed to return
control back in the hands of parents and
guardians, empowering them to ensure a
safe and verified digital future for their
children and their children's children.
What we'd like to do now is walk you
through a demonstration leveraging these
technologies.
What Fergal is going to be demonstrating
on the left-hand side is a representation
of the state of Utah Vital Records
platform. What he will be doing here is
issuing a birth certificate. Now, this may
be a manual process conducted by an
administrator. It could be a checkbox in
an existing system that's integrated
integrated. It could be fully automated.
It could be fully automated. It could be
fully automated. But the point here is
that there are certain aspects of SEDI
that must be introduced by the government
and others that fall into the power of the
parents. Fergal is forming a peer-to-peer
channel with the government leveraging the
mobile wallet of the child Oliver in
today's demonstration. The parent, Mary,
also has established a peer-to-peer
communication and she will be requesting
the government issue a birth certificate
to her child as well as a guardianship
credential. These are all ACDC technology.
So what has happened now is a guardianship
credential has been issued to the parent
and a birth certificate has been issued to
Oliver. What you can see online here is
the credential contains any amount of
information including a direct link
potentially to a file system or server. It
can be fully customized based on policy
and that is the most important aspect.
This is not tech providers dictating what
the state can use. This is technology that
is built based on policy and law. Now that
the birth certificate has been issued and
the guardianship credential has now been
issued issued to Mary the mother. And this
could be a multi-signature relationship
for both parents for example. All capable
with KERI and ACDC technology. Now Mary
will leverage the family portal. This is
all open source software you are seeing
here today. This could be running in your
home system like a home media center or it
could be provided by a third party. The
key difference here is these are not like
the centralized systems. The keys
controlling the data reside in the data
reside in the hand of the parent. They
never leave that platform. They never go
into this system you are seeing.
Everything must be signed and approved at
the edge or from the wallet. So now Mary
has logged into this system. You'll notice
there were no usernames, no passwords.
This is known as passwordless
authentication. And now Mary is presenting
her SEDI credentials to the family portal.
This will allow the portal to determine
what features should be available to her.
In there you will see a number of things
appearing in the family tree. This is this
chaining characteristic that was just
mentioned behind ACDC credentials. In the
SEDI wallet is not only a credential
dictating the guardian relationship for
Oliver but also the guardian relationship
to Liam, Liam's father. So this would be a
power of attorney issued by a court for
example. The idea is to demonstrate that
all of this information can be contained
within a chain of credentials that are
cryptographically built upon one another
similar to that scenario with the Lego
blocks just presented on screen. So now
the parents are empowered to issue
credentials to delegate authority to their
children completely removed from the
state. The state has provided the
credential to prove guardianship but now
the parent has control. Now Mary will
issue a credential to control. Now Mary
will issue a credential to Oliver and
you'll see there are three scenarios we've
explored here. Social media, streaming
platforms and gaming consoles. We will
demonstrate a social media credential and
the ability to customize the attributes.
What you can see here initially is a
conversational age rating. This is the
ability for the parent to decide the age
in which they want their children to
interact with. Second, you will see a time
constraint. They can set parameters around
when these credentials can be used when
these platforms can be accessed. And
finally there is a content rating that can
be set by the parent. You'll see a check
box at the bottom that says enable safe
interactions. What this is telling the
system wherever this credential is
presented that this user can only interact
with other SEDI endorsed users. What we're
going to do now is issue this credential
but before I do so. This is just an
example. The policy will dictate the
parameters of this credential. Not the
tech providers. So when that is
established exactly what will go into this
credential, what are those options, then
that will be implemented. They are fully
flexible. What you will see now is Mary
will receive a request because although it
looks like this system is creating and
issuing the credential, it isn't. It is
merely a Lego block to build but Mary the
ability to do the right. So Mary must sign
with the keys that are stored in her SEDI
wallet, her identity which is contained
within in order to execute this action.
And now what you will see is the child
will receive a prompt in their phone
saying their mother would like to issue
them a credential and they must also
approve this credential in order to hold
it and receive it. So what you see here is
not only holding and issuing but also the
ability to do decentralized verification
which is the next step. So now that Oliver
has received a social media access
credential, he can now register for a new
paradigm shift in social media that we are
calling SocialBook today. You'll notice
again there is no usernames and passwords.
Oliver will log in online with his
delegated authority from his mother in an
ACDC credential into the SocialBook
platform. Oliver will scan this QR code
you see on screen to establish a peer-to
-peer connection to establish a peer-to
-peer connection with SocialBook. He will
input his email but you'll notice Oliver
will not be telling the system how old he
is. The state endorsed digital identity
which empowered the mother to create a
social media access credential will inform
the platform cryptographically how old
Oliver is. Oliver will now register for
the platform and will then log into the
platform using no usernames and passwords.
Once Oliver has logged into the platform
we will now start to explore how those
criteria and restrictions that were set by
his parent can be visualized in a system.
What we have done here is we have tagged
the data in this post with a metadata
label indicating the content level of
which this image was and because the
parent has set that restriction to teen is
no longer view that image. If he wanted to
view it he could request it but let's move
on now to the chat to demonstrate how chat
now is leveraging that age restriction.
What you will see on screen here is
existing conversations that are already
underway and you will notice below there
are a number of SEDI tokens that indicate
that these are users that have leveraged a
SEDI based credential to access and
register for the system. and you will see
other users that have red tags there.
These fall outside of the constraints of
the age that was set by the mother. In a
scenario where Oliver would like to talk
to Justin he must receive approval from
his parents. In this scenario Mary in
order to do so. This is creating a shield
online that parents can control for their
children cryptographically. What we will
now do is we will move on to another
example of how social media can be
leveraged. We will move on to another
leveraged. We've had a couple of
conversations with social media platforms
as well as game development houses and we
were trying to establish proof of concept
leveraging decentralized identity and the
very common feedback we received was
decentralized identity is too complex to
integrate into gaming. Games must have
centralized servers and the very common
feedback. We have centralized servers and
the very common feedback we have
centralized servers. The identity systems
must be centralized in the platform to
ensure the game and user experience is
maintained. So although the concept and
the idea behind decentralized identity is
powerful and they understood the value it
could bring their statement was you simply
cannot integrate this comprehensive
technology. So I set this task upon my
team to do exactly that. So what we have
done is we have cloned roadblocks. We are
calling it KERI blocks. We did this in
less than two weeks. We did this in less
than two weeks. Just to give you an
understanding of the timeframe here. We
are not game developers by any means. And
what you will see is Oliver is now going
to register and log into this platform in
the exact same way leveraging a credential
that was issued to him by his mother in
order to play this game online. And all of
those constraints and restrictions that
are embedded inside the credential will
also pertain to his usage of this game
platform. So Oliver will join the system
and we he will begin gameplay. And there
are a number of elements here I would like
to touch upon. The level of predatory
engagement that is happening in in-game
chat is a significant concern. What you
have now demonstrated today on screen is
the ability to have age verification built
into a game. This is a complete KERI and
ACDC based chat integration into KERI
blocks. All of these communications are
digitally signed and the age of the
individuals that can communicate with
Oliver must fall within those constraints
that were set in the credential. Another
huge element to in-game concerns is
purchases. Many times parents will input
their credit card information to purchase
something that time and what has happened
is that they will be able to have racked
up their credit card bills. Children have
racked up credit card bills because that
information is in the game. The children
can click on things and purchase them and
mom and dad only find out once the bill
arrives. In the exact same way that Oliver
had to request permission to speak to
someone who was outside of the age
constraints, mom and dad also have to
approve the purchase. Again, this is a
completely new paradigm shift in in-game
purchases and parental controls for
individuals leveraging online systems. The
next one to two minutes of what you're
about to see is the potential future for
the users that are leveraging Roblox.
There are 20 to 40 million users a day
leveraging this system. There is a huge
opportunity here from a commercial
perspective but there is a huge risk that
can be solved with this technology.
Let's see if the sound works.
Okay. Okay. Sounds not working, but that's
okay. Go ahead. Do it one more time. Okay.
Secure, portable, and self-sovereign.
Using this identity, you can create your
own rules and trusted circles with
cryptographic proof. Set age limits for
your private space. Define your play hours
or grant access only to friends you have
personally approved. In KERI blocks, you
don't just build worlds. You build the
rules that govern them, creating a
provably safe and personalized gaming
experience. Developed by Veridian and
integrated with notblocks.online! KERI
blocks redefines how we play in a
connected world. So, I leave you here with
a thought. To the parents and guardians in
the audience and viewing online today, if
you could choose from this safe, secure,
friendly gaming experience for your
children, or you can take a gamble and
leverage the systems that are available
today, what choice would you make? Thank
you very much for your time. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you.
Thank you.
I'm Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild Wild
in her life. These are some of the things
that actually can do it in real time. And
so when a grandparent actually imagine a
future where a grandparent doesn't need to
use username and passwords. They just grab
their phone, push on an apps, log in, and
they can actually see all of their assets,
all of their ability to pay things, all of
the things that they own, all the
contacts. And it's actually managed by
someone that's given guardianship rights
from an organization like a state to be
able to help manage that grandparent.
Maybe it's a accounts. Maybe it's paying
bills. Maybe it's paying different
vendors. Maybe it's different assets and
how to pass them from one generation to
another. Maybe it's currencies. Maybe it's
the ability to actually manage contacts,
not just for your child, but also for
grandparents. There's a lot of confusion
when people get into that environment. And
then the ability to actually take these
types of things and actually drop from one
environment to another to actually make it
easy for them to pay. So if you wanted to
pay a utility bill or you wanted to pay a
grandchild, it's all integrated and
simple. It's all integrated and simple. So
that's a good example of a grandparent
type guardianship reality with a simple
app that you can pull down, log in today
and actually start using these types of
things. It also works with children. So
the ability for children to be able to be
managed from what apps are they using to
what sites are they going to. There's a
lot of functionality and opportunities
there. So I just want to say thank you for
those specifically Sam Smith, Phil
Windley, these are people that have
dedicated their lives to solving this
problem. Tim, I mean this is real. And
this is a nucleus here in Utah that we can
actually make a real difference. But
ultimately, it's actually all of you that
have said this is a problem that I want to
learn about and a problem that I want to
be able to be a part of the solution in
the future. So thank you for coming and
thank you for actually understanding
what's happening here in Utah. But it's
really the world. It's a problem that
society has a responsibility in our
generation. Like when all of us were born.
Like when all of us were born, we didn't
have the cell phones. We didn't have the
internet. And when we pass on, we've got
to pass on a better legacy than what's
currently there. So thank you for Chris
and all the hard work that he does to put
this together and those at the state that
truly are aligning with this effort.
Because I know it's not easy to put these
parts and pieces together. When we went
and searched the world, we could not find
a body like this. We went to the
government in the DC. We went here. We
went. It's just amazing to see the heart,
the alignment to support someone like
Cindy who 10 years ago lost a son. That's
real in this university. That young man
went to this university 10 years ago. And
here we are. So thank you for being here
and understanding some of these concepts.
!
I think
I should stay on our site to stay on site
to stay on site to stay on site to stay on
site to stay on site to stay on site to
stay on site to stay on site to stay on
stay on site to stay on site
Thank you. All right. My name is Steve
McCown and I am a commissioner on the Utah
Privacy Commission. I'm also chief
architect of Anonomy Labs. And I'd like to
talk to you about surveillance and
tracking today and what SEDI does to get
in the way of that. Years ago, I worked
for the US Department of Energy as
basically a computer hacker. And one of my
assignments was to work on compromising
cell phones. Another part of my assignment
was what they call open source
intelligence. And this is the collection
and analysis of data gathered from open
sources, think internet, and in order to
produce actionable intelligence. And in
that capacity, I was able to be given
target sites and pull together enough
information from the internet that
resulted in classified reports. So the
first, I wanted to look and see when the
first open source intelligence was taking
place. And this is January of 1862. A
publication called Harper's Weekly was
publishing articles about force movements
during the US Civil War. And as you can
see here, the text talks about a general's
expeditions and where the troops were
going, what assets he had. And while the
specific targets were secret, they also
were able to surmise where they were
going, they went so far as to draw
pictures of the target locations and the
forces attacking the other forces. In
modern times, let's talk about
surveillance for modern times. So how do
email marketers know when to call you? So
sometimes, and this happened to me
personally, I was reading an email and
within five minutes of reading the email,
I received a call from from the sender of
the sender of the sender of the email. And
I engaged them in conversation to find out
how they were doing this. Here's an
example, one of many examples of what we
call tracking beacons. So what they'll do,
an email is simply like a webpage. It's an
HTML-based email these days. And they'll
put a one-by-one pixel transparent image
on there. And for those of you who know
HTML, HTML, HTML, there's a little tag
called image that's supposed to load an
actual image. And instead of loading an
image, what it does is it contacts the
internet and pings a web service. And that
web service can do a variety of things.
And you can add a variety of information,
username, email address, GPS location,
whatever you can get your handle, whatever
you can get a hold of and your email
client allows, you can then send that off.
So that's a modern example of open source
intelligence. And this leads us into what
we call surveillance capitalism, which is
a concept in political economics which
denotes the widespread collection and
commodification of personal data by
corporations. It's not limited to
corporations. Governments can do this too
and there can be collaboration between the
two. A couple of interesting points about
surveillance surveillance capitalism is
that it operates without meaningful
mechanisms of consent. It just happens to
you. And you can lose your self
-determination through the manipulation of
advertising and other practices that might
happen as a result of this. Duke
University with West Point University with
the Army, they did a study back in 2023
about data brokers and the sale of data
brokers and the sale of data on US
military personnel. So data brokers using
these kinds of methods were able to
collect sufficient information that it
became of interest to foreign entities.
And so as part of the study, they were
able to approach the data brokers
originating from either US domains or dot
Asia domains and purchase information on
US service members and veterans. And when
they ordered in bulk, it was about 12 to
32 cents per record that you could get on
US military members. Think of all the
things we do on social media and how that
might be used as we heard this morning for
blackmail in order to invoke espionage.
This is a real problem, yet it's also the
way the web kind of operates these days.
Their recommendations were federal privacy
legislation and also to restrict the data
on current and how that might
be used as we have to protect our
identity. So one of the things if you look
back to SB 260, it says in a couple of
lines in here, the state endorsed digital
identity enables an individual to
selectively disclose elements of an
individual's identity. So taking the
driver's license as an individual's
identity. So taking the driver's license
as an example, when you go to a government
entity, say the Department of Motor
Vehicles, you don't really have an
expectation of privacy. You're going there
to give your information in order to get a
driver's license credential. So we don't
really have an expectation of privacy in
that regard just by the nature of that
interaction. However, when we go to the
bank, you don't need to give your height
and your weight and your donor status and
your donor status and all that kind of
stuff. And so you can selectively disclose
what the bank requires. Then if you go
shopping on Amazon or somewhere other than
payment information, they need your name
and they need your address to ship
whatever it is you're buying. They don't
need your driver's license number. And so
over the summer, Apple has allowed MDLs to
be used for website logins and that may
create some very unintended side effects
about the transfer of information.
Another aspect of SB260 is asserting with
zero correlation. So part of the one of
the lines in that bill says verify that
the individual's age satisfies an age
requirement without revealing the
individual's age or date of birth. So for
example, if I were to go to the Department
of Alcoholic Beverage Services, which is
where you buy liquor here in Utah, the
assertion you need to make is I'm 21 or
older. That's what's required in the law.
You don't have to give your name, your
address, or any other information. There
should be a way to give only the
information that is required. And that's
what SEDI is after. So when I go to a
concert at the Delta Center and I want to
use that neat, fancy digital ticket,
digital ticket, digital ticket, digital
ticket, I need to be able to assert that I
purchased a ticket, that I'm authorized to
get in having paid my money and so forth
without having to give all the other
information that may sometimes come with
digital credentials. I want this to be a
process of least disclosure, not full
disclosure. Now when I go to the hardware
store as a veteran myself, I'm offered a
10% discount and I get that by scanning
everything on my driver's license. That
includes obviously that I am a veteran
which is on my status. It includes whether
I'm a donor, my height, my weight, my
address, all these things that are
unnecessary for that transaction. So SEDI
gives you a choice. Here's a quote from
the US Supreme Court from back in 1995. It
says, anonymity is a shield from the
tyranny of the majority. It thus
exemplifies the purpose behind the Bill of
Rights and the First Amendment in
particular to protect unpopular
individuals from retaliation at the hand
of an intolerant society. Now whether
you're on the left or the right, this
should resonate with you maybe for
different reasons. But this is a really
important principle because if we don't
enable you to disclose only the right,
this should not enable you to disclose
only the information that's required in an
untrackable sense in some situations, what
we will end up with is what Scott McNeely
from Sun Microsystems said back in 1999,
you have zero privacy anyway, get over it.
And so SEDI is giving you the choice of
what you disclose and when you disclose it
and they put that choice in the hands of
the holder. So that's what I would hope
that you would take away with and you
would go back to your respective
companies, departments and states and pose
this to your constituents because we want
a private identity system that keeps
individuals safe. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
I can be honest. I can be honest. I can be
honest. I can be honest. I can be honest.
I can be honest.
I can be honest. I can be honest. I can be
honest. I can be honest. I can be honest.
honest!
I Thank you. Okay. Good afternoon all.
Apologies for being your remote speaker of
the day. Unfortunately, I couldn't get
across from the UK to join for this. But
I'd like to spend the next 10 minutes
looking at something slightly different in
terms of the presentations that have
happened so far. We've heard an awful lot
today about what SEDI can protect from the
fraud, making sure everything is assured,
making sure we have the assertions, making
sure child age verification and adult age
verification can put in place. I'd like to
spend a few minutes looking at the flip
side of that and looking at economic
benefit as a result of a state-endorsed
digital identity and what can be achieved
there and bring forwards a proof point to
show that this has happened and the sort
of values that can be expected from that.
So, Simon Wood, I've been involved in
identity systems for a long time now. Most
recently, Group CEO of Ubisecure.
Ubisecure is a UK company but deploys a
lot in the Nordics. Ubisecure has deployed
a number of platforms in a number of
platforms in Finland and Sweden and the
case studies taken from there. One of the
things I'd just like to touch on before
getting into that is a differentiator that
McKinsey makes on digital identity versus
advanced identity. Everything that has
been spoken about today, I would say falls
in that advanced identity category as
defined by McKinsey. In the UK, we're
obviously reeling at the moment from the
brick card announcements and so on. And
the McKinsey report is often rolled out as
one of the values for having an identity
and it's referred to as digital identity
in the general sense. But if you read that
report in detail, you'll see that to
benefit from the advanced capabilities and
the returns and the GDP increases that are
positioned there specifically for the US
and for the UK, it needs to be advanced
identity which brings in additional
attributes, additional information and
additional features as well. You've
already seen a number of demonstrations of
those today in a SEDI context and that's
what we're looking at here. We're looking
at those advanced capabilities beyond just
authentication and authorization which is
McKinsey's classical definition of digital
identity. I want to run you through a very
quick scenario. You've seen a couple of
diagrams like this already today where we
have a chain of delegation. Ficknish's
example here, we'll look at setting up a
new company in Utah. So the CEO of that
company to be contacts the Utah Division
of Corporate Corporations goes online and
uses their SEDI identity to register that
company. The Utah Division of Corporations
automatically passes that across to the
state tax commission because there will be
taxes to pay and collect from that
organization and the tax commission will
send a request back to the CEO using let's
assume that there's a secure main box
capability from a SEDI implementation so
you can securely contact people who have
that identity and a request of that tax
registration. The CEO will obviously go to
that website register to submit the taxes
but then the CEO themselves will not be
undertaking that work. They will delegate
that capability to the CFO of the
organization. So that delegation will be
done through the website. The CEO will
invite the CFO to that system using their
SEDI identity as well. And so a delegation
chain is built. You've seen examples of
such a delegation chain already in a
couple of the demos that have been
delivered today. But if we consider
consider that tax is reasonably complex,
you might have three different types of
sales tax, corporation tax, employment
tax, maybe the employment tax is
outsourced to an organization. So that
organization can be invited in and
delegated to the administrator in the
organization can pick that up and then
onwards delegate to an internal
accountant. So we've got a chain of
delegations running through individuals
and organizations using an identity that's
highly assured and available to them. This
delegation chain builds and allows all of
the tax to take place all of the tax to
take place and not once as the state tax
commission being involved in that. They've
just provided that service to allow it to
happen. Now this seems like a great
scenario. If that were true, what would
deliver us? Well, that does happen already
in Finland. There is a platform delivered
in 2008. I believe
so. Are they not coming coming through?
That will help?
How's that?
So just to reiterate that previous slide
so you can see what was there. It's a
delegation chain across individuals and
through an organization there towards the
bottom as we have around here. Chris, I
assume that's coming through now.
Is that okay?
Is that okay? I think that's okay. So this
platform was delivered or it is delivered
in Finland. It's called the Katsio
platform delivered in 2008. 2008. It is a
state-operated platform as opposed to
state-endorsed. Back in 2008, there was
not this distinction and this
understanding of privacy and how important
that is as we acknowledge today. State
-operated platform integrates with the
business registry to generate that link to
the tax office. In 2018, the Finnish
government published stats on the savings
as a result of having that platform. And
when they published that, at that time
there were 450,000 users registered on
there. 420,000 organizations and 104
different online government services using
that platform. One of those services was
the tax office and it worked exactly as I
just described in that delegation chain
that's there. In terms of the stats that
were collected on that, a significant
reduction in physical service points
because everything was online and
everything was driven by the organization
that was registering. They could massively
reduce the physical points of presence.
That allowed them to make a 20% year on
year tax admin staff reduction. That
allowed them to make a 20% year on year
tax admin staff reduction, repurpose them
to more profitable areas and the cost of
servicing the tax transactions when they
went from the old physical base to an
online basis dropped from 35 euros per tax
transaction to 30 euro cents. That's a 99%
reduction in cost per transaction measured
by the Finnish government. That's the
value that they achieved deploying a
highly assured identity that has
delegation capabilities that has the
ability to work across individuals and
organizations.
Within that you've heard me talking about
organizations. Organizations are an
important part of the identity chain.
Incorporating an organization identity
enables the really advanced identity use
cases and that's where we see a lot of the
economic benefit coming from. Now, it
would be wrong to assume that
organizations are just legal entities. We
get a lot of utility and benefit from
lower assurance levels of organizations.
Just like individual identities. Just like
individual identities, there can be low
assurance and high assurance and we see
economic savings at higher assurance
levels. You've heard multiple times today
that SB260 already considers organization
identity in the form of family units and
family structures. That is an
organization. There's no reason not to
have the ability ultimately to extend that
to bring in private sector legal entities
as well to take advantage of that massive
uplift in utility and economic potential
that comes comes from there. So, to
conclude from there. We've seen already
that SEDI has phenomenal potential for
protection for implementing privacy and
for making sure that state citizens, the
public get the protection and the
facilities that they need. But once that's
up and running, then extending that to
organization identity will bring
significant significant benefit as well.
We've seen a significant benefit as well.
We've heard again a number of times that
we shouldn't let private sector define
this and I fully agree. It needs to be run
at the policy level, generating the
privacy that's needed, ensuring that's
first and then bringing utility and
benefit to public sector organizations
afterwards. But incorporating those public
sector organizations and allowing them to
leverage that information and be involved
in there and integrate their platforms and
their systems to that will bring
significant significant benefit. And what
has already happened in the Nordics and in
the Baltics gives very strong proof points
to show what can be done and the level of
savings and level of return that can be
achieved there. I've run through this very
quickly and realize this is remote and a
little bit more complicated but I believe
the slides and this recording will be out
later. So, you can always contact me
afterwards or Chris can put you in contact
and I can provide more information if
that's useful. Thank you very much. Thank
you.
All right. All right. Oh, am I? Oh. It was
today. I was obviously here all day.
Actually, it looked like I missed some
meetings today. So, I assure you, I work
really hard. I really do. All right. This
is actually, I think, going to be the most
exciting part of the day. This is the
final discussion. I am going to ask and we
didn't plan on some chairs. Could we get a
couple chairs just for some of this? We're
actually going to discuss how are we going
to move forward. We have enough brain
power in this room. We have enough
policymaking authority. We have the
ability to create legislation. We had
Senator Kullimore here earlier, our Senate
majority leader. I've already heard
there's going to be discussions happening
with some other state Senate majority
leaders. We have counterparts in states.
We have companies we work with. So, now
the discussion for this last hour before
we leave is how do we move forward? You
never want to have a summit like this
without some outcome and some
deliverables. We have a lot of momentum
built and in order to keep this going, you
don't stop. That's what usually slows
government down is then you go back and
you review. So, the question is how do we
keep the momentum going? I think three
will be good. So, we're going to ask
Representative Cutler to come up and then
is Alan Fuller in here? Alan, if you'll
come up. So, this is we're going to have
we'll just have one mic for us to share
but then the rest of the mics we'll have
some interns around and we want to discuss
what are we doing next? What are our next
action items from our side but then how do
we engage with states to go ahead and get
this consortium going? And then I see the
clock here says 14 minutes but I think
we're just at the end right? So, we have
until four timers, right? Okay. So, let's
actually check.
I think it'd be beneficial if we explain
some of what our next steps are actually
going to be. Alan, do you want to take the
first? Let me just get started by saying
that Senate Bill 260 gave the Department
of Government Operations of which Chris
and I and Marvin Dodge was here are a part
or all are all part of and it tasks us
with coming back to the legislature with a
specific proposal and the input we receive
here and the input we received through a
request for information that we put out
many of you responded to that RFI. Thank
you for for that. We over the next couple
of months are going to be putting together
a proposal to go back to the legislature
for our for our SEDI program going forward
and you know we live in the real world we
have to if we're going to create a system
that's going to have provide identity for
millions of people in the state it has to
be something that works really well as
performant as secure as private and so all
of the principles we've talked about today
need to eventually come together in a real
life system that actually works. If we can
turn over to you represent Cutler. Sure.
One of the thoughts that I have is if is
in order to we can I mentioned this before
we can pass the policy but we need our
industry partners and we need a large
enough coalition that that we have a
critical mass. So what you can do to help
is encourage our industry partners that
you by telling them look I'm interested in
this by telling them look I'm interested
in this or let's work together to get
something done.
Communicating that you're interested in
being part of a critical mass to move this
forward even if even if we don't
necessarily agree on all the finer points
I think is really important and the I
thought the gentleman Steve from the the
blockchain co-inventor that that was real
wisdom that working together even even if
it's not perfect we can make a tremendous
impact so but we can't do this without our
industry partners pushing very very hard
and getting products that we can put in an
alpha phase or a beta phase and start
testing and finding the flaws and finding
the successes.
Two practical things that I think we can
expand here in Utah for the last couple
months we've actually held a private
private sector stakeholder group every
Friday we meet whether we're exhausted or
not to engage with the private sector. I
do think we should expand that to invite
all private sector in other states if you
are ready to participate and you want to
engage you want to help be part of
building the solution we can expand that
and get that set up so you can come and
coordinate and this doesn't have to just
be a Utah stakeholder group this is part
of the SEDI consortium. How do we make
sure everybody's engaged and
participating? we want a diverse set of
ideas you know so long as you love
constitutional rights and but but but I
think you know it we all have a role to
play here and for the private market
there's always going to be money to play
you can bring real value-added services we
don't want government to be doing beyond
the bare minimum of providing a foundation
to protect individuals so this is amazing
for you this is going to be really
disruptive in a good way to move that
money from incumbent players to others
that can help create a more competitive
marketplace so that's one thing we'll do
right away we'll open that up I'll start
on the communication for that and get
invites out set next week I think we had
the National Chamber of Commerce
Foundation here today as well so I'm
assuming you might be able to help us with
that as well how do we get this out to all
the businesses that are part of that the
other thing is now that we're through the
summit we need to go back and start
defining some of those baseline
requirements what is what are the
requirements we're going to compare
technology to and everybody should play a
part in that obviously the RFI is closed
we have a was that a thousand or thirteen
hundred pages to read we have 1200 pages
to read and I know we don't have all the
info we need so we're going to need
everyone to participate to say what
additional requirements are we missing and
then comes the hard work of the technology
needs to prove itself how do you meet the
requirements and then also I think to what
you said earlier the hierarchy of values
that's going to be the hardest part I know
a lot of people in this room are concerned
that we are going to compromise on the
wrong things in the name of
interoperability interoperability and
efficiency so as we define the
requirements we're going to have to create
this hierarchy of values which I have seen
nowhere I think that slide was the first
time I've seen that presented in that way
to have technology value at the highest
level of that constitutional rights so
that's going to be a hard part in the
requirements building list but that's the
type of stuff that's going to build trust
with the public when they see what we are
prioritizing and I think it's going to be
great I think it's actually going to be
great for government trust is at an all
-time low so this is a really good way to
be very transparent to an extreme and let
them know that we really want to protect
them. One of the things I think that we
should talk a lot about is something that
Ryan brought up earlier in his
presentation about the kind of practical
side of rolling something like this of
rolling something like this out and
gaining adoption we need to find a launch
customer that not maybe customer is not
the right word but a launch tenant that
can help us that will pick this up and run
with it maybe in Utah like a Zions Bank or
something like that that will help launch
the whole process and also create the
system in such a way that it incentivizes
use rather than disincentivizing use
rather than disincentivizing use in order
to get adoption. One of the big problems
that we have with our current MDL program
in Utah is that by charging the verifiers
for the verification software it's a
disincentive for them to verify and that
makes it so you got a you got an MDL that
that people can walk around with on their
phone but there's not very many places it
can be used so then you have not very much
adoption and we want to set this up
systematically so that it will have
adoption and incentives to use from the
beginning.
Chris and Alan if people have ideas for
use cases where do they go and I think I'm
thinking back to our experience with
verifiable digital credentials we didn't
start with the most critical key we
started with something easy that that no
one was it wasn't controversial. So I
think maybe there's some lessons learned
here that how do we start this and get
some use cases where we can learn from
before scaling it and what's what are your
thoughts on that process? Well, I was
thinking they should call the legislator.
All the
RFI responses are protected but I think I
can semi quote what was in them. One of
the best ones that I read was it was
actually from an entity that's not looking
to compete. They were just giving advice
of how they could best serve their
customers with this and they said and this
is actually a saying I was in health human
services for seven years before this role.
They said in the RFI response help us meet
the clients where they are meet people
where the use cases are and so they said
you know TSA probably was not the best
example. That's not something that you
know everybody is going to need. But
there's lots of people who have their kids
going to school every year. They need to
enroll and need to have a birth
certificate or immunization records. There
are use cases where we don't have to try
to replicate what's already being done
with MDL and is working and they're
getting traction on that side. What are
other use cases that we can tackle to
tackle other more complex issues that are
a different subset of individuals but it's
meeting people where they are and they're
going to use it and government's great. I
love the saying government can actually do
almost whatever it wants because it's the
only entity that can have a legal
monopoly. So the only thing stopping us
from getting the credentials out to where
they're needed in a secure way and getting
these use cases is I think that's the
legislature. Speaking of the legislature.
You need money. Yeah, if we need money, we
know who to talk to. You know, this is not
just about us talking. We really want to
this is audience participation. I really
wanted to maybe start by asking the
audience some questions. especially can I
start with the legislators in the room.
What do you feel like you've seen today or
what questions do you have coming out of
the conversations today? Would anybody
like to please?
And introduce yourself too.
Okay. Knowledge is power and you know
getting more more of us in the room or you
know legislative trainings, etc. Because
it's hard to vote for something if you're
insecure or ignorant of an issue. You're
less apt to vote for something or even
make any kind of progress if you are
unsure of what you're voting for, which is
a good thing. You don't want your
legislators voting on things that they're
they don't know about. So I think you know
increase you know I see a handful of us
here today. Maybe it's because you know my
colleagues just know all the things but
I've certainly learned a lot today. I
appreciate especially those presenters who
really broke it down into simplistic terms
for me and you know I'm a lot more
comfortable. I was never against not
completely against it but I definitely
feel more comfortable after the things
I've learned today. So I would just say
especially with our lawmakers we need
them. We need us in a room so that
everyone can understand and then make the
decision based on that. And I think that
you know the more people learn the more
comfortable they'll be with the direction
that we're heading. Thank you.
Anyone else? Questions out there? Yeah,
let's open up to everyone. Other thoughts
and…
Thank
you.
Were you the one that was that works with
the Anonomy Labs? Anonomy Labs? No, he's
over there. Steve McCown. So I use my
pseudo and that's yep. Excellent. I was
curious. So you're asking how we can
implement this technology into that. I
mean is this something that's being
implemented into my pseudo? We do a wide
variety of credentials and so we implement
and support a wide variety of current
credentials and so So SEDI is definitely
on our roadmap.
Okay, well that's awesome. And I just
think that this is excellent technology.
My limited understanding so far but I
think from some of the policies that we've
seen get passed the app store
identification forgetting SB whichever one
that was and just a variety of bills that
Utah has passed has been you know for the
children is kind of like the the messaging
push behind it but it's devastating to
internet privacy and anonymity like we've
talked about some of these here in my
opinion and I think that SEDI is one of
the technologies that can bridge that gap
and that can really help us and my
understanding right now it seems like this
is some vital technology. So I just I'm
championing you know everyone here working
on this. It's great. So. Thank you.
Question over here. So maybe not so much a
question. It's just you know you talked
about what use cases and things that you
can do to make it move forward. So Eric
Torgensen. So Eric Torgensen. I'm the
Motor Vehicle Director out of Arizona.
Fantastic conversation and discussion this
week. Thank you very much for today for
putting it on. I think a couple things
that I would just want to say that I think
would be key was one is you know we
already have a great head start on this
with MDL. Right? So somebody early on said
hey let's not worry about the technology
aspect of it. This is really about the
underpinning policies and I will tell you
I've been involved with MDL for the past
10 years almost over 10 years now and I
haven't heard a single thing today that
like butts heads with that technology and
the good news is when we talk about
adoption 60% of the US population is
covered by a state that issues a MDL
today. So we already have it and in
Arizona by the way we have over 1 million
1.2 million MDL issued issued. We have a
population of 5.6 million driver's
licenses out there. Biggest use case is
not TSA. It's the Motor Vehicle Division.
It's state services. We use it now we used
it in a pre part 7 ISO compliant way to do
it but we had it out there. We consume our
own MDL and that became one of the biggest
use cases massive driver for adoption for
us. So something to think about and
something that is in your control as you
look at it is why not use it yourselves?
That's a place where you can control both
sides of the equation and make sure not
only is the provisioning done in a privacy
preserving secure way but the consumption
too and set kind of that example for
everybody else on how to consume it too.
So just a thought. That's terrific and
also let's acknowledge Chris Keras. Chris
if you could raise your hand. He's our the
director of the director of our driver's
license division here in the state of Utah
and has done a terrific job leading our
MDL program. We're grateful for him. I
think Jimmy Higgs is here as well
somewhere. I don't see him at the moment
who will be the next driver's license
division lead after Chris retires. We are
I believe that my expectation and hope and
this was mentioned to me today too from
someone else that likely the states who
are already doing MDL will be the first
adopters of moving to more broad study
because they kind of get it and have
already invested in creating a credential
like that. Let's see. I think I saw a hand
up here. I think it was was it Sarah or
Okay,
we'll go here and then back. Oh, yeah,
Amelia, please. Yeah, I know that I've
obviously been working on this with you
guys for years. Introduce yourself,
Amelia. My name is Amelia Powers Gardner.
I'm a county commissioner. I'm a county
commissioner in Utah County and I've been
working on decentralized ID and self
-sovereign identity since 2019 pre-COVID.
And, you know, as I look for as a county
commissioner in the fastest growing county
in the state or 43.6% of the state's
growth as I'm starting to look at capital
projects and building brick and mortar to
the tune of tens of millions of dollars
because of for a growing population, the
sooner we can get these services you know,
instituted in a way that we can start
utilizing them to deliver services to our
citizens in a secure private way. That
prevents me from having to spend millions
of dollars. And so my question comes in
like I know we've got the groundwork, but
I mean, you know me, I'm like rock. I want
to run first. I want to run first and then
I want to walk and then I want to crawl
on. We do need backwards compatibility,
but when are we going to have the ability
for an organization like mine that has
already done some of this work? Like, when
are we going to start adopting this? When
are we going to start adopting this on a
broad scale? Like when do I start getting
the schema and the requirements so that I
can start implementing this for my
citizens so that I can deliver services to
my citizens without having to spend tens
of millions of dollars building brick and
mortar buildings? Was that chastising us,
Amelia? I'm joking. Now, wait. Yeah. Yeah.
So, there's a lot actually going on in
Utah for those that are from other states
and just, you know, we work with Amelia
all the time. So, we've had this
discussion. For every state, you actually
have a unique opportunity right now. Every
state nationwide is pretty much non
-compliant with their records management
and data governance laws. And Amelia is
shaking her head, but this is the
opportunity. So, when I say that, what I
mean is you all have antiquated laws from
the 70s and 80s that require certain
things like disposal of data according to
retention schedules. Most systems have not
been created to dispose of data. Most
states haven't established the purpose and
use of data. Most states haven't been
giving privacy notices. And that sounds
really bad, but the great thing about it
means there needs to be a modernization
anyway over the next decade. And so,
you're in the unique spot of because you
know there's non-compliance. And I'll
actually I'll share out after if one of my
team can take a note. We had interns over
the summer actually research all 50
states' laws to determine where they are
legislation wise. So, you can see where is
your state with privacy, with records
management, with data governance. You'll
know you're non-compliant, but now that
you know what's coming with digital
identity, you know you need data
governance. And now what Amelia mentioned
is the schemas, this concept of what are
the rules? What's the schema? What's the
formats of the data that needs to be
collected? When Amelia is asking what's
the schema, it's hey, when somebody
applies for a building permit, what is the
exact data that the county should be
collecting? What needs to be on the forms?
What needs to be on the forms? They can
automatically ingest it, automate that
process with AI or machine learning, and
then move toward the efficiency that
government can get. So, what I'm saying is
now is actually the perfect time to learn
where you are. You and it takes about a
decade to transform. Utah is about three
years in on this journey. And that's why
we've been modernizing our laws. We've
been getting comprehensive privacy law.
Amelia, but the schemas will come sooner.
We actually have on our team, we're doing
modernization of then the data governance
structures, the rules around the data. How
long can you keep it? What's the legal
basis? What's the purpose and purposes and
uses? We're starting to define what are
the immutable records? Which records are
immutable public permanent records which
make sense to go on a blockchain. These
are the things you need in a schema to
then implement technology correctly. If
you jump right to the technology without
having these things, you end up having to
backtrack. So, I don't know if that's the
answer, but it's coming soon. And the
schemas I think will be very soon. We have
some almost ready. Maybe Sarah? Maybe
Sarah?
Learn from you also share what we are
doing in Colorado and other states so that
we can learn together. I was reflecting on
the statement about MDL and opportunities
around MDL. We recently discovered that
the standard MDL contract with the big
tech wallet companies, Apple, Google,
Samsung in our case, have a clause in them
that says they are sole and exclusive
provisioner and revoker of MDL. And like
that's something I want to share with you
all about like one particular thing
because it does conflict with the SEDI
idea. And so how do we join forces
together and say like, hey, Apple, Google,
let's not have that as the standard
clause. All of us are sort of against that
idea. So, I think that there is an ask
maybe and how can we contribute? It's not
just an ask of you. Can we host it? Can we
do something so that we can do that
knowledge sharing and really accelerate
our co-growth? We will be emailing out
after the summit. One, obviously we had
the white paper of what is SEDI. We have
some resources that we've created of model
legislation, model resolutions, model
executive orders. For us to do a formal
consortium, there should be something you
want your elected officials, governor or
legislature to authorize. We've had this
discussion with our governor and let him
know we wanted to do a consortium, which
is why we've invited you all today. If one
more state for, I mean, we've had a couple
of people reach out and say, actually,
we're very interested. If you can get the
formal approval, we'll start SEDI.gov. And
it's not SEDI.Utah.gov, SEDI.gov. You need
at least two states with formal approval.
And that's where we start building that
multi-state formal consortium. And we can
start then advocating for ourselves and
for our citizens and put these resources
there and we can build it together. there.
More hands over here. Go. Yeah, that
works. Okay. So first of all, thank you.
This is actually turned out very well as
an event. And I think there's been a lot
of really great interest. I always talk
about this as an idea when we talk about
off-Broadway use cases as Representative
Koehler mentioned, but I think the idea of
vital records records is something that is
not so much having anything really
implemented yet. And I always like to say
death records because everyone needs one
one day. Death and taxes are the two
things that they say are inevitable. And
there's a guardianship mechanism and a
burial permit mechanism and a plot of
land. Kind of have everything at once. I
do am the treasurer of a cemetery. So I
would love some funds. We're actually
going to have George McKeown make a
comment about how are we engaging vital
records. The amazing thing actually about
government is once we start saying we want
to do something, it opens doors with all
these organizations. I wasn't anticipating
getting on stage. So one of the things
we've done is we've reached out to Napsis
and I just gave a discussion to their
security and privacy group last week. We
are actually talking about the schema that
they have for a national standard for a
certified birth certificate and their
digital schema. So we have committed that
if they want us to come out to their
December event, we will bring a SEDI
compatible version of that. So they're
close on their standard. We just need to
wrap it in the appropriate cryptography to
make sure that meets the SEDI threshold.
And I think we'll be there. The real goal
will be is in June of next year when they
have their annual event that we'll really
move that forward with them and kind of
codify all that.
One of the this session as we go in to
make recommendations for the SEDI program
and we also need to recommend what would
the next legislation look like. Part of
that does need to be prioritization of
credentials and that's been a very common
ask. How do we get these other value-added
credentials, not just mobile driver's
license or a driving credential, but it
was birth certificate, your immunization
records, your death certificate. And so I
would anticipate that would be part of the
discussion we have this session is not
only do we need to get it out there, but
then we need to work with the group. So we
had I think we had part of the group here
from Health and Human Services today where
vital records is, but I think that is a
low-hanging fruit use case to get out
there. We'd actually love to know what are
you going to use that data for if people
have it, what's the private sector able to
provide value for if you have those
records though? And Scott, I think you had
a question, right? – Oh, sorry. – Three
things. One, excellent day, really
outstanding. Two, incrementalism is
important, but there's a cart and a horse
kind of kind of aspect to this kind of
kind of aspect to this. And so who, how do
you get to trust? And I think that's one
thing that we really need to ask ourselves
in terms of who is trusted to each of us
and if that's our teacher, our professor,
our doctor, our lawyer, our banker. I mean
where that comes in, I think really it
might help you define use cases and how to
go after those early and first. And third,
if you want an example of one state that I
if you went to Hawaii anytime during the
pandemic, Hawaii did a really excellent
job of making sure that they could reopen
their economy, which is tourism, by making
sure that they had the smart health card
for people to come in and show proof. You
had to prove you were vaccinated in order
to visit at that time. And they did a
really great job job of it. People were
motivated of it. People were motivated of
course to fill this out and ID for it. But
it's just one example that you might want
to loop in Hawaii on.
– So listening to all the constituents
here, the challenge I think that we have
here is a scope problem. There's lots of
things that can be done, but the way to
get something done is iterative and it
needs to start with the core of what
you're looking for. It needs to start with
the core of what you're looking for. So
you've done two things. You've said we're
going to have a state endorsed identity.
Okay? And you have a law. So you have two
things to build upon. I think you start
there. What is the state going to do?
Whether you have paper to present to the
state to endorse, but it has to be focused
on the first and foremost thing, which is
how do we issue a state state endorsed
digital identity? And then use cases will
come once you have that established. If
you don't have that established, what's
the SEDI project? So that needs to be the
absolute core and it needs to start with a
risk assessment because there's a million
risks we talk about today, but there are
only certain risks that can be mitigated
by a project like this. And that will
drive the scope of how you can mitigate
the risk to the degree that the state the
state can accept. And you take the law and
all the requirements that you have in the
law and put it in the governance framework
and set of requirements. And at least you
are have momentum. You need to start with
momentum and leadership and others will
come and use cases will come, but it has
to be right down the road for what you've
done. Don't lose focus on that. You have
law to drive a state endorsed digital
identity. Make that law and you have the
means to do it and you have the expertise
in the room here to start for sure.
So Matthew Helstone here from Brigham
Young University and I think transcripts
and educational data is a very complex use
case and been working on this since 2016
with SSI space and we've made a long way
so it's really amazing. But I wanted to
emphasize something that I think about
with decentralized identity is something
that I think about with decentralized
identity I think is important is that just
because we have a credential and a steady
credential doesn't mean we have a
ubiquitous identifier. So we don't want to
have a unique identifier that correlates
us wherever we go. We have the possibility
of using that identifier where we want to
but we can create an ephemeral identifier
with our credential and make a connection
with another entity to present our
information. That's really important that
when we think of our use cases we're not
thinking of I can be correlated wherever
and that's a great user experience and
that may be true but I may not want that
as an individual and the technology needs
to support the privacy policy of me being
able to choose to create an identifier to
present my interface and my information
through. So I want to emphasize that
another thing I wanted to emphasize is
credentials need to be credentials need to
be intentional. They don't have to be
where everything is stored in one
credential, right? I can have a very micro
credential for a specific intended purpose
and the technology stack allows me to take
multiple credentials and draw selective
disclosure information from each of them
and aggregate it into a presentation for
the verifier. So that means as an issuer
of a credential I don't have to solve all
my use cases where I think my credential
is going to be used. I just have to focus
on my data and give that to the individual
and let the verifier define their own data
contract that really empowers them from a
data model perspective of verifier defines
their contract and we can fulfill it from
a number of credentials. We can give an
example of that with our the first
credential and this is what representative
Kutler is referring to is is our off
highway vehicle training certificate which
we put out a verifiable digital credential
for this training certificate to drive
your four-wheeler on the roads. Yeah,
thank you. And we have but it doesn't say
who you are. So you still it doesn't
provide your identity. You have to have
both an identity and this credential to
say you know who you are and that you've
taken the course. Let's see where are we
with our microphones maybe here. Yeah, go
ahead. Yeah, Phil Long from the US Chamber
of Commerce Foundation and T3 Innovation
and T3 Innovation Network. I just want to
bring us back to the actually the first
presentation that was given this morning
by Ryan first who are Ryan yeah that
reminded us that we really need to look at
the the examples of failures of the things
that we're looking at as potential
priorities to try to learn from them
because we we tend to dismiss you know
that was done by them it was done at a
different time perhaps a year ago it may
not be relevant but there are things and
lessons in there that will be extremely
valuable if you look for them. So that's
one thing. The second to reinforce several
of the comments here which is to pick the
two or three to start with that are win
-wins for all of the stakeholders involved
because everybody's going to have
resistance to it at some point in this
early stage. So where you can come up with
one where there's beneficial time savings
for a government office to get something
done that time savings benefits the
individual who's benefits the individual
who's making a request and the benefit of
the credential actually has direct value
to that person for what they're trying to
do. Those combinations are absolutely
critical and I applaud you for doing all
of this. Thank you. Do we still have
Jeremy Grant here? I'm going to steal a
line that he said we can't build identity
or what did he call it? It says we can't
build identity or we're a bunch of
identity weenies building identity for
other identity weenies. And so we can't be
identity nerds trying to build this really
small use case of like yeah it'd be great
to use a verifiable credential to I don't
know Timothy what's a really weird use
case you can probably think of one off
your head. What? Okay. You got it you got
a use case? Which one? Oh yeah. What about
the beekeepers license? Okay. All right.
Beekeepers license. That's a pretty small
use case and does government go and
actually check beekeepers keep your
licenses. So but we have to build identity
for people that it's going to have value
and we have to meet them where they are.
Who how are they going to get value? How
is government going to get some value? And
I think that's also where I said we have
the ability because we are a monopoly to
solve the catch-22 of well let's create
that instance where both can get value and
we're already spending money on it. So
it's let's move those resources to
actually realize the savings that can come
from that. All right. So who has ideas of
how we can work together with other
government entities?
Hello hello my name is Mariano. Mariano
Green. I'm from Mexico City. I'm very glad
to be here with you guys. Even though that
I'm born Mexican-American, I'm more
Mexican than American. I live most of my
life there in Mexico. So I have learned a
lot with you guys how we can implement. We
have been working with clear companies try
to like develop the Mexican the Mexican
environment there and develop the Mexican
environment there. But we came to the
conclusion that it has to be a grassroots
movement. It has to be with the
communities. You know the community has to
endorse their own. So not only the
identity you know like yes the identity
has to be more broad you know but it's
something that this movement has to be
more locally. You know I have been talking
with some of these persons here and a lot
of those persons came to the same
conclusion you know and a lot of those
persons came to the same conclusion you
know and that's that's the way that I
think personally the human being has to
like has to move towards to that because
if not that will happen with
centralization and control power we all
know that. So this idea of stay indoors I
will say it more like community indoors.
That's my grain of salt. I like that
community indoors. One of the I had the
opportunity I think it was as
representative Chevrier still here. She
invited me to speak at one of her events
for Stand for Health Freedom a couple
weeks ago and we had a really interesting
discussion of you mentioned community of
how to decentralize the proofing process
out into the community. A lot of cities
and towns and school districts or even our
post offices are in the community. Do you
need to go essentially to a DMV to do
proofing or can we have lots of entities
doing it? Move it out to the community so
there's more trust because these are their
neighbors that work out there. If you can
standardize the identity verification and
proofing process there's some real low
hanging fruit and we can eliminate some of
those inefficiencies or barriers for
people that can't get it currently and if
you could just go to your local city
recorder or your local treasurer or your
local postal office why don't you have all
the options and that's I think a great way
to get that grassroots going of those
communities that want it. We know Utah
County and some small cities have been
saying we want it if we could build it
bring it out to them. Pat Brooks with the
state of Missouri judiciary.
I'm not sure how many people here are
familiar with the standard called NIME.
Anyone familiar with NIME? NIME is the
national information exchange model and
that started as what was the predecessor
of that was called GJ XDM and that was a
global justice data exchange change model.
And what you're talking about doing here
is following the same path that that
program followed. You have a grassroots
follow along with the gentleman just
before that people had a need to do
something and the standards were
established and not so much in legislation
but in adoption from a technology
perspective to say this is how we can get
the work done. Going back to the comments
of publishing schemas, publishing
standards that people can adopt and the
organization that started that was a multi
-state organization and it was in the
justice domain. And what happened to it
was it saw a need to exchange information
in multiple domains and identity is one of
those domains. And so I would encourage
you to make sure that if we're
establishing a standard for multiple
states to follow that we look at if there
is RA something at the national level that
could be more readily adopted than maybe
building something from total to scratch.
You have governance that you have to
issue. You have to have vitality issues.
You have technology standards. But I think
this is a wonderful idea and I think that
it can be well served to see how others
have done something similar and how others
have done something similar and going
forward.
Michael proper. I have seen this dilemma
that we've been building and sitting upon
for years. Well over a decade actually.
And the solution is right in front of us.
But will we really see it? And what I mean
by that is we know that we've all got to
come together and adopt a system. And we
know that there's a political side of it
and there's a technology side of it. But
what if they really existed? Would you
really adopt them? Would you really use
them? Even if it had the beekeeper
scenario built into it and 86 other
certificates, permits, licenses that
already exist and already use these
standards. would you really use them?
Would you really use them? Would you
really use them? Would you really use it?
Would the state of Utah really use it?
Would the state of Arizona really use it?
Would Mexico really use it? Mexico doesn't
know. It's a community thing. It's the
person that would actually be the ultimate
decision maker if they're going to use it.
That's why MDL has such I think Arizona
has a ton of adoption. 17% adoption. If we
could do that with a decentralized system
where the individual actually will throw.
If we could do the same 20% of MDL energy
into a decentralized system and people
knew about it, the awareness and adoption
would go through the roof because it's
around the individual first. If we want to
be true and honest around what's going on,
Cindy who has a son that's dead is one
very small proof. It's not just a person's
life and their breath and their breath
that's gone. It's their time on earth that
sucked from them from these corporations.
Whether they're slumming around
pornography or they're slumming around
video games that are taking the youth or
we're allowing AI to be able to replicate
and take not just from the next
generation, the grandparents, our parents,
our children. This is our responsibility.
In Hawaii, it's our kuleana. It's our
kuleana. It's our time. And I look at what
Chris and Phil and Sam and Tim, these
people have dedicated decades of their
life. I too, 19 years, $28 million of my
own hard-earned money into this technology
for the state, for the countries, other
countries, for no price. Would you really
adopt it? Would you really look at it?
Because if you do it here and you can do
10% of what we're talking about, other
states will get on board with it. If you
give it back to the individuals and truly
let them own their own identity, their own
data, their own payments, their own
assets, and pass it to the next generation
instead of the state sucking out hundreds
of millions of dollars of unclaimed assets
because people don't even know where they
are. where they are. The technology is
here today. It's not just in some
proprietary phone that's really open. It's
not about a phone. Even though Cindy's
parents, Cindy's son, that's how they took
his life. That's how they stole him. As a
parent of six kids, I want to be able to
say, I did everything that I could so that
my son that went to this university and
when I sat on the board of this
university, when her son killed himself,
was responsible enough to say, you know
what? Enough is enough. We got to stop the
games. We got to come together with the
policy. We got to come together with the
technology. And we have to actually act.
Charlie Kirk was killed 500 feet from
here, 150 feet from here. The action
behind his choice network was all what
it's about. It's about acting. It's about
doing. The technology's here. People have
seen it. People can live it. They can
adopt it. You can download it. Utah life.
Go to your app store, download it, log in.
It's simple. This isn't hypothetical.
These are real systems that really
function better than Bitcoin, better than
Ethereum, better than the banking system,
better than the current identity
management systems. And I'm sorry, I want
to slow down and I want to slow down and I
want to just let the process take its
process. And Chris, I emphatically support
everything that you're doing. But we don't
have time. We don't have another 10 years
for another decade worth of kids to not
only stick bullets in their heads, but to
stick bits in their heads that takes them
away from the life that they've been
given. It steals their time. It steals
their souls. It steals their hearts. It
steals their hearts. I'm sorry that this
means so much to me. But I can see the
solution.
Thank you, Michael. And our timeline is
that 10 years is data governance. Our time
on lists is as fast as we can. Senator
Collin Moore said this on KUTV last week
and he said, we have to say, we have to
get it right. We don't want to cause more
harm, but the time is as fast as we can
get out there. So parents and individuals
have the tool. So that's our timeline and
that's our commitment as we're trying to
get it out as fast as we can. Obviously,
we have to follow the law, but we
understand the importance and that it's
needed now. This is not something that we
want regular bureaucracy to just sit on.
And I think that's why we're all here.
This is not normal bureaucracy. This is
not a normal meeting. This is something
different is happening. This is something
different is happening and this is going
to get done right.
I'm not going to try to follow that, but
my question is for those in the private
sector partners who are helping us, what
can we do to help move this faster?
Understanding that we have to do it right,
but how can we move faster? I think Tim.
Tim.
I've been
working in the space for over a decade
now. It's like trying to push a really
heavy rock uphill really hard. A lot of
failure. A lot of things we tried in
different ways that didn't work. And I'm
very optimistic about SEDI and what's
happening in the state level? I think the
answer, I've always been a small
government guy. And the reality is that
now that government is getting into the
digital identity space, it's several
decades behind private industry and
private industry has turned the digital
identity space into this just incredible
surveillance mechanism. But now
government's getting into the digital
identity space. And government at the end,
you said has the monopoly on whatever it
decides to do. Government will dictate how
much privacy or freedom or autonomy we
have or don't have in the digital realm is
my prediction after all I've seen. So to
answer your question about how to finally
solve this, I think Utah has to be
successful in getting other states and
create momentum. I know that Utah has deep
prioritized interoperability, which is
really interesting when you look at Utah's
hierarchy of values for a lot of identity
initiatives specifically, but technology
in general, the highest priority is
interoperability. And so what gets
sacrificed is security and privacy.
Specifically with the MDL standard, there
was a country that said we need to have
phone home and they didn't call it that we
need to have server retrieval. We need to
have server retrieval and it was baked
into the standard because a country
demanded it. Different culture. It's not
our culture. Someone else's culture
demanded it. It got baked in. A bunch of
us squawked about this a couple few months
ago and they have now separated it
thankfully. But the point is that was made
earlier.
We as Utah need to do what's best for
Utahns if even if it means that we're not
interoperable with the rest of the world.
We have to deprioritize interoperability
and do what's best for the privacy and
security of our citizens. And so what I
think is the answer to your question is to
get Utah to be more than just Utah that's
doing this to get some representatives
from other states who are here to actually
move forward and join. It reminds me of
the end of the movie A Bug's Life where
the grasshoppers were were bullying the
ants through the whole movie and finally
at the very end the ants realize they're
more powerful if they lock arms. I have
this digital identity thing is so big and
I see grasshoppers everywhere who are the
bullies in digital identity and I think
the only way we do it is Utah's an ant and
we need to lock lock arms with other ants
and scare the grasshoppers out of this
space.
My name is Jeremy Furster from Cardano
Foundation in Veridian and I'm going to
say that I'm in the technology a
technologist camp camp or stakeholder
group and normally when speaking to
policymakers there is a view from
technologists that you're way off the mark
with what you're presenting as policy.
However, that is not the case at all when
coming to SEDI and I think the engagement
that you receive and the interest that
you're receiving the reason why it's so
high is because fundamentally the policy
makes sense for the constituents. We've
been able to demonstrate with our demo
that today SEDI is not just policy. It can
be codified. It can be implemented. And I
would ask do you see a path where you can
eat your own dog food? Because when you
look to implement SEDI you need that first
user. A very easy low-hanging fruit could
be having a SEDI wallet to have a
passwordless login to have a passwordless
login to a government website. And if you
do something like this it's very low risk
to actually get things started and have
something put into production that is end
-to-end.
Well, I'm going to make a quick comment
because I actually got some text I get
texts every weekend just you guys know
from citizens that are like I hate this
what are you doing? And they actually sent
a text and you may have been about to go
here where they're going to say hey what
they were like what is this Utah ID I now
need to use to log into a system. It's a
just a single sign-on portal which any
it's any single sign-on system is going to
have tracking. It's a centralized. Yeah,
it's a username password type system. So
there's low hanging fruit and I think
there's discussions already happening. So
we know constituents have identified the
system. They actually have said they want
SEDI on. We have the man here in charge of
it. So we have a couple of initiatives
that we're working on and we have first of
all we have our we have we have in a beta
form our next version citizen portal which
we branded my Utah and you'll probably see
Governor Cox making an announcement about
this early next year but the goal and we
don't have this quite here yet I'm looking
at but we'll we'll be getting there where
we hope to be able to have people
authenticate with a SEDI credential for
that and we don't quite have the SEDI
credential yet to do that but we want it
and so that'll be be one of our first and
best use cases to get that going and we
also want to look at state systems. So we
have our 22,000 state employees and we
have identity and access management that
we log them into our state system and we
like to have a a SEDI credential so that
they can log in as employees and we would
like to move away from passwords even with
our multi-factor we don't love them we'd
like to move to a more secure SEDI type
credential for login and use in identity
and access management systems across the
state hopefully that will be one place we
can start to get rolling.
Hi, I'm Mark Allen. I'm with citizen
portal my brother today ancestor.com and
we're trying to work towards government
transparency and accountability and Chris
you're spot on when you say that most of
the state of Utah is not compliant. I
think our stats show about 15% of public
meetings are being recorded gavel to
gavel. I think some of the low-hanging
fruit that I think some of the low-hanging
fruit that I'd suggest for authentication
and certification would be within your own
home of state government. I have been
branded a vexatious litigant as of last
night but the judge of Charlie Kirk case
because I asked for a court record. Let
that sink in. I asked for a Webex video
hearing.
I can't get anybody in the state of Utah
to give me a certified record. When I'm
doing grammar they say oh it's a duplicate
request. I want state certified
authenticated genuine record that I can
take to the bank and say I'm innocent. But
when I asked for that I get branded a
vexatious litigant. So my admission
admonition as a state and county delegate
is also with what we're doing is clean up
your own house first not at your level but
at the clerk level where they won't give
me a certified record where the keyboard
is the weapon of today and I'm the first
victim probably in the state of Utah of
lawfare and but if I had everything that
you've been talking about today set
ability to authenticate ability to track
back into the record to see who was the
ghost that hit the keyboard word to
backdate the record by two years. I
wouldn't be as smart as I am now but I've
learned a lot in the last 10 years and I'd
say Utah let's get it right first. Let's
start in the judiciary where the problems
are and then my personal identifying
information I can control and protect it
but mine's been scattered to databases
around the world and I don't know how to
undamage what that's been done. We also
have a problem with all three branches of
government in Utah. They're not
watchdogging each other. There's not
enough healthy friction. I'd like to see a
little more healthy friction between
stuff. So and this is not specific SETI
related. It really is civil rights, my
personal protections and I don't need to
go deeper down that because I really
appreciate what you're trying to do. If we
would have had implemented what you did,
what you're talking about 10 years ago, my
life would be totally different. But I've
seen how China weaponizes and surveils.
I've been surveilled in Utah, Provo, Utah.
So court certified records definitions are
really important. What's a certified
record? What does a certified record look
like to you if I go down to the court and
try and get a digital copy or something
that someone will go, oh, this is we made
a mistake. How do we undo the mistake? So
that's a personal use case scenario. But I
think our courts, they don't on a standard
basis do a transcript. You can't get a
certified record unless I pay for it. $2
,500 for me to get a certified record. So
I would start within the court judiciary
and start certifying records and start
doing court transcripts. If it were me,
that's low hanging fruit that would
benefit most of Utah. Thank you, Mark. We
are all right. We're going to have one
more question. We're at time. But Jeremy
Baker is a Utah privacy commissioner. If
you don't know, governance structure in
Utah, we have a whole commission dedicated
to privacy. So take that back to your
state if you don't have one. Go ahead,
Jeremy. So I'm actually going to take this
from a different perspective and this is
from my private sector experience with
being someone that integrates security and
identity into software applications. And
it's related to how do we get the private
sector to adopt this. A lot of private
sector companies like even roblox or
others. They end up using identity
providers like AWS Cognito, Okta, Azure,
B2C. All of those they've added in
different integrations for identities. So
you have like your social media logins
that are allowed in there as well as like
the current adoption of passkeys which has
been really slow to roll out across the
entire private sector even though they're
significantly better idea than passwords
and user names. But to get SEDI adopted
across all of them, I think the framework
like what we've talked about today having
an open framework where those major
identity providers could bring that
integration in as an authentication
service under the umbrella to have it as
an option to add directly into
applications that are currently working
with their products. I think that would be
be a significant push for adoption. Thank
you, Jeremy. Okay, we're going to close up
first by raise of hands who wants to help
get SEDI going forward. Okay, and if it's
not up, okay, everyone got it up. I and
that was the worst thing to do because I
am shameless. One of my tricks in
government is I have no problem asking for
your time. So you will all be getting
calls in your states to move this forward
and we'll be shameless together to take
this national. We are so thankful that
everyone came today. I know this is a long
day and this was a lot of information but
you now are ready to actually have the in
-depth discussions. So we will go back.
We'll do some of the grunt work to get
organized. We'll set up and we'll make our
materials available. We'll reach out to
the states to get at least one more
formally involved so we can get SEDI.gov
going going at SEDI.Utah.gov doesn't have
the same you know ring to it. We want SEDI
.gov. But we'll get rolling on that and
we're going to meet back here again in
less than six months for the next SEDI
summit and from what we're already hearing
it's probably going to be twice as big and
by that point with the pace we're going
not only we have more legislation but
hopefully we have a lot more to share so
other states can take it steal from our
tax dollars and take it to your state so
you don't have to pay for it and let's get
SEDI rolling. So thank you everyone.
Thanks Brian. Brian Thank you.
Thank you.